<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2022 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="application" name="NXapm" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="n_ions">
            <doc>
                 Total number of ions collected.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_dld_wires">
            <doc>
                 Total number of independent wires in the delay-line detector.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_support">
            <doc>
                 Number of support points for e.g. modeling peaks.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_ivec_max">
            <doc>
                 Maximum number of allowed atoms per (molecular) ion (fragment).
                 Needs to match maximum_number_of_atoms_per_molecular_ion.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_ranges">
            <doc>
                 Number of mass-to-charge-state-ratio intervals of this ion type.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_x">
            <doc>
                 Number of bins in the x direction.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_y">
            <doc>
                 Number of bins in the y direction.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_z">
            <doc>
                 Number of bins in the z direction.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_bins">
            <doc>
                 Number of bins.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Application definition for atom probe and field ion microscopy experiments.
    </doc>
    <group type="NXentry" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <attribute name="version">
            <doc>
                 An at least as strong as SHA256 hashvalue of the file
                 that specifies the application definition.
            </doc>
        </attribute>
        <field name="definition">
            <doc>
                 NeXus NXDL schema to which this file conforms.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="NXapm"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="experiment_identifier">
            <doc>
                 Ideally, a (globally) unique persistent identifier
                 for referring to this experiment.
                 
                 The identifier is usually defined/issued by the facility, laboratory,
                 or the principle investigator. The identifier enables to link
                 experiments to e.g. proposals.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="experiment_description" optional="true">
            <doc>
                 Free-text description about the experiment.
                 
                 Users are strongly advised to detail the sample history in the 
                 respective field and fill rather as completely as possible the fields
                 of the application definition behind instead of filling in these
                 details into the experiment_description free-text description field.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME" recommended="true">
            <doc>
                 ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information
                 included when the microscope session started.
                 If the application demands that time codes in this section of the
                 application definition should only be used for specifying when the
                 experiment was performed - and the exact duration is not relevant
                 - this start_time field should be used.
                 
                 Often though it is useful to specify a time interval with specifying
                 both start_time and end_time to allow for more detailed bookkeeping
                 and interpretation of the experiment. The user should be aware that
                 even with having both dates specified, it may not be possible
                 to infer how long the experiment took or for how long data
                 were collected.
                 
                 More detailed timing data over the course of the experiment have to be
                 collected to compute this event chain during the experiment.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME" recommended="true">
            <doc>
                 ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC included
                 when the microscope session ended.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="program">
            <doc>
                 Commercial or otherwise given name to the program which was used
                 to create the original results file of the atom probe experiment.
                 This file and program should not be confused with downstream
                 processing operations and file format conversion tasks.
                 
                 Atom probe microscopy experiments are except for still very much cases
                 controlled via commercial software. Such software is designed as an
                 integrated acquisition and instrument control software.
                 
                 For AMETEK/Cameca local electrode atom probe (LEAP) instruments the
                 least processed (rawest) numerical results and metadata are stored
                 in so-called RHIT and HITS files, which are proprietary and the
                 specifications of which are not publicly documented.
                 
                 Supplementary metadata are kept in a database which is connected
                 to the instrument control software and synced with the experiment
                 while signal is being detected. In effect, RHIT and HITS files
                 store the (rawest) experiment data in a closed manner that is
                 practically useless for users unless they have access to the
                 commercial software.
                 
                 To arrive at a state that atom probe microscopy (APM) with LEAP instruments
                 delivers a dataset with which users can study reconstructed atomic
                 position and do e.g. composition analyses or other post-processing
                 analysis tasks, these raw data have to be processed. Therefore, it is
                 necessary that for an application definition to be useful, details about
                 the physical acquisition of the raw data and all its
                 processing steps have to be stored.
                 
                 With this a user can create derived quantities like ion hit positions
                 (on the detector) and calibrated time-of-flight data. These derived
                 quantities are also needed to obtain calibrated mass-to-charge-state
                 ratios, and finally the tomographic reconstruction of the ion positions.
                 
                 In most cases, an APM dataset is useful only if it gets post-processed
                 via so-called ranging. Ranging defines rules for mapping time-of-flight
                 and mass-to-charge-state ratio values on ion species. This is post-processing
                 even though in practice it is performed sometimes already (as preview)
                 already while data are still being collected.
                 
                 The ion types decode molecular identities which can very often be
                 mapped to elemental identities, and also to resolve isotopes.
                 All these steps are in most cases performed using commercial software.
                 
                 Frequently, though, ranging and post-processing is also performed with
                 (open-source) research software. Therefore, there is strictly speaking
                 not a single program used throughout an atom probe analysis not even
                 for the early stage data acquisition and processing stages to obtain
                 a useful reconstructed and ranged dataset.
                 
                 Therefore, this application definition documents not only the measurement
                 but also the key post-processing steps which transform the proprietary
                 data into a tomographic reconstruction with ranging definitions.
                 
                 Future guidance by the vendors could improve this description to cover
                 a substantial larger number of eventually metadata that so far
                 are not publicly documented and accessible in an open-source manner.
            </doc>
            <attribute name="version">
                <doc>
                     Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of an
                     ever persistent resource where the source code of the program and
                     build instructions can be found so that the program can be configured
                     in such a manner that the result file is ideally recreatable
                     yielding the same results.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="run_number">
            <doc>
                 Neither the specimen_name nor the experiment_identifier but the identifier
                 through which the experiment is referred to in the control software.
                 For LEAP instruments it is recommended to use the IVAS/APSuite
                 run_number. For other instruments, such as the one from Stuttgart or
                 Oxcart from Erlangen, or the instruments at GPM in Rouen, use the
                 identifier which is closest in meaning to the LEAP run number.
                 
                 As a destructive microscopy technique, a run can be performed only once.
                 It is possible, however, to interrupt a run and restart data acquisition
                 while still using the same specimen. In this case, each evaporation run
                 needs to be distinguished with different run numbers.
                 We follow this habit of most atom probe groups.
                 
                 This application definition does currently not allow to store the
                 entire set of such interrupted runs to be stored and covered. However,
                 this is not because of a technical limitation within NeXus but
                 because we have not seen a covering use case based on which we could
                 have implemented and conceptualized this. Atom probers are invited to
                 contact the respective people in the FAIRmat team to fix this.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <group name="experiment_documentation" type="NXnote" optional="true">
            <doc>
                 Binary container for a file or a compressed collection of files which
                 can be used to add further descriptions and details to the experiment.
                 The container can hold a compressed archive.
                 
                 Required for operation_mode apt_fim or other to give further details.
                 Users should not abuse this field to provide free-text information.
                 Instead, these pieces of information should be mapped to
                 respective groups and sections.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <group name="thumbnail" type="NXnote" optional="true">
            <doc>
                 A small image that is representative of the entry; this can be an
                 image taken from the dataset like a thumbnail of a spectrum.
                 A 640 x 480 pixel jpeg image is recommended. 
                 Adding a scale bar to that image is recommended but not required
                 as the main purpose of the thumbnail is to provide e.g. thumbnail
                 images for displaying them in data repositories.
            </doc>
            <attribute name="type"/>
        </group>
        <field name="operation_mode">
            <doc>
                 What type of atom probe microscopy experiment is performed.
                 This field is primarily meant to inform materials database systems
                 to qualitatively filter experiments:
                 
                 * apt are experiments where the analysis_chamber has no imaging gas.  
                   experiment with LEAP instruments are typically performed as apt.  
                 * fim are experiments where the analysis_chamber has an imaging gas,  
                   which should be specified with the atmosphere in the analysis_chamber group.  
                 * apt_fim should be used for combinations of the two imaging modes.  
                 * other should be used in combination with the user specifying details in the  
                   experiment_documentation field.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="apt"/>
                <item value="fim"/>
                <item value="apt_fim"/>
                <item value="other"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <group type="NXuser" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
            <doc>
                 Contact information and eventually details of at least one person
                 involved in the taking of the microscope session. This can be the
                 principle investigator who performed this experiment.
                 Adding multiple users if relevant is recommended.
            </doc>
            <field name="name">
                <doc>
                     Given (first) name and surname of the user.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="affiliation" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Name of the affiliation of the user at the point in time
                     when the experiment was performed.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="address" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Postal address of the affiliation.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="email" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Email address of the user at the point in time when the experiment
                     was performed. Writing the most permanently used email is recommended.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="orcid" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Globally unique identifier of the user as offered by services
                     like ORCID or ResearcherID. If this field is field the specific 
                     service should also be written in orcid_platform
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="orcid_platform" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Name of the OrcID or ResearcherID where the account
                     under orcid is registered.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="telephone_number" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     (Business) (tele)phone number of the user at the point
                     in time when the experiment was performed.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="role" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Which role does the user have in the place and at the point 
                     in time when the experiment was performed? Technician operating
                     the microscope. Student, postdoc, principle investigator, guest
                     are common examples.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="social_media_name" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     Account name that is associated with the user
                     in social media platforms.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="social_media_platform" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     Name of the social media platform where the account
                     under social_media_name is registered.
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="specimen" type="NXsample">
            <field name="name">
                <doc>
                     Descriptive name or ideally (globally) unique persistent identifier.
                     The name distinguishes the specimen from all others and especially the
                     predecessor/origin from where the specimen was cut.
                     In cases where the specimen was e.g. site-specifically cut from
                     samples or in cases of an instrument session during which multiple
                     specimens are loaded, the name has to be descriptive enough to resolve
                     which specimen on e.g. the microtip array was taken.
                     
                     The user is advised to store the details how specimens were
                     cut/prepared from samples in the sample history. This field must
                     not be used for an alias of the specimen. Instead, use short_title.
                     
                     In cases where multiple specimens have been loaded into the microscope
                     the name has to be the specific one, whose results are stored
                     by this NXentry, because a single NXentry should be used only for
                     the characterization of a single specimen in a single continuous run.
                     
                     Details about the specimen preparation should be stored in the
                     sample history.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="sample_history">
                <doc>
                     Ideally, a reference to the location of or a (globally) unique
                     persistent identifier of e.g. another file which should document
                     ideally as many details as possible of the material, its
                     microstructure, and its thermo-chemo-mechanical processing/
                     preparation history.
                     
                     In the case that such a detailed history of the sample/specimen is not
                     available, use this field as a free-text description to specify a
                     sub-set of the entire sample history, i.e. what you would consider
                     as being the key steps and relevant information about the specimen,
                     its material, microstructure, thermo-chemo-mechanical processing
                     state and details of the preparation.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="preparation_date" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
                <doc>
                     ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information
                     when the specimen was prepared.
                     
                     Ideally, report the end of the preparation, i.e. the last known time
                     the measured specimen surface was actively prepared. Usually this
                     should be a part of the sample history, i.e. the sample is imagined
                     handed over for the analysis. At the point it enters the microscope
                     the session starts.
                     
                     Knowing when the specimen was exposed to e.g. specific atmosphere is
                     especially required for environmentally sensitive material such as
                     hydrogen charged specimens or experiments including tracers with a
                     short half time. Further time stamps prior to preparation_date should
                     better be placed in resources which describe the sample_history.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="short_title" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     Possibility to give an abbreviation of the specimen name field.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="atom_types">
                <doc>
                     List of comma-separated elements from the periodic table
                     that are contained in the sample. 
                     If the sample substance has multiple components, all 
                     elements from each component must be included in `atom_types`. 
                     
                     The purpose of the field is to offer materials database systems an
                     opportunity to parse the relevant elements without having to interpret
                     these from the sample history or from other data sources.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="description" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     Discouraged free-text field in case properly designed records
                     for the sample_history are not available.
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group type="NXdata" optional="true">
            <doc>
                 Hard link to a location in the hierarchy of the NeXus file
                 where the data for default plotting are stored.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <group type="NXcoordinate_system_set" recommended="true">
            <doc>
                 Container to hold different coordinate systems conventions.
                 
                 For the specific idea and conventions to use with the
                 NXcoordinate_system_set inspect the description of the
                 NXcoordinate_system_set base class. Specific details for application
                 in atom probe microscopy follow.
                 
                 In this research field scientists distinguish usually several
                 Euclidean coordinate systems (CS):
                 
                 * The laboratory space;  
                   a CS specifying the room where the instrument is located in or  
                   a physical landmark on the instrument, e.g. the direction of the  
                   transfer rod where positive is the direction how the rod  
                   has to be pushed during loading a specimen into the instrument.  
                 * The specimen space;  
                   a CS affixed to either the base or the initial apex of the specimen,  
                   whose z axis points towards the detector.  
                 * The detector space;  
                   a CS affixed to the detector plane whose xy plane is usually in the  
                   detector and whose z axis points towards the specimen.  
                   This is a distorted space with respect to the reconstructed ion  
                   positions.  
                 * The reconstruction space;  
                   a CS in which the reconstructed ion positions are defined.  
                   The orientation depends on the analysis software used.  
                 * Eventually further coordinate systems attached to the  
                   flight path of individual ions might be defined.  
                 
                 Coordinate systems should be right-handed ones.
                 Clockwise rotations should be considered positive rotations.
                 
                 In atom probe microscopy a frequently used choice for the detector
                 space (CS) is discussed with the so-called detector space image
                 (stack). This is a stack of two-dimensional histograms of detected ions
                 within a predefined evaporation ID interval. Typically, the set of
                 ion evaporation sequence IDs is grouped into chunks.
                 
                 For each chunk a histogram of the ion hit positions on the detector
                 is computed. This leaves the possibility for inconsistency between
                 the so-called detector space and the e.g. specimen space.
                 
                 The transformation here resolves this ambiguity by specifying how
                 the positive z-axes of either coordinate systems is oriented.
                 Consult the work of A. J. Breen and B. Gault and team
                 for further details.
            </doc>
            <group name="TRANSFORMATIONS" type="NXtransformations" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        </group>
        <group type="NXmonitor" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <group name="atom_probe" type="NXinstrument">
            <doc>
                 Metadata and numerical data of the atom probe and the lab in which it 
                 stands.
                 
                 An atom probe microscope (experiment) is different compared to a large-
                 scale facility or electron accelerator experiments in at least two ways:
                 
                 * First, ionized atoms and molecular ion(s fragments)  
                   (in the case of atom probe tomography)  
                   and (primarily) imaging gas ions (in the case of field ion  
                   microscopy) are accelerated towards a position-sensitive  
                   and time-of-flight taking detector system.  
                   Hence, there is no real probe/beam.  
                 * Second, the specimen is the lens of the microscope.
            </doc>
            <field name="instrument_name">
                <doc>
                     Given name of the atom probe at the hosting institution. This is an
                     alias. Examples could be LEAP5000, Raptor, Oxcart, one atom at a time,
                     etc.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="location" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     Location of the lab or place where the instrument is installed.
                     Using GEOREF is preferred.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <group type="NXfabrication" recommended="true">
                <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
            </group>
            <field name="flight_path_length" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     The space inside the atom probe along which ions pass nominally
                     when they leave the specimen and travel to the detector.
                     
                     THIS DOCSTRING NEEDS CLARIFICATION.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="field_of_view" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     The nominal diameter of the specimen ROI which is measured in the
                     experiment. It is important to mention that the physical specimen
                     cannot be measured completely because ions may launch but not be
                     detected or hit elsewhere in the analysis_chamber.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <group type="NXreflectron">
                <field name="applied" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Is a reflectron installed and was it used?
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="name" optional="true"/>
                <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                    <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                </group>
                <field name="description" recommended="true"/>
            </group>
            <group name="local_electrode" type="NXlens_em">
                <doc>
                     A local electrode guiding the ion flight path.
                </doc>
                <field name="name">
                    <doc>
                         Identifier of the local_electrode in an e.g. database.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <group type="NXaperture_em" optional="true">
                    <field name="name" recommended="true"/>
                    <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                        <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                        <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                    </group>
                    <field name="value" type="NX_NUMBER" recommended="true"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="ion_detector" type="NXdetector">
                <doc>
                     Detector for taking raw time-of-flight and
                     ion/hit impact positions data.
                </doc>
                <field name="type">
                    <doc>
                         Description of the detector type. Specify if the detector is
                         not the usual type, i.e. not a delay-line detector.
                         In the case the detector is a multi-channel plate/
                         delay line detector, use mcp_dld. In the case the detector is
                         a phosphor CCD use phosphor_ccd. In other case specify
                         the detector type via free-text.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="name" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Given name/alias.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="model" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Given brand or model name by the manufacturer.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="serial_number" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Given hardware name/serial number or hash identifier
                         issued by the manufacturer.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="manufacturer_name" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the manufacturer.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="signal_amplitude" type="NX_FLOAT" optional="true" units="NX_CURRENT">
                    <doc>
                         Amplitude of the signal detected on the multi-channel plate (MCP).
                         
                         This field should be used for storing the signal amplitude quantity
                         within ATO files. The ATO file format is used primarily by the
                         atom probe groups of the GPM in Rouen, France.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="pulser" type="NXpulser_apm">
                <field name="pulse_mode"/>
                <field name="pulse_frequency" type="NX_FLOAT"/>
                <field name="pulse_fraction" type="NX_FLOAT"/>
                <field name="pulsed_voltage" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true"/>
                <field name="standing_voltage" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true"/>
                <group name="laser_gun" type="NXsource" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="2">
                    <doc>
                         Atom probe microscopes use controlled laser, voltage, or a
                         combination of pulsing strategies to trigger the excitation
                         and eventual field evaporation/emission of an ion during
                         an experiment.
                         If pulse_mode is set to laser or laser_and_voltage (e.g. for
                         LEAP6000-type instruments) having the group/section laser_gun
                         is required and the following of its fields have to be filled:
                         
                         * name  
                         * wavelength  
                         * energy
                    </doc>
                    <field name="name"/>
                    <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                        <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                        <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                        <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                        <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                    </group>
                    <field name="wavelength" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="power" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="pulse_energy" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true"/>
                </group>
                <group name="laser_beam" type="NXbeam" recommended="true">
                    <group name="pinhole_position" type="NXcollection" recommended="true"/>
                    <group name="spot_position" type="NXcollection" recommended="true"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="stage_lab" type="NXstage_lab">
                <field name="base_temperature" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_TEMPERATURE">
                    <doc>
                         Average temperature at the specimen base, i.e.
                         base_temperature during the measurement.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="analysis_chamber" type="NXchamber">
                <field name="name" optional="true"/>
                <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                    <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                </group>
                <field name="description" optional="true"/>
                <field name="pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                    <doc>
                         Average pressure in the analysis chamber.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="buffer_chamber" type="NXchamber" optional="true">
                <field name="name" optional="true"/>
                <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                    <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                </group>
                <field name="description" optional="true"/>
                <field name="pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                    <doc>
                         Average pressure in the buffer chamber.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="load_lock_chamber" type="NXchamber" optional="true">
                <field name="name" optional="true"/>
                <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                    <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                </group>
                <field name="description" optional="true"/>
                <field name="pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                    <doc>
                         Average pressure in the load_lock_chamber.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="getter_pump" type="NXpump" optional="true">
                <field name="design" recommended="true"/>
                <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                    <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="roughening_pump" type="NXpump" optional="true">
                <field name="design" recommended="true"/>
                <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                    <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="turbomolecular_pump" type="NXpump" optional="true">
                <field name="design" recommended="true"/>
                <group type="NXfabrication" optional="true">
                    <field name="vendor" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="model" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="identifier" recommended="true"/>
                    <field name="capabilities" optional="true"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="specimen_monitoring" type="NXcollection" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     A place where details about the initial shape of the specimen
                     can be stored. Ideally, here also data about the shape evolution
                     of the specimen can be stored. There are currently very few
                     techniques which can measure the shape evolution:
                     
                     * Correlative electron microscopy coupled with modeling  
                       but this usually takes an interrupted experiment  
                       in which the specimen is transferred, an image taken,  
                       and a new evaporation sequence initiated.  
                       Examples are `I. Mouton et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927618016161&gt;`_  
                       and `C. Fletcher &lt;https://doi.org/10.1088/1361-6463/abaaa6&gt;`_.  
                     * Another method, which is less accurate though, is to monitor  
                       the specimen evolution via the in-built camera system  
                       (if available) in the instrument.  
                     * Another method is to use correlated scanning force microscopy  
                       methods like reported in `C. Fleischmann &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2018.08.010&gt;`_.  
                     * A continuous monitoring of the specimen in a   
                       correlative electron microscopy/atom probe experiment  
                       is planned to be developed by `T. Kelly et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927620022205&gt;`_  
                       Nothing can be said about the outcome of this research yet but  
                       here is where such spatio-temporally data could be stored.
                </doc>
                <field name="initial_radius" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                    <doc>
                         Ideally measured or best elaborated guess of the
                         initial radius of the specimen.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="shank_angle" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANGLE">
                    <doc>
                         Ideally measured or best elaborated guess of the shank angle.
                         This is a measure of the specimen taper. Define it in such a way
                         that the base of the specimen is modelled as a conical frustrum so
                         that the shank angle is the (shortest) angle between the specimen
                         space z-axis and a vector on the lateral surface of the cone.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="detection_rate" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_DIMENSIONLESS">
                    <doc>
                         Average detection rate over the course of the experiment.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="control_software" type="NXcollection">
                <doc>
                     The majority of atom probe microscopes come from a
                     single commercial manufacturer `AMETEK (formerly Cameca) &lt;https://www.atomprobe.com&gt;`_.
                     Their instruments are controlled via an(/a set) of integrated
                     instrument control system(s) (APSuite/IVAS/DAVis).
                     
                     By contrast, instruments which were built by individual
                     research groups such as of the French (GPM, Rouen, France),
                     the Schmitz (Inspico, Stuttgart, Germany),
                     the Felfer (Oxcart, Erlangen, Germany),
                     the Northwestern (D. Isheim, Seidman group et al.),
                     or the PNNL group (Pacific Northwest National Laborary,
                     Portland, Oregon, U.S.) have other solutions
                     to control the instrument.
                     
                     Some of which are modularized and open,
                     some of which realize also integrated control units with
                     portions of eventually undisclosed source code and
                     (so far) lacking (support of)/open APIs.
                     
                     Currently, there is no accepted/implemented
                     community-specific API for getting finely granularized
                     access to such control settings.
                     
                     These considerations motivated the design of the NXapm
                     application definition in that it stores quantities in NXcollection.
                     groups to begin with. Holding heterogeneous, not yet standardized
                     but relevant pieces of information is the purpose of this collection.
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Name of the control software of the microscope 
                         used during acquisition (e.g. IVAS/APSuite).
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of an
                             ever persistent resource where the source code of the program and
                             build instructions can be found so that the program can be configured
                             in such a manner that the result file is ideally recreatable
                             yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <group name="buffer_chamber" type="NXcollection" optional="true">
                    <doc>
                         Track time-dependent details over the course of the measurement about the
                         buffer_chamber.
                    </doc>
                </group>
                <group name="load_lock_chamber" type="NXcollection" optional="true">
                    <doc>
                         Track time-dependent details over the course of the measurement about the
                         load_lock_chamber.
                    </doc>
                </group>
                <group name="analysis_chamber" type="NXcollection" optional="true">
                    <doc>
                         Track time-dependent details over the course of the measurement about the
                         analysis_chamber.
                    </doc>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="ion_impact_positions" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Details about where ions hit the ion_detector and data processing
                     steps related to analog-to-digital conversion of detector signals
                     into ion hit positions. For AMETEK LEAP instruments this processing
                     takes place partly in the control unit of the detector partly
                     in the software. The process is controlled by the acquisition/
                     instrument control software (IVAS/APSuite/DAVis).
                     The exact details are not documented by AMETEK in an open manner.
                     For instruments built by individual research groups,
                     like the Oxcart instrument, individual timing data from the
                     delay-line detector are openly accessible.
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                         Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                         processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                             an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                             and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                             configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                             recreatable yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <field name="arrival_time_pairs" type="NX_NUMBER" recommended="true" units="NX_TIME">
                    <doc>
                         Raw readings from the analog-to-digital-converter
                         timing circuits of the detector wires.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="3">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                        <dim index="2" value="n_dld_wires"/>
                        <dim index="3" value="2"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
                <field name="hit_positions" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                    <doc>
                         Evaluated ion impact coordinates at the detector
                         (either as computed from the arrival time data
                         or as reported by the control software).
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="2">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                        <dim index="2" value="2"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="hit_multiplicity" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Data post-processing step which is, like the impact position analyses,
                     usually executed in the integrated control software. This processing
                     yields how many ions were detected with each pulse.
                     
                     It is possible that multiple ions evaporate and hit the same or
                     different pixels of the detector on the same pulse.
                     These data form the basis to analyses of the so-called
                     (hit) multiplicity of an ion.
                     
                     Multiplicity must not be confused with how many atoms 
                     f the same element or isotope, respectively, a molecular
                     ion contains (which is instead encoded with the
                     isotope_vector field of each NXion instance).
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                         Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                         processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                             an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program 
                             and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                             configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                             recreatable yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <field name="pulses_since_last_ion" type="NX_UINT" recommended="true" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                    <doc>
                         Number of pulses since the last detected ion pulse.
                         For multi-hit records, after the first record, this is zero.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
                <field name="pulse_id" type="NX_UINT" optional="true" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                    <doc>
                         Number of pulses since the start of the atom probe
                         run/evaporation sequence.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
                <field name="hit_multiplicity" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                    <doc>
                         Hit multiplicity.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="ion_filtering" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Like impact position and hit multiplicity computations,
                     ion filtering is a data post-processing step with which users
                     identify which of the detected ions should be included
                     in the voltage-and-bowl correction.
                     This post-processing is usually performed via GUI interaction
                     in the reconstruction pipeline of IVAS/APSuite.
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                         Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                         processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                             an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                             and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                             configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                             recreatable yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <field name="evaporation_id_included" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Bitmask which is set to true if the ion 
                         is considered and false otherwise.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="voltage_and_bowl_correction" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Data post-processing step to correct for ion impact
                     position flight path differences, detector biases,
                     and nonlinearities. This step is usually performed
                     with commercial software.
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                         Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                         processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                             an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                             and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                             configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                             recreatable yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <field name="raw_tof" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true" units="NX_TIME">
                    <doc>
                         Raw time-of-flight data as read out from the acquisition software
                         if these data are available and accessible.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
                <field name="calibrated_tof" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_TIME">
                    <doc>
                         Calibrated time-of-flight.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
                <group name="tof_calibration" type="NXcollection" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         The key idea and algorithm of the voltage-and-bowl correction is
                         qualitatively similar for instruments of different manufacturers
                         or research groups.
                         
                         Specific differences exists though in the form of different
                         calibration models. For now we do not wish to resolve or
                         generalize these differences. Rather the purpose of this collection
                         is to provide a container where model-specific parameters
                         and calibration models can be stored if users know these
                         for sure.
                         
                         For AMETEK LEAP instruments this should be the place for
                         storing initial calibration values. These values are
                         accessible normally only by AMETEK service engineers.
                         They use these for calibrating the detector and instrument.
                         
                         Users can also use this NXcollection for storing the
                         iteratively identified calibrations which scientists
                         will see displayed in e.g. APSuite while they execute
                         the voltage-and-bowl correction as a part of the
                         reconstruction pipeline in APSuite.
                    </doc>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="mass_to_charge_conversion" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Data post-processing step in which calibrated time-of-flight data
                     (ToF) are interpreted into mass-to-charge-state ratios.
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                         Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                         processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                             an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                             and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                             configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                             recreatable yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <group name="parameter" type="NXcollection" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Store vendor-specific calibration models here (if available).
                    </doc>
                </group>
                <field name="mass_to_charge" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
                    <doc>
                         Mass-to-charge-state ratio values.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="1">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="reconstruction" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Data post-processing step to create a tomographic reconstruction
                     of the specimen based on selected calibrated ion hit positions,
                     the evaporation sequence, and voltage curve data.
                     Very often scientists use own software scripts according to
                     published procedures, so-called reconstruction protocols,
                     i.e. numerical recipes how to compute x, y, z atomic positions
                     from the input data.
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                         Similar comments as voltage_and_bowl_correction apply.
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                             an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                             and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                             configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                             recreatable yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <field name="protocol_name">
                    <doc>
                         Qualitative statement about which reconstruction protocol was used.
                    </doc>
                    <enumeration>
                        <item value="bas"/>
                        <item value="geiser"/>
                        <item value="gault"/>
                        <item value="cameca"/>
                        <item value="other"/>
                    </enumeration>
                </field>
                <field name="parameter">
                    <doc>
                         Different reconstruction protocols exist. Although these approaches
                         are qualitatively similar, each protocol uses different parameters
                         (and interprets these differently). The source code to IVAS/APSuite
                         is not open. For now users should store reconstruction parameter
                         in a collection.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="crystallographic_calibration">
                    <doc>
                         Different strategies for crystallographic calibration of the
                         reconstruction are possible. The field is required and details
                         should be specified in free-text at least. If the not crystallographic
                         calibration was performed the field should be filled with the n/a,
                         meaning not applied.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="reconstructed_positions" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                    <doc>
                         Three-dimensional reconstructed positions of the ions.
                         Interleaved array of x, y, z positions in the specimen space.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="2">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_ions"/>
                        <dim index="2" value="3"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
                <group name="naive_point_cloud_density_map" type="NXprocess">
                    <doc>
                         To get a first overview of the reconstructed dataset,
                         the format conversion computes a simple 3d histogram
                         of the ion density using one nanometer cubic bins without
                         applying smoothening algorithms on this histogram.
                    </doc>
                    <field name="program">
                        <doc>
                             Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                             Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                             processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="version">
                            <doc>
                                 Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                                 an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                                 and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                                 configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                                 recreatable yielding the same results.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                    <group type="NXdata">
                        <doc>
                             A default three-dimensional histogram of the total
                             number of ions in each bin obtained via using a rectangular
                             transfer function.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="signal"/>
                        <attribute name="axes"/>
                        <attribute name="AXISNAME_indices"/>
                        <field name="title"/>
                        <field name="data_counts" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                            <doc>
                                 Array of counts for each bin.
                            </doc>
                            <dimensions rank="3">
                                <dim index="1" value="n_z"/>
                                <dim index="2" value="n_y"/>
                                <dim index="3" value="n_x"/>
                            </dimensions>
                        </field>
                        <field name="axis_z" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                            <doc>
                                 Bin center of mass position along the z axis.
                            </doc>
                            <dimensions rank="1">
                                <dim index="1" value="n_z"/>
                            </dimensions>
                            <attribute name="long_name"/>
                        </field>
                        <field name="axis_y" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                            <doc>
                                 Bin center of mass position along the y axis.
                            </doc>
                            <dimensions rank="1">
                                <dim index="1" value="n_y"/>
                            </dimensions>
                            <attribute name="long_name"/>
                        </field>
                        <field name="axis_x" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                            <doc>
                                 Bin center of mass position along the x axis.
                            </doc>
                            <dimensions rank="1">
                                <dim index="1" value="n_x"/>
                            </dimensions>
                            <attribute name="long_name"/>
                        </field>
                    </group>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="ranging" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Data post-processing step in which elemental, isotopic,
                     and/or molecular identities are assigned to the ions.
                     The documentation of these steps is based on ideas
                     described in the literature:
                     
                     * `M. K. Miller &lt;https://doi.org/10.1002/sia.1719&gt;`_  
                     * `D. Haley et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927620024290&gt;`_  
                     * `M. Khbach et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927621012241&gt;`_
                </doc>
                <field name="program">
                    <doc>
                         Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                         Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                         processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                    </doc>
                    <attribute name="version">
                        <doc>
                             Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                             an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                             and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                             configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                             recreatable yielding the same results.
                        </doc>
                    </attribute>
                </field>
                <field name="number_of_ion_types" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                    <doc>
                         How many ion types are distinguished.
                         If no ranging was performed each ion is of the special unknown type.
                         The iontype ID of this unknown type is 0 which is a reserve value.
                         Consequently, iontypes start counting from 1.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="maximum_number_of_atoms_per_molecular_ion" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                    <doc>
                         Assumed maximum value that suffices to store all relevant
                         molecular ions, even the most complicated ones.
                         Currently a value of 32 is used.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <group name="mass_to_charge_distribution" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies the computation of the mass-to-charge histogram.
                         Usually mass-to-charge values are studied as an ensemble quantity,
                         specifically these values are binned.
                         This (NXprocess) stores the settings of this binning.
                    </doc>
                    <field name="program">
                        <doc>
                             Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                             Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                             processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="version">
                            <doc>
                                 Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                                 an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                                 and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                                 configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                                 recreatable yielding the same results.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                    <field name="range_minmax" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
                        <doc>
                             Smallest and largest mass-to-charge-state ratio value.
                        </doc>
                        <dimensions rank="1">
                            <dim index="1" value="2"/>
                        </dimensions>
                    </field>
                    <field name="range_increment" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
                        <doc>
                             Binning width of the mass-to-charge-state ratio values.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <group name="mass_spectrum" type="NXdata">
                        <doc>
                             A default histogram aka mass spectrum of
                             the mass-to-charge-state ratio values.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="signal"/>
                        <attribute name="axes"/>
                        <attribute name="AXISNAME_indices"/>
                        <field name="title"/>
                        <field name="data_counts" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                            <doc>
                                 Array of counts for each bin.
                            </doc>
                            <dimensions rank="1">
                                <dim index="1" value="n_bins"/>
                            </dimensions>
                            <attribute name="long_name"/>
                        </field>
                        <field name="axis_mass_to_charge" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
                            <doc>
                                 Right boundary of each mass-to-charge-state ratio value bin.
                            </doc>
                            <dimensions rank="1">
                                <dim index="1" value="n_bins"/>
                            </dimensions>
                            <attribute name="long_name"/>
                        </field>
                    </group>
                </group>
                <group name="background_quantification" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Details of the background model which was used to
                         correct the total counts per bin into counts.
                    </doc>
                    <field name="program">
                        <doc>
                             Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                             Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                             processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="version">
                            <doc>
                                 Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                                 an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                                 and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                                 configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                                 recreatable yielding the same results.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                </group>
                <group name="peak_search_and_deconvolution" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         How where peaks in the background-corrected in the histogram
                         of mass-to-charge-state ratio values identified?
                    </doc>
                    <field name="program">
                        <doc>
                             Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                             Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                             processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="version">
                            <doc>
                                 Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                                 an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                                 and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                                 configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                                 recreatable yielding the same results.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                    <group type="NXpeak" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                        <field name="label" recommended="true"/>
                        <field name="peak_model">
                            <doc>
                                 THIS DOCSTRING NEEDS CLARIFICATION.
                            </doc>
                        </field>
                    </group>
                </group>
                <group name="peak_identification" type="NXprocess" recommended="true">
                    <doc>
                         Details about how peaks, with taking into account
                         error models, were interpreted as ion types or not.
                    </doc>
                    <field name="program">
                        <doc>
                             Given name of the program that was used to perform this computation.
                             Apart from the classical approach to use AMETEK software for this
                             processing step, a number of open-source alternative tools exists.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="version">
                            <doc>
                                 Program version plus build number, commit hash, or description of
                                 an ever persistent resource where the source code of the program
                                 and build instructions can be found so that the program can be
                                 configured in such a manner that the result file is ideally
                                 recreatable yielding the same results.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                    <group type="NXion" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="256">
                        <field name="isotope_vector" type="NX_UINT"/>
                        <field name="charge_state" type="NX_INT"/>
                        <field name="mass_to_charge_range" type="NX_FLOAT"/>
                        <field name="nuclid_list" type="NX_UINT" recommended="true"/>
                        <field name="name" recommended="true"/>
                    </group>
                </group>
            </group>
        </group>
    </group>
</definition>
