<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2025 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXapm_msr" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="p">
            <doc>
                 Number of pulses collected in between start_time and end_time
                 resolved by an instance of :ref:`NXevent_data_apm`.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Base class for collecting a session with a real atom probe or field-ion microscope.
         
         Workflows used during experiments or simulations of atom probe and related field-evaporation
         research should be documented in more detail and be better contextualized not only because of
         ongoing developments and the tighter becoming connection between atom probe and other
         methods for material characterization foremost electron microscopy (see `T. Kelly et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927620022205&gt;`_, `C. Fleischmann et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2018.08.010&gt;`_, `W. Windl et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1093/micmic/ozad067.294&gt;`_, `C. Freysoldt et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.124.176801&gt;`_, or `G. da Costa et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-54169-2&gt;`_ to mention but a few). 
         To arrive at a design of base classes and an application definition which can be used for both real and simulated atom probe experiments,
         it is worthwhile to recall concepts that are related to events and (molecular) ions:
         
         * Pulsing events which are used to trigger ion extraction events.
         * Physical events and corresponding signal triggered by an ion hitting the detector.
           Some of these events are not necessarily caused by or directly correlated with an identifiable pulsing event.
         * Processed ion hits which are the result of an algorithm that took the physical and pulsing events as input
           and qualified some of these events as to be of sufficiently high quality to call them (molecular) ions that are
           wortwhile to be considered further and eventually included in the reconstructed volume.
         * Calibration and signal filtering steps applied to these processed ion hits as input which results in actually
           selected (molecular) ions based on which an instance of a reconstruction is created.
         * Correlation of these ions with a statistics and theoretical model of mass-to-charge-state ratio values
           and charge states of the (molecular) ions to substantiate that some of these ions can be considered
           as rangable ions and hence an iontype can be assigned to these via running peak finding algorithms
           and subsequent peak labeling. In the field of atom probe this these peak identification methods
           are known as ranging definitions.
         
         Not only in AMETEK/Cameca's IVAS/APSuite software, which the majority of atom probers use, these concepts
         are well distinguished. However, the algorithms used to transform correlations between pulses and physical events
         into actual events (detector hits) ions is a proprietary one - the so-called hit finding algorithm.
         
         Due to this practical inaccessibility of details, virtually all atom probe studies currently use a reporting scheme
         where the course of the specimen evaporation is documented such that quantities are a function of evaporation identifier
         i.e. actual event/ion, i.e. after having the hit finding algorithm and correlations applied.
         That is evaporation_identifier values take the role of an implicit time and course of the experiment given that
         ion extraction physically is a sequential process.
         
         There is a number of research groups who build own instruments and share different aspects of their technical
         specifications and approaches how they apply data processing (e.g. `M. Monajem et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927622003397&gt;`_, `P. Stender et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927621013982&gt;`_ , or `I. Dimkou et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1093/micmic/ozac051&gt;`_ to name but a few).
         Despite some of these activities embrace practices of open-source development, they use essentially the same
         workflow that has been proposed by AMETEK/Cameca and its forerunner company Imago: A graphical user interface
         software is used to explore and thus analyze reconstructed atom probe datasets.
         
         Specifically, software is used to correlate and interpret pulsing and physical events into processed ion hits.
         Some of these ion hits are reported as (molecular) ions with ranged iontypes to yield a dataset based on which
         scientific conclusions about the characterized material volume are made. Also here a reconstruction is 
         point cloud that serves as the proxy for the characterized material volume, i.e. the reconstruction is a model.
         
         By contrast, simulations of field-evaporation have the luxury to document the flight path and allow a following of all
         the whereabouts of each ion evaporated if this is desired. This level of detail is currently not characterizable in experiment.
         Thus, there is a divide between schemas describing simulations of atom probe vs measurements of atom probe.
         We argue that this divide can be bridged with realizing the above-mentioned context and the realization that
         similar concepts are used in both research realms with many concepts not only being similar but being exactly the same.
         
         A further argument to support this view is that computer simulations of atom probe usually are compared to reconstructed
         datasets, either to the input configuration that served as the virtual specimen or to a real world atom probe experiment
         and reconstructions computed from these. In both cases, the recorded simulated physical events of simulated ions hitting
         a simulated detector is not the end of the research workflow but typically the input to apply additional algorithms such as
         (spatial) filtering and reconstruction algorithms.
         
         Only the practical need for making ranging definitions is (at least as of now) not as much needed in field-evaporation simulations
         than it is in real world measurements because each ion has a prescribed iontype in the simulation. Be it a specifically charged
         nuclid or a molecular ion whose flight path the simulation resolves.
         Although, in principle simpler though, we have to consider that this is caused by many assumptions made in the simulations.
         Indeed, the multi-scale (time and space) aspects of the challenge that is the simulating of field-evaporation often require
         simplifications because of otherwise too high becoming computing resource demands and existent knowledge gaps
         in how to deal with all quantum physics complexities. Molecular ion dissociation upon flight is one such complexity.
         Also the complexity of simulation setups is typically defined simpler in simulation (e.g. straight flight path assumption)
         than in a measurement with a real instrument. In addition, simulation often also ignore objects and fields in the flight path
         such as local electrodes or physical obstacles and electric fields (controlled or stray fields).
    </doc>
    <group name="instrument" type="NXinstrument">
        <doc>
             Metadata of the atom probe or field-ion microscope instrument, henceforth called
             microscope or instrument, and the lab in which it stands.
        </doc>
        <!--(NXcsg):
  doc: |
    Possibility to include a detailed computational geometry description of the instrument.-->
        <field name="instrument_name" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Given name of the microscope as defined by the hosting lab. This is an alias.
                 Examples could be LEAP6000, Raptor, Oxcart, one atom at a time, etc.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="location" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Location of the lab or place where the instrument is installed.
                 Using GEOREF is preferred.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <group type="NXfabrication"/>
        <group name="reflectron" type="NXobject">
            <doc>
                 Device which reduces ToF differences of ions in ToF experiments.
                 
                 For atom probe the reflectron can be considered an energy compensation device.
                 Such a device can be realized technically for example with a Poschenrieder lens.
                 
                 Consult the following U.S. patents for further details:
                 
                 * 3863068 and 6740872 for the reflectron
                 * 8134119 for the curved reflectron
            </doc>
            <field name="status" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Presence and status of the reflectron.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="present"/>
                    <item value="used"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Given name/alias.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="description" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Free-text field to specify further details about the reflectron.
                     The field can be used to inform e. g. if the reflectron is flat or curved.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="voltage" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
                <doc>
                     The maximum voltage applied to the reflectron, relative to system ground.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <group name="fabrication" type="NXfabrication">
                <doc>
                     Manufacturer metadata that inform about the reflectron
                </doc>
            </group>
            <group type="NXtransformations">
                <doc>
                     Affine transformation(s) which detail where the reflectron is located
                     relative to e.g. the origin of the specimen space reference coordinate
                     system. This group can also be used for specifying how the reflectron
                     is rotated relative to a given axis in the instrument.
                </doc>
            </group>
        </group>
        <group name="decelerate_electrode" type="NXlens_em">
            <doc>
                 A counter electrode of the LEAP 6000 series atom probes.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <!--counter_electrodes being optional WO2016171675A1
see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Einzel_lens for details double einzel lens in the invizo 6000
according to A. Breen (UNSW)-->
        <group name="local_electrode" type="NXlens_em">
            <doc>
                 A local electrode guiding the ion flight path.
                 Also called counter or extraction electrode.
            </doc>
            <field name="voltage" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
                <doc>
                     Acceleration voltage
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <!--but the local_electrode does not really on purpose create a magnetic field,
specific for an electro-magnetic lens is the symmetry of its field
NEW ISSUE: for now keep that we have what is an NXlens_em
NEW ISSUE: APEX MONITOR / LEAP distance monitoring
NEW ISSUE: the definition of flat test data should be included and documented
NEW ISSUE: local electrode, baking strategies, storage-->
        <group name="ion_detector" type="NXdetector">
            <doc>
                 Detector for taking raw time-of-flight and ion/hit impact positions data.
            </doc>
            <field name="mcp_efficiency" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_DIMENSIONLESS">
                <doc>
                     TODO
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="mesh_efficiency" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_DIMENSIONLESS">
                <doc>
                     TODO
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <!--model, serial_number, manufacturer_name all inherited from NXdetector base class-->
        <group name="pulser" type="NXpulser_apm"/>
        <group name="stage" type="NXstage_lab">
            <field name="specimen_temperature" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_TEMPERATURE">
                <doc>
                     CRunHeader.CAnalysis.fSpecimenTemperature
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <!--NEW ISSUE: add NXapm_energy_analyzer, a voltage grid like done in Rouen/GPM-->
        <group name="analysis_chamber" type="NXchamber">
            <field name="flight_path" type="NX_FLOAT" recommended="true" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     The space inside the atom probe along which ions pass nominally
                     when they leave the specimen and travel to the detector.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                <doc>
                     CRunHeader.CLasHeader.fAnalysisPressure
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="buffer_chamber" type="NXchamber"/>
        <group name="load_lock_chamber" type="NXchamber"/>
        <group name="getter_pump" type="NXpump"/>
        <group name="roughening_pump" type="NXpump"/>
        <group name="turbomolecular_pump" type="NXpump"/>
        <field name="comment" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Free text field for additional comments.
            </doc>
        </field>
    </group>
    <field name="status" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             A statement whether the measurement was successful or failed prematurely.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <!--enumeration: [success, failure, unknown]-->
    <group name="event_data" type="NXobject">
        <doc>
             Group to hold instances of :ref:`NXevent_data_apm`.
             
             Which temporal granularity is adequate depends on the situation and research
             question. Using a model which enables a collection of events offers the most
             flexible way to cater for both atom probe experiments or simulation.
             
             To monitor the course of an ion extraction experiment (or simulation)
             it makes sense to track time explicitly via time stamps or implicitly
             via e.g. a clock inside the instrument, such as the clock of the pulser
             and respective pulsing event identifier.
             
             As set and measured quantities typically change over time and we do not
             yet know during the measurement which of the events have associated
             (molecular) ions that will end up in the reconstructed volume, we must not
             document quantities as a function of the evaporated_identifier but as a
             function of the (pulsing) event_identifier.
        </doc>
        <group type="NXevent_data_apm"/>
    </group>
</definition>
