<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXapm_paraprobe_tool_config" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Base class documenting the configuration used for a tool of the paraprobe-toolbox.
         
         The paraprobe-toolbox is a collection of open-source software tools for performing
         efficient analyses of point cloud data where each point can represent atoms or
         (molecular) ions. A key application of the toolbox has been for research in the
         field of Atom Probe Tomography (APT) and related Field Ion Microscopy (FIM):
         
         * `paraprobe-toolbox &lt;https://www.gitlab.com/paraprobe/paraprobe-toolbox&gt;`_
         * `M. Kühbach et al. &lt;https://paraprobe-toolbox.readthedocs.io/en/main/&gt;`_
         
         The toolbox does not replace but complements existent software tools in this
         research field. Given its capabilities of handling points as objects with
         properties and enabling analyses of the spatial arrangement of and inter-
         sections between geometric primitives, the software can equally be used
         for analyzing data in Materials Science and Materials Engineering.
         
         The configuration and results of a run of a tool from the toolbox is documented
         using binary container formats. Currently, paraprobe-toolbox uses the
         Hierarchical Data Format 5 (HDF5).
    </doc>
    <!--sequence_id is inherited from NXprocess-->
    <group type="NXidentifier"/>
    <field name="analysis_identifier" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Internal identifier used by the tool to refer to an analysis (aka simulation
             id).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="description" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Possibility for leaving a free-text description about this analysis.
             
             Although offered here for convenience we strongly encourage to
             parameterize such descriptions as much as possible to support
             reusage and clearer communication.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <!--tool-specific input, examples for definitions for common types of input granularized into this
base class from which tool-specific appdefs inherit-->
    <group name="reconstruction" type="NXserialized">
        <doc>
             Specification of the tomographic reconstruction to use for this analysis.
             
             Typically, reconstructions in the field of atom probe tomography are communicated
             via files which store at least reconstructed ion positions and mass-to-charge-state-ratio
             values. Container files like HDF5 though can store multiple reconstructions.
             Therefore, the position and mass_to_charge concepts point to specific instances
             to use for this analysis.
        </doc>
        <field name="position" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Name of the node which resolves the reconstructed ion position
                 values to use for this analysis.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="mass_to_charge" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Name of the node which resolves the mass-to-charge-state-ratio
                 values to use for this analysis.
            </doc>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="ranging" type="NXserialized">
        <doc>
             Specification of the ranging definitions to use for this analysis.
             
             Ranging is the process of labeling time-of-flight data with so-called iontypes
             (aka ion species). Ideally, iontypes specify the most likely (molecular) ion
             that is assumed to have been evaporated given that its mass-to-charge-state ratio
             lies within the specific mass-to-charge-state-ratio value interval of the iontype.
             
             The so-called UNKNOWNTYPE iontype represents the null model of an ion
             that has not been ranged (for whatever reasons).
             The identifier of this special iontype is always the reserved value 0.
        </doc>
        <field name="ranging_definitions" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Name of the (parent) node directly below which (in the hierarchy)
                 the ranging definition for (molecular) ions are stored.
            </doc>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="surface" type="NXserialized">
        <doc>
             Specification of the triangulated surface mesh to use for this analysis.
             
             Such a surface mesh can be used to define the edge of the reconstructed
             volume to account for finite size effects.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <!--mesh(NX_CHAR):
  doc: |
    Name of the (parent) node directly below which (in the hierarchy)
    an instance of :ref:`NXcg_triangle_set` is stored.-->
    <group name="surface_distance" type="NXserialized">
        <doc>
             Specification of the point-to-triangulated-surface-mesh distances to
             use for this analysis.
        </doc>
        <field name="distance" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the distance values.
                 The tool assumes that the values are stored in the same order as
                 points (ions).
            </doc>
        </field>
    </group>
    <!--filters-->
    <group type="NXspatial_filter"/>
    <group type="NXsubsampling_filter"/>
    <group type="NXmatch_filter"/>
</definition>
