<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="application" type="group" name="NXapm_paraprobe_nanochem_config" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="n_ityp_deloc_cand">
            <doc>
                 How many iontypes does the delocalization filter specify.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_grid">
            <doc>
                 How many grid_resolutions values.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_var">
            <doc>
                 How many kernel_variance values.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_control_pts">
            <doc>
                 How many disjoint control points are defined.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_fct_filter_cand">
            <doc>
                 How many iontypes does the interface meshing iontype filter specify.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_fct_iterations">
            <doc>
                 How many DCOM iterations.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_ivec_max">
            <doc>
                 Maximum number of atoms per molecular ion.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_rois">
            <doc>
                 Number of cylinder ROIs to place for oned_profile if no feature mesh is used.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Application definition for a configuration file of the paraprobe-nanochem tool.
         
         This tool is part of the paraprobe-toolbox. Inspect :ref:`NXapm_paraprobe_tool_config` for details.
    </doc>
    <group type="NXentry" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
        <field name="definition" type="NX_CHAR">
            <attribute name="version" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="NXapm_paraprobe_nanochem_config"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <group name="delocalization" type="NXapm_paraprobe_tool_config" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
            <doc>
                 Discretization and distributing of the ion point cloud on a 3D grid
                 to enable continuum-scale analyses.
                 
                 By default, the tool computes a full kernel density estimation of decomposed
                 ions to create one discretized field for each element.
                 
                 One delocalization task configures a parameter sweep with at least one
                 delocalization. The total number of runs depends on the number of
                 grid_resolution and kernel_variance values. For example, setting two grid_resolutions
                 and three kernel_variance will compute six runs. Two sets of three with the first set using
                 the first grid_resolutions and in sequence the kernel_variance respectively.
            </doc>
            <!-- Although, this uses an efficient multithreaded algorithm the computation is costly.
 Therefore, it can be advantageous for users to load an already computed delocalization.
 This can be achieved with the load_existent option.-->
            <group type="NXidentifier" optional="true"/>
            <field name="analysis_identifier" type="NX_UINT" recommended="true"/>
            <group name="reconstruction" type="NXserialized">
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="position" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="mass_to_charge" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
            <group name="ranging" type="NXserialized">
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="ranging_definitions" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
            <group name="surface" type="NXserialized">
                <doc>
                     A precomputed triangulated surface mesh representing a model (of the surface)
                     of the edge of the dataset. This model can be used to detect and control
                     various sources of bias in the analyses.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="vertices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the array
                         of vertex positions for the triangles in that triangle_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="indices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the array
                         of vertex indices for the triangles in that triangle_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="surface_distance" type="NXserialized" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Distance between each ion and triangulated surface mesh.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="distance" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
            <group name="spatial_filter" type="NXspatial_filter">
                <field name="windowing_method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <group name="hexahedron_set" type="NXcg_hexahedron_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <group name="hexahedra" type="NXcg_face_list_data_structure">
                        <field name="vertices" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    </group>
                </group>
                <group name="cylinder_set" type="NXcg_cylinder_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <field name="center" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="height" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="radii" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                </group>
                <group name="ellipsoid_set" type="NXcg_ellipsoid_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <field name="center" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="half_axes_radii" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="orientation" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                </group>
                <group name="polyhedron_set" type="NXcg_polyhedron_set" optional="true"/>
                <!--TODO-->
                <group name="bitmask" type="NXcs_filter_boolean_mask" optional="true">
                    <field name="number_of_objects" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    <field name="bitdepth" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    <field name="mask" type="NX_UINT"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <!--leave open if scalar or matrix
  dim: (i,)
identifier(NX_UINT):-->
            <group name="evaporation_id_filter" type="NXsubsampling_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="min_incr_max" type="NX_INT"/>
            </group>
            <group name="iontype_filter" type="NXmatch_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="match" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
            </group>
            <group name="hit_multiplicity_filter" type="NXmatch_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="match" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
            </group>
            <!--config-->
            <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Compute delocalization or load an existent one from input.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="compute"/>
                    <item value="load_existent"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <group name="input" type="NXserialized">
                <doc>
                     Serialized result of an already computed delocalization which is for performance
                     reasons here just loaded and not computed again.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="results" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the group within which
                         individual delocalization results are stored.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <!--TODO: add more descriptions-->
            <field name="nuclide_whitelist" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                     Matrix of nuclides representing how iontypes should be accounted for during
                     the delocalization. This is the most general approach to define if and how many
                     times an ion is to be counted. The tool performs a so-called atomic decomposition
                     of all iontypes, i.e. the tool analyses from how many atoms of each nuclide
                     or element respectively an (molecular) ion is built from.
                     
                     Taking the hydroxonium H3O+ molecular ion as an example:
                     It contains hydrogen and oxygen atoms. The multiplicity of hydrogen
                     is three whereas that of oxygen is one. Therefore, the respective atomic decomposition
                     analysis prior to the iso-surface computation adds three hydrogen counts for each
                     H3O+ ion.
                     
                     This is a practical solution which accepts that on the one hand not every bond is
                     broken during an atom probe experiment but also that ions may react further during
                     their flight to the detector. The exact details depend on the local field conditions,
                     quantum mechanics of possible electron transfer and thus the detailed trajectory
                     of the system and its electronic state.
                     
                     The detection of molecular ions instead of always single atom ions only is the
                     reason that an atom probe experiment tells much about field evaporation physics
                     but also faces an inherent loss of information with respect to the detailed spatial
                     arrangement that is independent of other imprecisions such as effect of limited
                     accuracy of reconstruction protocols and their parameterization.
                     
                     Unused values in each row of the matrix are nullified.
                     Nuclides are identified as hashed nuclide (see :ref:`NXion`) for further details.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="2">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_ityp_deloc_cand"/>
                    <dim index="2" value="n_ivec_max"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
            <field name="grid_resolution" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     Array of edge lengths of the cubic cells used for discretizing the reconstructed dataset
                     on a cuboidal 3D grid (:ref:`NXcg_grid`). The tool performs as many delocalization
                     computations as values are specified in grid_resolution.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_grid"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
            <field name="kernel_size" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                     Half the width of a :math:`{(2 \cdot n + 1)}^3` cubic kernel of cubic voxel
                     beyond which the Gaussian Ansatz function will be truncated. Intensity outside
                     the kernel is factorized into the kernel via a normalization procedure.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="kernel_variance" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     Array of variance values :math:`\sigma` of the Gaussian Ansatz kernel
                     (:math:`\sigma_x := \sigma`, :math:`\sigma_x = \sigma_y = 2 \cdot \sigma_z`).
                     The tool performs as many delocalization computations as values are specified
                     in kernel_variance.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_var"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
            <field name="normalization" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     How should the results of the kernel-density estimation be normalized into quantities.
                     By default, the tool computes the total number (intensity) of ions or elements.
                     Alternatively, the tool can compute the total intensity, the composition,
                     or the concentration of the ions/elements specified by the nuclide_whitelist.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="none"/>
                    <item value="composition"/>
                    <item value="concentration"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <field name="has_scalar_fields" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                <doc>
                     Specifies if the tool should report the delocalization 3D field values.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <group name="isosurfacing" type="NXprocess" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
                <doc>
                     Configuration of the set of iso-surfaces to compute using that delocalization.
                     Such iso-surfaces are the starting point for a reconstruction of so-called objects or
                     (microstructual) features. Examples of scientific relevant are (line features e.g. dislocations
                     poles, surface features such as interfaces, i.e. phase and grain boundaries, or volumetric
                     features such as precipitates.
                     Users should be aware that reconstructed datasets in atom probe are a model and may face
                     inaccuracies and artifacts that can be mistaken incorrectly as microstructural features.
                </doc>
                <field name="edge_method" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         As it is detailed in `M. Kühbach et al. &lt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.13510&gt;`_, the handling of
                         triangles at the surface (edge) of the dataset requires special attention especially for
                         composition-normalized delocalization. Here, it is possible that the composition
                         increases towards the edge of the dataset because the quotient of two numbers
                         that are both smaller than one is larger instead of smaller than the counter.
                         
                         By default, the tool uses a modified marching cubes algorithm of Lewiner et al.
                         which detects if voxels face such a situation. In this case, no triangles are generated
                         for such voxels.
                         
                         Alternatively, keep_edge_triangles instructs the tool to not remove triangles at the
                         edge of the dataset at the cost of bias. When using this keep_edge_triangles users
                         should understand that all features in contact with the edge of the dataset get usually
                         artificial enlarged. Consequently, triangulated surface meshes of these objects are
                         closed during the marching. However, this closure is artificial and can biased shape
                         analyses for those objects. This also holds for such practices that are offered in
                         proprietary software like IVAS / AP Suite. The situation is comparable to analyses
                         of grain shapes via orientation microscopy from electron microscopy or X-ray
                         diffraction tomography. Features at the edge of the dataset may have not been
                         captured fully.
                         
                         Thanks to collaboration with V. V. Rielli and S. Primig from the Sydney atom probe group,
                         paraprobe-nanochem implements a complete pipeline to process features at the edge of the
                         dataset. Specifically, these are modelled and replaced with closed polyhedral objects using
                         an iterative mesh and hole-filling procedures with fairing operations.
                         
                         The tool bookkeeps such objects separately to lead the decision whether or not to
                         consider these objects to the user. Users should be aware that results from fairing operations
                         should be compared to results from analyses where all objects at the edge
                         of the dataset have been removed. Furthermore, users should be careful with overestimating
                         the statistical significance of their dataset especially when using atom probe when they
                         use their atom probe result to compare different descriptors. Even though a dataset may
                         deliver statistically significant results for compositions, this does not necessarily mean that
                         same dataset will also yield statistically significant and insignificantly biased results for
                         3D object analyses!
                         
                         Being able to quantify these effects and making atom probers aware of these subtleties
                         was one of the main reasons why the paraprobe-nanochem tool was implemented.
                    </doc>
                    <enumeration>
                        <item value="default"/>
                        <item value="keep_edge_triangles"/>
                    </enumeration>
                </field>
                <field name="edge_threshold" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                    <doc>
                         The ion-to-surface distance that is used in the analyses of features to identify whether
                         these are laying inside the dataset or close to the surface (edge) of the dataset.
                         
                         If an object has at least one ion with an ion-to-surface-distance below this threshold,
                         the object is considered close to the edge of the dataset. The tool uses a distance-based
                         approach to solve the in general complicated and involved treatment of computing
                         volumetric intersections between closed 2-manifolds that are not necessarily convex.
                         The main practical reason is that such computational geometry analyses face numerical
                         robustness issues as a consequence of which a mesh can be detected as being completely
                         inside another mesh although in reality it is only :math:`\epsilon`-close only, i.e. almost
                         touching only the edge (e.g. from inside).
                         
                         Practically, humans would likely still state in such case that the object is close to the
                         edge of the dataset; however mathematically the object is indeed completely inside.
                         In short, a distance-based approach is rigorous and flexible.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="phi" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
                    <doc>
                         Iso-contour values. For each value, the tool computes an iso-surface and performs
                         subsequent analyses for each iso-surface. The unit depends on the choice for the
                         normalization of the accumulated ion intensity values per voxel:
                         
                         * total, total number of ions, irrespective their iontype
                         * candidates, total number of ions with type in the isotope_whitelist.
                         * composition, candidates but normalized by composition, i.e. at.-%
                         * concentration, candidates but normalized by voxel volume, i.e. ions/nm^3
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_triangle_soup" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report the triangle soup which represents each triangle of the
                         iso-surface complex. The resulting set of triangles is colloquially referred to as a soup
                         because different sub-set may not be connected.
                         
                         Each triangle is reported with an ID specifying to which triangle cluster (with IDs starting at zero)
                         the triangle belongs. The clustering of triangles within the soup is performed with a
                         modified DBScan algorithm.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should analyze for each cluster of triangles how they can be combinatorially
                         processed to describe a closed polyhedron. Such a closed polyhedron (not-necessarily convex!)
                         can be used to describe objects with relevance in the microstructure.
                         
                         Users should be aware that the resulting mesh does not necessarily represent the original precipitate.
                         In fact, inaccuracies in the reconstructed positions cause inaccuracies in all downstream processing
                         operations. Especially the effect on one-dimensional spatial statistics like nearest neighbor correlation
                         functions were discussed in the literature `B. Gault et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927621012952&gt;`_.
                         
                         In continuation of these thoughts, this applies also to reconstructed objects.
                         A well-known example is the discussion of shape deviations of scandium-rich precipitates in aluminium alloys
                         which in reconstructions may appear as ellipsoids although they should be indeed almost spherical
                         provided their size is larger than the atomic length scale.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object_geometry" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report a triangulated surface mesh for each identified closed polyhedron.
                         It is common that a marching cubes algorithm creates iso-surfaces with a fraction of tiny sub-complexes
                         (e.g. small isolated tetrahedra).
                         
                         These can be small tetrahedra/polyhedra about the center of a voxel of the support grid
                         on which marching cubes operates. Such objects may not contain an ion; especially when considering
                         that delocalization procedures smoothen the positions of the ions. Although these small objects are
                         interesting from a numerical point of view, scientists may argue they are not worth to be reported because
                         a microstructural feature should contain at least a few atoms to become relevant.
                         Therefore, paraprobe-nanochem by default does not report closed objects which bound a volume
                         that contains no ion.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object_properties" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report properties of each closed polyhedron, such
                         as volume and other details.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object_obb" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report for each closed polyhedron an approximately optimal bounding box
                         fitted to all triangles of the surface mesh of the object and ion positions inside or on the surface of the mesh.
                         This bounding box informs about the closed object's shape (aspect ratios).
                         
                         Users should be aware that the choice of the algorithm to compute the bounding box can have an
                         effect on aspect ratio statistics. It is known that computing the true optimal bounding box of in 3D
                         is an :math:`\mathcal{O}^3`-time-complex task. The tool uses well-established approximate algorithms
                         of the Computational Geometry Algorithms Library (CGAL).
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object_ions" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report for each closed polyhedron all evaporation IDs of those ions which
                         lay inside or on the boundary of the polyhedron. This information is used by the paraprobe-intersector
                         tool to infer if two objects share common ions, which is then understood as that the two objects intersect.
                         
                         Users should be aware that two arbitrarily closed polyhedra in three-dimensional space can intersect
                         but not share a common ion. In fact, the volume bounded by the polyhedron has sharp edges and flat
                         face(t)s. When taking two objects, an edge of one object may for instance pierce into the surface of
                         another object. In this case the objects partially overlap / intersect volumetrically; however this piercing
                         might be so small or happening in the volume between two reconstructed ion positions. Consequently,
                         sharing ions is a sufficient but not a necessary condition for interpreting (volumetric) intersections
                         between objects.
                         
                         Paraprobe-intersector implements a rigorous alternative to handle such intersections using a tetrahedralization
                         of closed objects. However, in many practical cases, we found through examples that there are polyhedra (especially when they are non-convex and have almost point-like) connected channels, where
                         tetrahedralization libraries have challenges dealing with. In this case, checking intersections
                         via shared_ions is a more practical alternative.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object_edge_contact" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report if a (closed) object has contact with the surface aka edge of the dataset.
                         For this the tool currently inspects if the shortest distance between the set of triangles of the triangulated
                         surface mesh and the triangles of the edge model is larger than edge_threshold.
                         If this is the case, the object is assumed to be deeply embedded in the interior of the dataset.
                         Otherwise, the object is considered to have an edge contact, i.e. it shape is likely affected by the edge.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_proxy" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should analyze a closed polyhedron (aka proxy) for each cluster of triangles whose
                         combinatorial analysis according to has_object returned that the object is not a closed polyhedron.
                         Such proxies are closed via iterative hole-filling, mesh refinement, and fairing operations.
                         
                         Users should be aware that the resulting mesh does not necessarily represent the original feature.
                         In most cases objects, precipitates in atom probe end up as open objects because they have been
                         clipped by the edge of the dataset. Using a proxy is in this case a strategy to still be able to account
                         for these objects. However, users should make themselves familiar with the consequences and
                         potential biases which this can introduce into the analysis.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_proxy_geometry" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Like has_object_geometry but for the proxies.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_proxy_properties" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Like has_object_properties but for the proxies.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_proxy_obb" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Like has_object_obb but for the proxies.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_proxy_ions" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Like has_object_ions but for the proxies.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_proxy_edge_contact" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Like has_object_edge_contact but for the proxies.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object_proxigram" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report for each closed object a (cylindrical) region-of-interest (ROI) that gets
                         placed, centered, and aligned with the local normal for each triangle of the object.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_object_proxigram_edge_contact" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool should report for each ROI that was placed at a triangle of each object if this ROI intersects
                         with the edge the dataset. Currently, the tool supports cylindrical ROIs. A computational geometry test is
                         performed to check for a possible intersection of each ROI with the triangulated surface mesh that is defined
                         via surface. Results of this cylinder-set-of-triangles intersection are interpreted as follows:
                         If the cylinder intersects with at least one triangle of the surface (mesh) the ROI is assumed to make edge contact.
                         Otherwise, the ROI is assumed to make  no edge contact.
                         
                         Users should note that this approach does not work if the ROI is laying completely outside the dataset as also
                         in this case the cylinder intersects with any triangle. However, for atom probe this case is practically irrelevant
                         provided constructions such as alpha shapes or alpha wrappings (such as paraproeb-surfacer does) about the
                         ions of the entire reconstructed volume are used.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
        </group>
        <!--has_object_mesh_smoothing(NX_BOOLEAN):
  doc: Specifies if the tool should post-process each mesh to improve the mesh quality.
mesh_smoothing(NXprocess):
NEW ISSUE: here we need to specify how the meshes were smoothened-->
        <group name="interface_meshing" type="NXapm_paraprobe_tool_config" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
            <doc>
                 Use a principle component analysis (PCA) to mesh a single free-standing interface patch within
                 the reconstructed volume that is decorated by ions of specific iontypes (e.g. solute atoms).
                 
                 Interface_meshing is a typical starting point for the quantification of Gibbsian interfacial excess
                 in cases when closed objects constructed from patches e.g. iso-surfaces are not available or
                 when there is no substantial or consistently oriented concentration gradients across an interface
                 patch. The functionality can also be useful when the amount of latent crystallographic information
                 within the point cloud is insufficient or when combined with interface_meshing based on ion density
                 traces in field-desorption maps (see `Y. Wei et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0225041&gt;`_
                 and `A. Breen et al. &lt;https://github.com/breen-aj/detector&gt;`_ for details).
                 
                 Noteworthy to mention is that the method used is conceptually similar to the work of `Z. Peng et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927618016112&gt;`_ and related work (DCOM algorithm) by `P. Felfer et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2015.06.002&gt;`_. Compared to these implementations
                 paraprobe-nanochem uses inspection functionalities which detect potential geometric
                 inconsistencies or self-interactions of the evolved DCOM mesh.
            </doc>
            <group type="NXidentifier" optional="true"/>
            <field name="analysis_identifier" type="NX_UINT" recommended="true"/>
            <group name="reconstruction" type="NXserialized">
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="position" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="mass_to_charge" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
            <group name="ranging" type="NXserialized">
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="ranging_definitions" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
            <group name="surface" type="NXserialized" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     A precomputed triangulated surface mesh representing a model (of the surface)
                     of the edge of the dataset. This model can be used to detect and control
                     various sources of bias in the analyses.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="vertices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the array
                         of vertex positions for the triangles in that triangle_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="indices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the array
                         of vertex indices for the triangles in that triangle_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="spatial_filter" type="NXspatial_filter">
                <field name="windowing_method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <group name="hexahedron_set" type="NXcg_hexahedron_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <group name="hexahedra" type="NXcg_face_list_data_structure">
                        <field name="vertices" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    </group>
                </group>
                <group name="cylinder_set" type="NXcg_cylinder_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <field name="center" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="height" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="radii" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                </group>
                <group name="ellipsoid_set" type="NXcg_ellipsoid_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <field name="center" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="half_axes_radii" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="orientation" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                </group>
                <group name="polyhedron_set" type="NXcg_polyhedron_set" optional="true"/>
                <!--TODO-->
                <group name="bitmask" type="NXcs_filter_boolean_mask" optional="true">
                    <field name="number_of_objects" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    <field name="bitdepth" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    <field name="mask" type="NX_UINT"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <!--leave open if scalar or matrix
  dim: (i,)
identifier(NX_UINT):-->
            <group name="evaporation_id_filter" type="NXsubsampling_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="min_incr_max" type="NX_INT"/>
            </group>
            <group name="iontype_filter" type="NXmatch_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="match" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
            </group>
            <group name="hit_multiplicity_filter" type="NXmatch_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="match" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
            </group>
            <!--config-->
            <field name="initialization" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     How is the PCA initialized:
                     
                     * default, means based on segregated solutes in the ROI
                     * control_point_file, means based on reading an external list of
                       control points, currently coming from the Leoben APT_Analyzer.
                     
                     The control_point_file is currently expected with a specific format.
                     The Leoben group lead by L. Romaner has developed a GUI tool `A. Reichmann et al. &lt;https://github.com/areichm/APT_analyzer&gt;`_ creates a control_point_file that
                     can be parsed by paraprobe-parmsetup-nanochem to match the here required
                     formatting in control_points.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="default"/>
                    <item value="control_point_file"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <group name="control_point" type="NXserialized">
                <doc>
                     Details about the control point file used.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="control_points" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         X, Y, Z position matrix of disjoint control points.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Method used for identifying and refining the location of the interface. Currently,
                     paraprobe-nanochem implements a PCA followed by an iterative loop of isotropic
                     mesh refinement and DCOM step(s), paired with self-intersection detection.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="pca_plus_dcom"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <group name="decoration_filter" type="NXmatch_filter">
                <doc>
                     Specify those nuclides which the tool should inspect iontypes for if they contain such nuclides.
                     If this is the case ions of such type are taken with the number of nuclides of this multiplicity found.
                     The atoms of these ions are assumed to serve as useful markers for locating the interface and
                     refining the interface mesh.
                </doc>
                <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <enumeration>
                        <item value="whitelist"/>
                    </enumeration>
                </field>
                <field name="match" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                    <doc>
                         Array of nuclide iontypes to filter.
                    </doc>
                    <dimensions rank="2">
                        <dim index="1" value="n_fct_filter_cand"/>
                        <dim index="2" value="n_ivec_max"/>
                    </dimensions>
                </field>
            </group>
            <field name="number_of_iterations" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                     How many times should the DCOM and mesh refinement be applied?
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="target_edge_length" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     Array of decreasing positive not smaller than one nanometer real values
                     which specify how the initial triangles of the mesh should be iteratively
                     refined by edge splitting and related mesh refinement operations.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_fct_iterations"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
            <field name="target_dcom_radius" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     Array of decreasing positive not smaller than one nanometer real values
                     which specify the radius of the spherical region of interest within which the
                     DCOM algorithm decides for each vertex how the vertex might be relocated.
                     
                     The larger it is the DCOM radius in relation to the target_edge_length the more
                     likely it becomes that vertices will be relocated so substantially that triangle
                     self-intersections may occur. The tool detects these and stops in a controlled
                     manner so that the user can repeat the analyses with using a different parameterization.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_fct_iterations"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
            <field name="target_smoothing_step" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                     Array of integers which specify for each DCOM step how many times the mesh
                     should be iteratively smoothened. Users should be aware that all three arrays
                     target_edge_length, target_dcom_radius, and target_smoothing_step are interpreted
                     in the same sequence, i.e. the zeroth entry of each array specifies the respective
                     parameter values to be used in the first DCOM iteration. The first entry of each array
                     those for the second DCOM iteration and so on and so forth.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_fct_iterations"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="oned_profile" type="NXapm_paraprobe_tool_config" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="1">
            <doc>
                 Analysis of one-dimensional profiles in ROIs placed in the dataset.
                 Such analyses are useful for quantifying interfacial excess or for
                 performing classical composition analyses.
                 
                 The tool will test for each ROIs if it is completely embedded in the dataset.
                 Specifically, each such test evaluates if the ROI cuts at least one triangle
                 of the triangulated surface mesh that is referred to by surface.
                 If this is the case the ROI is marked as one close to the surface
                 and not analyzed further. Otherwise, the ROI is marked as one far
                 from the surface and processed further.
                 
                 For each ROI the tool computes atomically decomposed profiles.
                 This means, molecular ions are splitted into nuclides as many times as
                 their respective multiplicity. For each processed ROI the tool stores
                 a sorted list of signed distance values to enable post-processing with
                 other software like e.g. reporter to perform classical
                 Krakauer/Seidman-style interfacial excess analyses.
                 
                 Users should be aware that the latter intersection analysis is not
                 a volumetric intersection analysis. Given that the triangulated mesh
                 referred to in surface is not required to mesh neither a watertight
                 nor convex polyhedron a rigorous testing of volumetric intersection
                 is much more involved. If the mesh is watertight one could use split
                 the task in first tessellating the mesh into convex polyhedra (e.g.
                 tetrahedra and apply a volumetric intersection method like the
                 Gilbert-Johnson-Keerthi algorithm (GJK). In cases when the mesh is not
                 even watertight distance-based segmentation in combination with again
                 intersection of triangles and convex polyhedra is a robust but currently
                 not implemented method to quantify intersections.
            </doc>
            <group type="NXidentifier" optional="true"/>
            <field name="analysis_identifier" type="NX_UINT" recommended="true"/>
            <group name="reconstruction" type="NXserialized">
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="position" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="mass_to_charge" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
            <group name="ranging" type="NXserialized">
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="ranging_definitions" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
            <group name="surface" type="NXserialized" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     A precomputed triangulated surface mesh representing a model (of the surface)
                     of the edge of the dataset. This model can be used to detect and control
                     various sources of bias in the analyses.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="vertices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the array
                         of vertex positions for the triangles in that triangle_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="indices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the array
                         of vertex indices for the triangles in that triangle_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="surface_distance" type="NXserialized" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Distance between each ion and triangulated surface mesh.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="distance" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the distance values.
                         The tool assumes that the values are stored in the same order as
                         points (ions).
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="feature" type="NXserialized" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     A precomputed triangulated mesh of the feature representing a model of the
                     interface at which to place ROIs to profile. This can be the mesh of an
                     interface as returned e.g. by a previous interface_meshing task or the
                     mesh of an iso-surface from a previous delocalization task.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="vertices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute HDF5 path to the dataset that specifies the array of vertex positions.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="indices" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute HDF5 path to the dataset that specifies the array of facet indices
                         which refer to vertices.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="facet_normals" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute HDF5 path to the dataset that  specifies the array of facet signed unit
                         normals.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="vertex_normals" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute HDF5 path to the dataset that specifies the array of vertex signed unit
                         normals.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <!--triangulated surface meshes are only approximations to eventually curved shape of objects
consequently, vertex and facet normals typically differ, the former are typically interpolated
from normals of neighboring facets, type of weighting schemes can affect results quantitatively-->
                <group name="patch_filter" type="NXmatch_filter" optional="true">
                    <doc>
                         If interface_model is isosurface this filter can be used to restrict the analysis to specific
                         patches of an iso-surface.
                    </doc>
                    <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                    <field name="match" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <group name="feature_distance" type="NXserialized" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     To enable an additional filtration of specific parts of the feature
                     mesh it is recommended to feed precomputed distances of each ion to
                     the triangles of the feature mesh.
                </doc>
                <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="path" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="checksum" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="distance" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Absolute path in the (HDF5) file that points to the distance values.
                         The tool assumes that the values are stored in the same order as
                         points (ions).
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="spatial_filter" type="NXspatial_filter">
                <field name="windowing_method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <group name="hexahedron_set" type="NXcg_hexahedron_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <group name="hexahedra" type="NXcg_face_list_data_structure">
                        <field name="vertices" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    </group>
                </group>
                <group name="cylinder_set" type="NXcg_cylinder_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <field name="center" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="height" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="radii" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                </group>
                <group name="ellipsoid_set" type="NXcg_ellipsoid_set" optional="true">
                    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="cardinality" type="NX_POSINT"/>
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <field name="center" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="half_axes_radii" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                    <field name="orientation" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
                </group>
                <group name="polyhedron_set" type="NXcg_polyhedron_set" optional="true"/>
                <!--TODO-->
                <group name="bitmask" type="NXcs_filter_boolean_mask" optional="true">
                    <field name="number_of_objects" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    <field name="bitdepth" type="NX_UINT"/>
                    <field name="mask" type="NX_UINT"/>
                </group>
            </group>
            <!--leave open if scalar or matrix
  dim: (i,)
identifier(NX_UINT):-->
            <group name="evaporation_id_filter" type="NXsubsampling_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="min_incr_max" type="NX_INT"/>
            </group>
            <group name="iontype_filter" type="NXmatch_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="match" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
            </group>
            <group name="hit_multiplicity_filter" type="NXmatch_filter" optional="true">
                <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                <field name="match" type="NX_NUMBER"/>
            </group>
            <!--config-->
            <group name="user_defined_roi" type="NXobject" optional="true">
                <doc>
                     As an alternative mode the tool can be instructed to place ROIs
                     at specific locations into the dataset. This is the programmatic
                     equivalent to the classical approach in atom probe to place ROIs
                     for composition analyses via positioning and rotating them via
                     a graphical user interface (such as in IVAS / AP Suite).
                </doc>
                <group name="cylinder_set" type="NXcg_cylinder_set">
                    <!--dimensionality(NX_POSINT):
cardinality(NX_POSINT):-->
                    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT"/>
                    <field name="center" type="NX_NUMBER">
                        <dimensions rank="2">
                            <dim index="1" value="n_rois"/>
                            <dim index="2" value="3"/>
                        </dimensions>
                    </field>
                    <field name="height" type="NX_NUMBER">
                        <dimensions rank="2">
                            <dim index="1" value="n_rois"/>
                            <dim index="2" value="3"/>
                        </dimensions>
                    </field>
                    <field name="radii" type="NX_NUMBER">
                        <dimensions rank="1">
                            <dim index="1" value="n_rois"/>
                        </dimensions>
                    </field>
                </group>
            </group>
            <!--could add other shapes in the future if necessary
but cylinders are most frequently used-->
            <field name="distancing_model" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Which type of distance should be reported for the profile.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="project_to_triangle_plane"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <field name="roi_orientation" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     For each ROI, along which direction should the cylindrical ROI
                     be oriented if ROIs are placed at triangles of the feature mesh.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="triangle_outer_unit_normal"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <field name="roi_cylinder_height" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     For each ROI, how high (projected onto the cylinder axis) should
                     the cylindrical ROI be if ROIs are placed at triangles
                     of the feature mesh.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="roi_cylinder_radius" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     For each ROI, how wide (in radius) should the cylindrical ROI
                     be if ROIs are placed at triangles of the feature mesh.
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="common" type="NXapm_paraprobe_tool_common">
            <field name="status" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            <group name="programID" type="NXprogram" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                <field name="program" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <attribute name="version" type="NX_CHAR"/>
                </field>
            </group>
            <group name="profiling" type="NXcs_profiling" recommended="true">
                <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME"/>
                <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME"/>
                <field name="total_elapsed_time" type="NX_FLOAT"/>
                <field name="current_working_directory" type="NX_CHAR"/>
            </group>
        </group>
    </group>
</definition>
