<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXapm_paraprobe_tool_common" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Base class documenting the information common to tools of the paraprobe-toolbox.
         
         The paraprobe-toolbox is a collection of open-source tools for performing
         efficient analyses of point cloud data where each point can represent atoms or
         (molecular) ions. A key application of the toolbox has been for research in the
         field of Atom Probe Tomography (APT) and related Field Ion Microscopy (FIM):
         
         * `paraprobe-toolbox &lt;https://www.gitlab.com/paraprobe/paraprobe-toolbox&gt;`_
         * `M. Kühbach et al. &lt;https://paraprobe-toolbox.readthedocs.io/en/main/&gt;`_
         
         The toolbox does not replace but complements existent software tools in this
         research field. Given its capabilities of handling points as objects with
         properties and enabling analyses of the spatial arrangement of and inter-
         sections between geometric primitives, the software can equally be used
         for analyzing data in Materials Science and Materials Engineering.
         
         The common section can be used as a place to store e.g. organizational
         metadata and contextualization of that analysis in a research data
         management system.
    </doc>
    <field name="status" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             A statement whether the tool executable managed to process the analysis
             or whether this failed. Status is written to the results file after the
             end_time beyond which point in time the tool must no longer compute
             any further analysis results but exit.
             
             Only when this status message is present and its value is `success`,
             one should consider the results of the tool. In all other cases it might
             be that the tool has terminated prematurely or another error occurred.
        </doc>
        <enumeration>
            <item value="success"/>
            <item value="failure"/>
        </enumeration>
    </field>
    <group type="NXprogram"/>
    <group type="NXidentifier"/>
    <field name="analysis_identifier" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Internal identifier used by the tool to refer to an analysis (aka simulation
             id).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group name="config" type="NXserialized">
        <doc>
             The configuration file that was used to parameterize
             the algorithms that this tool has executed.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group name="profiling" type="NXcs_profiling">
        <!--results_path(NX_CHAR):
  doc: |
    Path where the tool stores tool-specific results. If not specified,
   results will be stored in the current working directory.-->
        <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
            <doc>
                 ISO 8601 formatted time code with local time zone offset to UTC
                 information included when the analysis in this results file was started,
                 i.e. when the respective executable/tool was started as a process.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
            <doc>
                 ISO 8601 formatted time code with local time zone offset to UTC
                 information included when the analysis in this results file were
                 completed and the respective process of the tool exited.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="total_elapsed_time" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_TIME">
            <doc>
                 Wall-clock time.
            </doc>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group type="NXuser"/>
    <group type="NXcoordinate_system_set">
        <doc>
             Details about coordinate systems (reference frames) used. In atom probe several coordinate
             systems have to be distinguished. Names of instances of such :ref:`NXcoordinate_system`
             should be documented explicitly and doing so by picking from the
             following controlled set of names:
             
             * paraprobe
             * lab
             * specimen
             * laser
             * instrument
             * detector
             * recon
             
             The aim of this convention is to support users with contextualizing which reference frame
             each instance (coordinate system) is. If needed, instances of :ref:`NXtransformations`
             are used to detail the explicit affine transformations whereby one can convert
             representations between different reference frames.
             Inspect :ref:`NXtransformations` for further details.
        </doc>
        <group type="NXcoordinate_system">
            <group type="NXtransformations"/>
        </group>
    </group>
    <!--add further fields coming from using the charge state recovery
workflow from the ifes_apt_tc_data_modeling library-->
</definition>
