<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<definition category="base" extends="NXobject" name="NXcoordinate_system_set" type="group" xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <doc>
         Container to hold different coordinate systems conventions.
         
         By default NeXus uses the McStas coordinate system, whose axis convention 
         is so that the z axis is along the neutron propagation axis, 
         the y axis is vertical up, and the x axis points left when looking along
         the z-axis, completing a right-handed coordinate system.
         Assuming the McStas coordinate system as the reference (indicated by &quot;.&quot;),
         a specific experiment or simulation may defined further coordinate systems.
         
         It is the purpose of this base class to define these conventions and
         offer a place to store mappings between coordinate systems.
         
         For each coordinate system one should use a set of NXtransformations to define:
         * The axis conventions
         * The affine transformations which bring each axis of this coordinate system
         into registration with the McStas coordinate system.
         * Equally affine transformations from the inverse mapping should be specified.
         
         As an example one may take an experiment or computer simulation where
         there is a laboratory (lab) coordinate system, a sample/specimen coordinate
         system, a crystal coordinate system, and additional coordinate systems,
         which are eventually attached to components of the instrument.
         
         If no additional transformation is specified in this group or if an
         instance of an NXcoordinate_system_set is absent it should be assumed the
         McStas coordinate system is used.
    </doc>
    <group type="NXtransformations">
        <doc>
             A group of transformations which specify:
             * Base vectors of a coordinate system.
             * How to map each base vector to the McStas coordinate system.
             * How to map each McStas base vector to the coordinate system,
             i.e. the inverse mapping.
        </doc>
    </group>
</definition>
