<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXcoordinate_system_set" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Base class to hold different coordinate systems and representation conversions.
         
         How many nodes of type :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` should be used in an appdef?
         
         * 0; if no instance of :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` and therein or elsewhere across
           the appdef an instance of NXcoordinate_system is defined,
           the default NeXus `McStas &lt;https://mailman2.mcstas.org/pipermail/mcstas-users/2021q2/001431.html&gt;`_
           coordinate system is assumed. This makes :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` and
           NXcoordinate_system base classes backwards compatible to older
           NeXus conventions and classes.
         * 1; if only one :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` is defined, it should be placed
           as high up in the node hierarchy (ideally right below an instance of NXentry)
           of the application definition tree as possible.
           This :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` should at least define one NXcoordinate_system
           instance which should be called mcstas for the sake of improved clarity.
           Alternatively, at least one NXcoordinate_system member of the set should be
           defined and named such that it is clear how this coordinate system is
           typically referred to in a community. Additional NXcoordinate_system instances
           should be specified if possible in that same :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` instead
           of cluttering them across the tree.
           
           If this is the case, it is assumed that the NXcoordinate_system_members
           overwrite the NeXus default McStas coordinate system, i.e. users can thereby
           conveniently and explicitly specify the coordinate system(s) that
           they wish to use.
           
           Users are encouraged to write also explicit and clean depends_on fields in
           all groups that encode information about where the interpretation of coordinate
           systems is relevant. If these depends_on hints are not provided, it is
           automatically assumed that all children (to arbitrary depth)
           of that branch and sub-branches below the one in which that
           :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` is defined use either the only NXcoordinate_system_set
           instance in that set or the application definition is considered
           underconstrained which should at all costs be avoided and in which case
           again McStas is assumed.
         * 2 and more; as soon as more than one :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` is specified
           somewhere in the tree, different interpretations are possible as to which
           of these coordinate system sets and instances apply or take preference.
           We realize that such ambiguities should at all costs be avoided.
           However, the opportunity for multiple sets and their instances enables to
           have branch-specific coordinate system conventions which could especially
           be useful for deep classes where multiple scientific methods are combined or
           cases where having a definition of global translation and conversion tables
           how to convert between representations in different coordinate systems
           is not desired or available for now.
           We argue that having 2 or more :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` instances and respective
           NXcoordinate_system instances makes the interpretation eventually unnecessary
           complicated. Instead, developers of application definitions should always try
           to work for clarity and thus use only one top-level coordinate system set.
         
         For these reasons we conclude that the option with one top-level
         :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` instance is the preferred choice.
         
         McStas is used if neither an instance of :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` nor an instance
         of NXcoordinate_system is specified. However, even in this case it is better
         to be explicit like for every other coordinate system definition to support
         users with interpreting the content and logic behind every instance of the tree.
         
         How to store coordinate systems inside :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set`?
         Individual coordinate systems should be specified as members of the
         :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set` instance using instances of NXcoordinate_system.
         
         How many individual instances of NXcoordinate_system to allow within one
         instance of :ref:`NXcoordinate_system_set`?
         
         * 0; This case should be avoided for the sake of clarity but this case could
           mean the authors of the definition meant that McStas is used. We conclude,
           McStas is used in this case.
         * 1; Like above-mentioned this case has the advantage that it is explicit
           and faces no ambiguities. However, in reality typically multiple
           coordinate systems have to be mastered especially for complex
           multi-signal modality experiments.
         * 2 or more; If this case is realized, the best practice is that in every
           case where a coordinate system should be referred to the respective class
           has a depends_on field which resolves the possible ambiguities which specific
           coordinate systems is referred to. The benefit of this explicit and clear
           specifying of the coordinate system used in every case is that especially
           in combination with having coordinate systems inside deeper branches
           makes up for a very versatile, backwards compatible, but powerful system
           to express different types of coordinate systems using NeXus.
         
         In effect, 1 should be the preferred choice. However, if more than one coordinate
         system is defined for practical purposes, explicit depends_on fields should
         always guide the user for each group and field which of the coordinate system
         one refers to.
    </doc>
    <group type="NXcoordinate_system"/>
    <!--How to interpret "depends_on" calls for NXtransformations instances which live
within an instance of NXcoordinate_system(_set)?
Depends on cardinality of NXcoordinate_system_set, i.e. how many NXcoordinate_system are defined?
- 0, the root of an NXtransformation chain i.e. "." means McStas
- 1, the root of an NXtransformation chain i.e. "." means "that specific CS" i.e. the one defined by the single instance of NXcoordinate_system in the set
- > 1, "." becomes ambiguous. My suggestion, spell out the name of the specific NXcoordinate_system instance to be used, using "."
  despite all these, a warning should be raised, like a logic warning (and McStas kick in) or an error (i.e. be forbidden) be raised-->
</definition>
