<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2022 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXcoordinate_system_set" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Container to hold different coordinate systems conventions.
         
         It is the purpose of this base class to define these conventions and
         offer a place to store mappings between different coordinate systems
         which are relevant for the interpretation of the data described
         by the application definition and base class instances.
         
         For each Cartesian coordinate system users should use a set of
         NXtransformations:
         
         * These should define the three base vectors.  
         * The location of the origin.  
         * The affine transformations which bring each axis of this coordinate system  
           into registration with the McStas coordinate system.  
         * Equally, affine transformations should be given for the inverse mapping.  
         
         As an example one may take an experiment or computer simulation where
         there is a laboratory (lab) coordinate system, a sample/specimen coordinate
         system, a crystal coordinate system, and additional coordinate systems,
         which are eventually attached to components of the instrument.
         
         If no additional transformation is specified in this group or if an
         instance of an NXcoordinate_system_set is absent it should be assumed
         the so-called McStas coordinate system is used.
         
         Many application definitions in NeXus refer to this `McStas &lt;https://mailman2.mcstas.org/pipermail/mcstas-users/2021q2/001431.html&gt;`_ coordinate system.
         This is a Cartesian coordinate system whose z axis points along the neutron 
         propagation axis. The systems y axis is vertical up, while the x axis points
         left when looking along the z-axis. Thus, McStas is a right-handed coordinate system.
         
         Within each NXtransformations a depends_on section is required. The depends_on
         field specifies if the coordinate system is the root/reference
         (which is indicated by writing &quot;.&quot; in the depends_on section.)
    </doc>
    <group type="NXtransformations">
        <doc>
             A group of transformations which specify:
             
             * Three base vectors of the coordinate system.  
             * Origin of the coordinate system.  
             * A depends_on keyword. Its value can be &quot;.&quot; or the name of an  
               NXtransformations instance which needs to exist in the  
               NXcoordinate_system_set instance.  
             * If the coordinate system is the reference one it has to be named  
               reference.  
             
             In case of having more than one NXtransformations there has to be for  
             each additional coordinate system, i.e. the one not the reference:
             
             * A set of translations and rotations which map each base vector to the reference.  
             * A set of translations and rotations which map each reference base vector  
               to the coordinate system.  
             
             The NXtransformations for these mappings need to be formatted
             according to the descriptions in NXtransformations.
        </doc>
    </group>
</definition>
