<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<!--
`point Electronic GmbH <https://www.pointelectronic.de>`_-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXcomponent_em" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Base class for components used in an electron microscope.
         
         The electron microscope can be a real one or a simulated microscope.
         The key motivation behind this generalization is the observation that in all
         cases a controlled electron beam is generated in reality or that beam is simulated
         and this beam is then used or modified in a controlled manner for the purpose
         of studying physical interaction mechanisms of the beam with matter.
         Here it does not matter whether one considers a real specimen or a simulated one.
         
         Using a common description for the real experiment in the lab and - what is
         typically a simplification of it - via a computer simulation, has the benefit
         that many pieces of information can be stored in the same way. In effect,
         users are guided with finding information and unnecessary descriptive
         variety for what are exactly the same concept is avoided to work towards
         more interoperability.
         
         Another motivation to make no fundamental distinction between a scanning and
         a transmission electron microscope is that both are electron microscopes whose
         components are often very similar.
    </doc>
    <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Given name to the component e.g stage, lens C1, etc.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="description" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Ideally, a (globally) unique persistent identifier, link, or text to a
             resource which gives further details to this component.
             If such resource does not exist, a free-text field to report
             further details about the component is possible.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXfabrication"/>
    <group type="NXprogram"/>
    <group type="NXtransformations">
        <doc>
             Collection of axis-based translations and rotations to describe the
             location and geometry of the component in the instrument.
        </doc>
    </group>
</definition>
