<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXcs_filter_boolean_mask" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="n_objs">
            <doc>
                 Number of entries (e.g. number of points or objects).
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="bitdepth">
            <doc>
                 Number of bits assumed for the container datatype used.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_total">
            <doc>
                 Length of mask considering the eventual need for padding.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Computer science base class for packing and unpacking booleans.
         
         One use case is processing of object sets (like point cloud data).
         When one applies e.g. a spatial filter to a set of points to define which 
         points are analyzed and which not, it is useful to document which points were
         taken. One can store this information in a compact manner with an array of 
         boolean values. If the value is True the point is taken, else it is not.
         
         If the points are identified by an array of integer identifiers and an 
         arbitrary spatial filtering, the boolean array will be filled with True and False
         values in an arbitrary manner. Especially when the number of points is large,
         for instance several thousands and more, some situations can be more efficiently
         stored if one would not store the boolean array but just list the identifiers
         of the points taken. For instance if within a set of 1000 points only one point is
         taken, it would take (naively) 4000 bits to store the array but only 32 bits
         to store e.g. the ID of that taken point. Of course the 4000 bit field is so 
         sparse that it could be compressed resulting also in a substantial reduction 
         of the storage demands. Therefore boolean masks are useful compact descriptions
         to store information about set memberships in a compact manner. 
         In general it is true, though, that which representation is best, i.e. 
         most compact (especially when compressed) depends strongly on occupation of
         the array.
         
         This base class just bookkeeps metadata to inform software about necessary 
         modulo operations to decode the set membership of each object. This is useful
         because the number of objects not necessarily is an integer multiple of the bit depth.
    </doc>
    <field name="number_of_objects" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Number of objects represented by the mask.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="bitdepth" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Number of bits assumed matching on a default datatype.
             (e.g. 8 bits for a C-style uint8).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="mask" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             The unsigned integer array representing the content of the mask.
             If padding is used the padded bits have to be set to 0.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="n_total"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
    <field name="identifier" type="NX_UINT">
        <doc>
             Link to/or array of identifiers for the objects. The decoded mask is
             interpreted consecutively, i.e. the first bit in the mask matches
             to the first identifier, the second bit in the mask to the second
             identifier and so on and so forth.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="n_object"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
</definition>
