<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<!--
abTEM and other simulation packages, TEMgym, etc.-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXem_sim" extends="NXem_method" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Base class for simulating electron microscopy relevant beam-matter interaction.
         
         The concept behind this base class is to keep it as generic as possible
         that simulations of electron/ion beam interaction with matter can be
         represented. This base class is envisioned as the twin of the :ref:`NXem_msr`
         base class.
         
         It is an attempt to test the idea if at some point one might even use the
         same base class template to describe measurements and computer simulations
         of electron microscopy. This idea is attractive because the only practical
         difference between a description of a measurement with a microscope and a
         computer simulation is that the latter is typically a substantially simplified
         representation of the real microscope surplus the focus of the research
         in such cases on specific questions.
         
         Such simplification can be with respect to the optical setup, typically the
         ignoring of the fact that the electron beam is produced by a complex setup
         of lenses while in simulations often single Einzel lenses are considered.
         Dynamics of the environment like temperature fluctuation in a lab, vibrations,
         users, and multiple detectors are typically either ignored or reduced in
         complexity and number and coming with idealizations to keep the simulations
         focused on the specific reason questions and efficiently numerically executable.
    </doc>
    <group name="simulation" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
             Details about the simulation.
        </doc>
        <!--sequence_index(N):-->
        <group type="NXprogram"/>
        <group type="NXcg_geodesic_mesh"/>
        <group type="NXimage_r_set_diff"/>
    </group>
</definition>
