<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<!--
flesh out the description of that to read the docs, because currently the
description on the NeXus front-page is overwhelming
considering what we learned from the diataxis workshop we write here a
specification neither a how to nor a tutorial which explains all the context
because we address here developers of software-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXem_base" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <!--template to be used for an application definition-->
    <doc>
         Blue-print of a generic appdef for electron microscopy research formulated as a deep base class.
         
         This base class combines a method-specific and technical-design-level base class
         instance to provide a template for storing parameterized descriptions of
         pieces of information collected when performing electron microscopy research.
         
         The base class here shows all possible branches without making any statements
         as to which of these have to be used in an instance. Thereby, the base class
         provides a template how to name and structure concepts in a hierarchy
         to support finding information and reducing the need for renaming and
         restructuring information for a research field where many scientists perform
         very specific research but who all also share commonalities like usage of
         controlled electron beams, a focus on studies of electron beam matter interaction
         to explore physical mechanisms and phenomena, or the desire to characterize materials
         using electron microscopy.
    </doc>
    <!--each NeXus file instance should have a default plot
however as there are cases when this cannot be assured we cannot
make the default required, one example is e.g. a NeXus instance
where scientists just store conventions without a default plot-->
    <group type="NXentry">
        <field name="definition" type="NX_CHAR">
            <attribute name="version" type="NX_CHAR"/>
        </field>
        <!--enumeration: [NXem]
as NXem_base is a blue-print for an appdef written as a base class because
no other place for this in NeXus right now, NXem is the appdef along the lines of this blue-print-->
        <group name="profiling" type="NXcs_profiling">
            <doc>
                 The configuration of the I/O writer software (e.g. `pynxtools &lt;https://github.com/FAIRmat-NFDI/pynxtools&gt;`_)
                 which was used to generate this NeXus file instance.
            </doc>
            <group type="NXprogram">
                <doc>
                     A collection of all programs and libraries which are considered relevant
                     to understand with which software tools this NeXus file instance was
                     generated. Ideally, to enable a binary recreation from the input data.
                     
                     Examples include the name and version of the libraries used to write the
                     instance. Ideally, the software which writes these NXprogram instances
                     also includes the version of the set of NeXus classes i.e. the specific
                     set of base classes, application definitions, and  contributed definitions
                     with which the here described concepts can be resolved.
                     
                     For the `pynxtools library &lt;https://github.com/FAIRmat-NFDI/pynxtools&gt;`_
                     which is used by the `NOMAD &lt;https://nomad-lab.eu/nomad-lab&gt;`_
                     research data management system, it makes sense to store e.g. the GitHub
                     repository commit and respective submodule references used.
                </doc>
            </group>
        </group>
        <group name="experiment_identifier" type="NXidentifier">
            <doc>
                 Ideally, a (globally) unique persistent identifier
                 for referring to this experiment.
                 
                 An experiment should be understood in that this can be an experiment
                 in reality or a computer simulation because also the latter is an
                 experiment (see the Cambridge Dictionary experiment: 
                 *a test done in order to find out something, eg if an idea is correct*).
                 
                 The identifier is usually issued by the facility, laboratory,
                 or the principle investigator. The identifier enables to link
                 experiments/simulations to e.g. proposals.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <field name="experiment_description" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Free-text description about the experiment.
                 
                 Users are strongly advised to parameterize their description of the
                 experiment by using the respective base classes instead of writing prose
                 into this field.
                 
                 The reason is that such free-text field is difficult to machine-interpret.
                 The motivation behind keeping this field for now is to learn through
                 the information entered in this field in how far the current base
                 classes are incomplete.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
            <doc>
                 ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included
                 when the microscope session started. If the application demands that time
                 codes in this section of the application definition should only be used
                 for specifying when the experiment was performed - and the exact
                 duration is not relevant - this start_time field should be used.
                 
                 Often though it is useful to specify a time interval via setting both
                 a start_time and an end_time because this enables software tools and
                 users to collect a more detailed bookkeeping of the experiment.
                 
                 The user should be aware that even with having both time instances specified,
                 it may not be possible to infer how long the experiment took or for how
                 long data were acquired.
                 
                 More detailed timing data over the course of the experiment have
                 to be collected to compute this. These computations can take
                 advantage of individual time stamps start_time and end_time
                 in :ref:`NXevent_data_em` instances.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
            <doc>
                 ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC included when
                 the microscope session ended. See docstring of the start_time field
                 to see how the start_time and end_time should be used together.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <group type="NXcite"/>
        <group type="NXserialized">
            <doc>
                 Possibility to store a collection of serialized resources
                 that are associated with the experiment.
                 
                 An example how to use this set could be to document
                 from which files generated by software of technology partners
                 the information in an instance of NXem was filled.
                 
                 If resources from technology partners would also be documented
                 semantically annotated there would not even be a necessity to
                 copy over specific information in NeXus files as one could write
                 a inference and information/fact/knowledge retrieval algorithm whereby
                 a specific piece of information that is related to an experiment or simulation
                 is just read directly from the respective file of the technology partner.
                 
                 The reason why currently this works convincingly in hardly any research
                 data management system is the strong heterogeneity of the information contained
                 in such files and the fact that often context and documentation specifically
                 rich semantic documentation and contextualization is missing.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <!--using NXserialized here instead of NXnote as the former is more specific-->
        <group type="NXuser">
            <doc>
                 Contact information and eventually details of at least one person
                 who performed or was involved in the session. This can be the
                 principle investigator who performed this experiment or the student
                 who performed the simulation.
                 Adding multiple users if relevant is recommended.
            </doc>
            <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Given (first) name and surname of the user.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="affiliation" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Name of the affiliation of the user at the point in time
                     when the experiment was performed.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="address" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Postal address of the affiliation.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="email" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Email address of the user at the point in time when the experiment
                     was performed. Writing the most permanently used email is recommended.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <group name="identifier" type="NXidentifier">
                <doc>
                     Service as another mean of identification of a user than by the name.
                     Examples could be details about an ORCID or social media account of
                     the user.
                </doc>
            </group>
            <field name="telephone_number" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     (Business) (tele)phone number of the user at the point
                     in time when the experiment was performed.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="role" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Which role does the user have in the place and at the point
                     in time when the experiment was performed? Technician operating
                     the microscope, student, postdoc, principle investigator, or guest
                     are common examples.
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="sample" type="NXsample">
            <!--NEW ISSUE: inject the conclusion from the discussion with Andrea
according to SAMPLE.yaml 0f8df14 2022/06/15
ID: -> maps to name
name: -> short_title
user: -> not matched right now
citation: doi ->why relevant, should be solved by RDMS-->
            <doc>
                 A description of the material characterized in the experiment.
                 Sample and specimen are threaded as de facto synonyms.
                 Samples can be real specimens or virtual (see method).
            </doc>
            <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     A qualifier whether the sample is a real one or a
                     virtual one (in a computer simulation)
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="experiment"/>
                    <item value="simulation"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <!--MK:: declared_by_vendor I would rather expect this for a substance
COMPONENT.yaml
SUBSTANCE:
QUANTIFY-->
            <group name="identifier" type="NXidentifier">
                <doc>
                     Ideally, (globally) unique persistent identifier which distinguishes
                     the specimen from all others and especially the predecessor/origin
                     from where the specimen was cut. 
                     
                     This field must not be used for an alias! Instead, use name.
                     
                     In cases where multiple specimens were loaded into the microscope,
                     the identifier has to resolve the specific sample, whose results are
                     stored by this :ref:`NXentry` instance, because a single NXentry should be
                     used only for the characterization of a single specimen.
                     
                     Details about the specimen preparation should be
                     stored in resources referring to parent_identifier.
                </doc>
            </group>
            <group name="parent_identifier" type="NXidentifier">
                <doc>
                     Identifier of the sample from which the sample was cut or the string
                     *None*. The purpose of this field is to support functionalities
                     for tracking sample provenance via a research data management system.
                </doc>
            </group>
            <field name="preparation_date" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
                <doc>
                     ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information
                     when the specimen was prepared.
                     
                     Ideally, report the end of the preparation, i.e. the last known time
                     the measured specimen surface was actively prepared. Ideally, this
                     matches the last timestamp that is mentioned in the digital resource
                     pointed to by parent_identifier.
                     
                     Knowing when the specimen was exposed to e.g. specific atmosphere is
                     especially required for environmentally sensitive material such as
                     hydrogen charged specimens or experiments including tracers with a
                     short half time. Additional time stamps prior to preparation_date
                     should better be placed in resources which describe but which do not pollute
                     the description here with prose. Resolving these connected pieces of information
                     is considered within the responsibility of the research data management
                     system.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     An alias used to refer to the specimen to please readability for humans.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="atom_types" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     List of comma-separated elements from the periodic table that are
                     contained in the sample. If the sample substance has multiple
                     components, all elements from each component must be included in
                     `atom_types`.
                     
                     The purpose of the field is to offer research data management systems an
                     opportunity to parse the relevant elements without having to interpret
                     these from the resources pointed to by parent_identifier or walk through
                     eventually deeply nested groups in data instances.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <!--NEW ISSUE: use Andrea and MarkusK groups for describing the geometry of the sample-->
            <field name="thickness" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     (Measured) sample thickness.
                     
                     The information is recorded to qualify if the beam used was likely
                     able to shine through the specimen. For scanning electron microscopy,
                     in many cases the specimen is typically thicker than what is
                     illuminatable by the electron beam.
                     
                     In this case the value should be set to the actual thickness of
                     the specimen viewed for an illumination situation where the nominal
                     surface normal of the specimen is parallel to the optical axis.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <!--\@units: nm
NEW ISSUE: error estimates of the thickness and origin, i.e. how the value was obtained would be useful
NEW ISSUE: error model
NEW ISSUE: the KIT/SCC SEM, TEM schemata further qualify samples whether they are conductive e/ibeam sensitive
etc. The problem with this is that beam sensitivity is too vague but spatiotemporal electron dose integral dependent
KIT/SCC distinguish further conductivity and magnetic properties. While the motivation is clear, making
it thus simple is likely problematic when the data entered in such fields remaining qualitative.
what are good or bad properties, it would make sense though to quantify these values
this includes the description of eventual plasma cleaning steps,
just knowing that a sample was plasma cleaned is insufficient, maybe it was not cleaned long enough
if plasma cleaning is done outside the EM than its certainly history, if it happens inside the EM
are the ibeam description capabilities not sufficient enough?-->
            <field name="density" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
                <!--NX_MASS_PER_VOLUME-->
                <doc>
                     (Measured) density of the specimen.
                     
                     For multi-layered specimens this field should only be used to describe
                     the density of the excited volume. For scanning electron microscopy
                     the usage of this field is discouraged and instead an instance of an 
                     :ref:`NXinteraction_vol_em` within individual :ref:`NXevent_data_em`
                     instances can provide a cleaner description of the relevant details
                     why one may wish to store the density of the specimen.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="description">
                <doc>
                     Discouraged free-text field to provide further detail although adding
                     parent_identifier and having a working research data management system
                     should provide this contextualization.
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <!--(NXmonitor):-->
        <group type="NXdata"/>
        <group type="NXcoordinate_system_set"/>
        <!--link to an instance of an NXinstrument but that is anyway specialized for EM-->
        <group name="measurement" type="NXem_msr"/>
        <group name="simulation" type="NXem_sim"/>
        <group type="NXroi">
            <doc>
                 A region-of-interest analyzed either during or after the session
                 for which specific processed data generated from the measured or the
                 simulated data are available.
            </doc>
            <group name="se" type="NXem_img"/>
            <group name="bse" type="NXem_img"/>
            <group name="ebsd" type="NXem_ebsd"/>
            <group name="eds" type="NXem_eds"/>
            <group name="adf" type="NXem_adf"/>
            <group name="eels" type="NXem_eels"/>
            <group name="correlation" type="NXem_correlation"/>
        </group>
    </group>
    <!--cl(NXem_cl):-->
</definition>
