<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXem_correlation" extends="NXem_method" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Base class to combine different method-specific data in electron microscopy.
         
         This base class represent a template for documenting correlations
         (spatial, temporal) between different method-specific results.
    </doc>
    <group type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
             Details about processing steps.
        </doc>
        <field name="sequence_index" type="NX_INT"/>
    </group>
    <group name="indexing" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
             Details about correlated or logically connected EBSD datasets.
             
             One important class of such correlated experiments are the so-called
             (quasi) in-situ experiments. In this case the same or nearly the same ROI
             gets analyzed via a repetitive sequence of thermomechanical treatment,
             sample preparation, measurement, on-the-fly-indexing. Phenomena
             investigated are recrystallization, strain accumulation, material damage.
             Post-processing is required to correlate and reidentify eventual
             microstructural features or local ROIs across several orientation maps.
             
             Another important class of correlated experiments are the so-called
             serial-sectioning experiments. Here the same sample is measured
             repetitively after polishing each time, to create a stack of
             orientation data which can be reconstructed to a
             three-dimensional volume ROI.
             
             Data can be correlated in time, position (spatial), or both (spatiotemporal).
             
             Spatial correlations between repetitively characterized regions-of-interests
             are typically correlated using image registration and alignment algorithms.
             For this typically so-called landmarks are used. These can be grains with
             a very large size or specific shape, i.e. grains which are qualitatively
             different enough to be used as a guide how images are shifted relative to
             one another. Other commonly used landmarks are fiducial marks which are
             milled into the specimen surface using focus-ion beam milling and/or various
             types of indentation methods.
             
             As far as the same physical region-of-interest is just measured several times,
             the additional issue of the depth increment is not a concern. However, correct
             assumptions for the depth increment, amount of material removed along the milling
             direction is relevant for accurate and precise three-dimensional (serial-sectioning)
             correlations. For these studies it can be tricky though to assume or estimate
             useful depth increments. Different strategies have been proposed like
             calibrations, wedged-shaped landmarks and computer simulation assisted
             assumption making.
             
             Despite the use of landmarks, there are many practical issues which make the
             processing of correlations imprecise and inaccurate. Among these are drift
             and shift of the specimen, instabilities of the holder, the beam, irrespective
             of the source of the drift, charging effects, here specifically causing local
             image distortions and rotations which may require special processing algorithms
             to reduce such imprecisions.
             
             Time correlations face all of the above-mentioned issues surplus the challenge
             that specific experimental protocols have to be used to ensure the material state
             is observed at specific physical time. The example of quasi in-situ characterization
             of crystal growth phenomena, a common topic in engineering or modern catalysis research
             makes it necessary to consider that e.g. the target value for the desired annealing
             temperature is not just gauged based on macroscopic arguments but considers
             that transient effects take place. Heating or quenching a sample might thus might
             not have been executed under conditions in the interaction volume as they are
             documented and/or assumed.
             
             These issue cause that correlations have an error margin as to how accurately
             respective datasets were not only just synced based on the geometry of the
             region-of-interests and the time markers but also to asssure which physical
             conditions the specimen experienced over the course of the measurements.
             
             The fourth example of the em_om reference implementation explores the use of the
             correlation group with a serial-sectioning datasets that was collected by the
             classical Inconel 100 dataset collected by M. D. Uchic and colleagues
             (M. Groeber M, Haley BK, Uchic MD, Dimiduk DM, Ghosh S 3d reconstruction and
             characterization of polycrystalline microstructures using a fib-sem system data set.
             Mater Charac 2006, 57 259–273. 10.1016/j.matchar.2006.01.019M).
             
             This dataset was specifically relevant in driving forward the implementation
             of the DREAM.3D software. DREAM.3D is an open-source software project for
             post-processing and reconstructing, i.e. correlating sets of orientation
             microscopy data foremost spatially. One focus of the software is the
             (post-)processing of EBSD datasets. Another cutting edge tool with similar
             scope but a commercial solution by Bruker is QUBE which was developed by
             P. Konijnenberg and coworkers.
             
             Conceptually, software like DREAM.3D supports users with creating linear
             workflows of post-processing tasks. Workflows can be instructed via the
             graphical user interface or via so-called pipeline processing via command line
             calls. DREAM.3D is especially useful because its internal system documents all
             input, output, and parameter of the processing steps. This makes DREAM.3D a
             good candidate to interface with tools like em_om parser. Specifically, DREAM.3D
             documents numerical results via a customized HDF5 file format called DREAM3D.
             Workflow steps and settings are stored as nested dictionaries in JSON syntax
             inside a supplementary JSON file or alongside the data in the DREAM3D file.
             DREAM.3D has a few hundred algorithms implemented. These are called filters
             in DREAM.3D terminology.
             
             Users configure a workflow which instructs DREAM.3D to send the data through
             a chain of predefined and configured filters. Given that for each analysis
             the filter is documented via its version tags surplus its parameter and setting
             via a controlled vocabulary, interpreting the content of a DREAM3D HDF5 file
             is possible in an automated manner using a parser. This makes DREAM.3D analyses
             repeatable and self-descriptive. A key limitation though is that most frequently
             the initial set of input data come from commercial files like ANG.
             This missing link between the provenance of these input files, their associated
             creation as electron microscope session, is also what NXem_ebsd solves.
             
             Nevertheless, as this can be solved with e.g. NXem_ebsd we are convinced that
             the DREAM.3D and the em_om parser can work productively together to realize
             RDMS-agnostic parsing of serial-section analyses.
             
             The internal documentation of the DREAM.3D workflow also simplifies the
             provenance tracking represented by an instance of NXem_ebsd as not every
             intermediate results has to be stored. Therefore, the fourth example
             focuses on the key result obtained from DREAM.3D - the reconstructed
             and aligned three-dimensional orientation map.
             
             Usually, this result is the starting point for further post-processing
             and characterization of structural features. As here orientation microscopy
             is insofar scale invariant using DREAM.3D, NXem_ebsd, and em_om should
             be useful for different characterization methods, such as EBSD, Transmission
             Kikuchi Diffraction (TKD), Automated Crystal Orientation Mapping (ACOM),
             Nanobeam Electron Diffraction (using commercial systems like NanoMegas ASTAR)
             or open-source implementations of these techniques (such as via pyxem/orix).
             
             The result of orientation microscopy methods are maps of local orientation
             and thermodynamic phase (crystal structure) pieces of information. Virtually
             all post-processing of such results for structural features includes again
             a workflow of steps which are covered though by the NXms partner application
             definition. The respective source of the data in an instance of NXms can
             again be a link or reference to an instance of NXem_ebsd to complete the
             chain of provenance.
        </doc>
        <group type="NXcrystal_structure"/>
        <group name="roi" type="NXdata">
            <field name="descriptor">
                <doc>
                     Descriptor representing the image contrast.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <!--\@signal:  # data
\@axes:  # [axis_y, axis_x]
\@axis_x_indices: 0
\@axis_y_indices: 1
\@signal:
\@axes:
\@AXISNAME_indices:
\@long_name:-->
            <field name="title">
                <doc>
                     Title of the default plot.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="data" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                     Descriptor values displaying the ROI.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="3">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_z"/>
                    <dim index="2" value="n_y"/>
                    <dim index="3" value="n_x"/>
                </dimensions>
                <!--n_0 slowest 3, n_1 slow 2, n_2 fast 1, rgb triplet is fastest 0
in axes fast to fastest
while for _indices fastest to fast-->
                <attribute name="long_name">
                    <doc>
                         Descriptor values.
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
            <field name="axis_z" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     Calibrated coordinate along the z-axis.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_z"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="long_name">
                    <doc>
                         Label for the z axis
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
            <field name="axis_y" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     Calibrated coordinate along the y-axis.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_y"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="long_name">
                    <doc>
                         Label for the y axis
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
            <field name="axis_x" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                     Calibrated coordinate along the x-axis.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_x"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="long_name">
                    <doc>
                         Label for the x axis
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
        </group>
    </group>
    <!--NEW ISSUE: implement support for filters eventually many of them
NEW ISSUE: for now only show that data from DREAM3D can be loaded.
NEW ISSUE: how to handle landmarks
NEW ISSUE: again an entire set of workflows such as rigid or non-rigid
image registration etc.
sequence_index(N0):-->
</definition>
