<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXenergydispersion" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Subclass of NXelectronanalyser to describe the energy dispersion section of a
         photoelectron analyser.
    </doc>
    <field name="scheme" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Energy dispersion scheme employed, for example: tof, hemispherical, cylindrical,
             mirror, retarding grid, etc.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="pass_energy" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ENERGY">
        <doc>
             Mean kinetic energy of the electrons in the energy-dispersive portion of the analyser.
             This term should be used for hemispherical analysers.
             
             This concept is related to term `12.63`_ of the ISO 18115-1:2023 standard.
             
             .. _12.63: https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/en/#iso:std:iso:18115:-1:ed-3:v1:en:term:12.63
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="kinetic_energy" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ENERGY">
        <doc>
             Kinetic energy set for the dispersive analyzer section. Can be either the set kinetic energy,
             or the whole calibrated energy axis of a scan.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="drift_energy" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ENERGY">
        <doc>
             Drift energy for time-of-flight energy dispersive elements.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="center_energy" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ENERGY">
        <doc>
             Center of the energy window
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="energy_interval" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ENERGY">
        <doc>
             The interval of transmitted energies. It can be two different things depending
             on whether the scan is fixed or swept. With a fixed scan it is a 2 vector
             containing the extrema of the transmitted energy window (smaller number first).
             With a swept scan of m steps it is a 2xm array of windows one for each
             measurement point.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="diameter" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
        <doc>
             Diameter of the dispersive orbit
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="energy_scan_mode" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Way of scanning the energy axis
        </doc>
        <enumeration>
            <item value="fixed_analyser_transmission">
                <doc>
                     constant :math:`\Delta E` mode, where the electron retardation (i.e., the fraction of pass energy to
                     kinetic energy, :math:`R = (E_K - W/E_p)`, is scanned, but the pass energy :math:`E_p` is kept constant.
                     Here, :math:`W = e \phi` is the spectrometer work function (with the potential difference :math:`\phi_{\mathrm{sample}}`
                     between the electrochemical potential of electrons in the bulk and the electrostatic potential of an electron in the
                     vacuum just outside the surface).
                     
                     This mode is often used in XPS/UPS because the energy resolution does not change with
                     changing energy (due to the constant pass energy).
                     
                     Synonyms: constant :math:`\Delta E` mode, constant analyser energy mode, CAE
                     mode, FAT mode
                     
                     This concept is related to term `12.64`_ of the ISO 18115-1:2023 standard.
                     
                     .. _12.64: https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/en/#iso:std:iso:18115:-1:ed-3:v1:en:term:12.64
                </doc>
            </item>
            <item value="fixed_retardation_ratio">
                <doc>
                     constant :math:`\Delta E/E` mode, where the pass energy is scanned such that the electron retardation
                     ratio is constant. In this mode, electrons of all energies are decelerated with this same
                     fixed factor. Thus, the pass energy is proportional to the kinetic energy. This mode is often
                     used in Auger electron spectroscopy (AES) to improve S/N for high-KE electrons, but this
                     leads to a changing energy resolution (:math:`\Delta E \sim E_p`) at different kinetic energies.
                     It can however also be used in XPS.
                     
                     Synonyms: constant :math:`\Delta E/E` mode, constant retardation ratio mode, CRR
                     mode, FRR mode
                     
                     This concept is related to term `12.66`_ of the ISO 18115-1:2023 standard.
                     
                     .. _12.66: https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/en/#iso:std:iso:18115:-1:ed-3:v1:en:term:12.66
                </doc>
            </item>
            <item value="fixed_energy">
                <doc>
                     In the fixed energy (FE) mode, the intensity for one single kinetic energy is measured for a
                     specified time. This mode is particulary useful during setup or alignment of the
                     electron analyzer, for analysis of stability of the excitation source or for sample
                     alignment.
                     
                     Since the mode measures intensity as a function of time, the difference in channel signals
                     is not of interest. Therefore, the signals from all channels are summed.
                     
                     Synonyms: FE mode
                </doc>
            </item>
            <item value="snapshot">
                <doc>
                     Snapshot mode does not involve an energy scan and instead collects data from all channels of
                     the detector without averaging. The resulting spectrum reflects the energy distribution of
                     particles passing through the analyzer using the current settings. This mode is commonly used
                     to position the detection energy at the peak of a peak and record the signal, enabling faster
                     data acquisition within a limited energy range compared to FAT. Snapshot measurements are
                     particularly suitable for CCD and DLD detectors, which have multiple channels and can accurately
                     display the peak shape. While five or nine-channel detectors can also be used for snapshot
                     measurements, their energy resolution is relatively lower.
                </doc>
            </item>
            <item value="dither">
                <doc>
                     In dither acquisition mode, the kinetic energy of the analyzer is randomly varied by a small value
                     around a central value and at fixed pass energy. This allows reducing or removing inhomogeneities
                     of the detector efficiency, such as e.g. imposed by a mesh in front of the detector.
                     Mostly relevant for CCD/DLD type of detectors.
                </doc>
            </item>
        </enumeration>
    </field>
    <field name="tof_distance" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
        <doc>
             Length of the tof drift electrode
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXaperture">
        <doc>
             Size, position and shape of a slit in dispersive analyzer, e.g. entrance and
             exit slits.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group type="NXdeflector">
        <doc>
             Deflectors in the energy dispersive section
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group type="NXlens_em">
        <doc>
             Individual lenses in the energy dispersive section
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group type="NXfabrication"/>
    <field name="depends_on" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Specifies the position of the energy dispesive elemeent by pointing to the last
             transformation in the transformation chain in the NXtransformations group.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXtransformations">
        <doc>
             Collection of axis-based translations and rotations to describe the location and
             geometry of the energy dispersive element as a component in the instrument.
             Conventions from the NXtransformations base class are used. In principle,
             the McStas coordinate system is used. The first transformation has to point
             either to another  component of the system or . (for pointing to the reference frame)
             to relate it relative to the experimental setup. Typically, the components of a system
             should all be related relative to each other and only one component should relate to
             the reference coordinate system.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <attribute name="default">
        <doc>
             .. index:: plotting
             
             Declares which child group contains a path leading
             to a :ref:`NXdata` group.
             
             It is recommended (as of NIAC2014) to use this attribute
             to help define the path to the default dataset to be plotted.
             See https://www.nexusformat.org/2014_How_to_find_default_data.html
             for a summary of the discussion.
        </doc>
    </attribute>
</definition>
