<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<definition category="base" extends="NXobject" name="NXevent_data_em" type="group" xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <doc>
         A container to store metadata and settings of the instrument which are
         specific for scans, images, and metadata. The need for such a structuring
         of data is evident from the fact that electron microscopes are dynamic.
         
         Oftentimes it suffices to calibrate the instrument at the start of the 
         session. Subsequently, data (images, spectra, etc.) can be collected. 
         Users may wish to take a single data item after which their session is complete.
         
         For this use case one may argue that the need for an additional grouping 
         is redundant. Instead, the metadata could equally have been stored inside
         the respective groups of the top-level mandatory NXinstrument group. 
         On the flip side, even for a session with a single image it would also not 
         harm to nest the data.
         
         Frequently users spend much longer at the microscope in the course of which
         the recalibrate and take data items with each calibration.
         
         In fact, oftentimes scientists feel that there is a need to store details 
         about eventual drift of the specimen in its holder (if such data is available)
         or record changes the lens excitations or apertures used. 
         Although, current microscopes are usually equipped with stabilization 
         systems for many of the individual components, it can still be useful 
         to store time-dependent data more seriously.
         
         Another reason if not a need for a more finely granularizable options for 
         storing time-dependent data, is that over the course of a session one may
         reconfigure the microscope. What is a reconfiguration? This could be the
         change of an aperture mode because a scientist may first collect an image
         with some aperture and then choose a different mode before taking the next
         image. As the aperture affects the electron beam it will affect the system.
         Not necessarily to a level that the microscopy requires a recalibration but
         at least at the level of each image the application definition has to assure
         that these specific settings can be stored for each collected signal/image.
         
         Let aside for a moment the technology and business models, an EM could be 
         monitored (and will likely be in the future) for streaming out spatio-temporal
         details about its components, locations and eventually applied stimuli and 
         positioning of the specimen. Some snapshot or integrated data from this stream
         are relevant to understand the signal genesis. In such a generic case
         it might be necessary to sync these streaming data with those intervals
         in time when specific measurements are taken (spectra collected, 
         images taken, diffraction images indexed on-the-fly).
         
         Theoretically, an instrument and specimen should be considered as dynamic.
         Scientists often report or feel (difficult to quantify) observations that
         microscopes &quot;&quot;&quot;perform differently&quot;&quot;&quot; across sessions, without sometimes a 
         clear root cause. Users of the instrument may consider such conditions
         impractical and thus either abort their session or try to bring the 
         microscope first into a state where conditions are considered stable and
         of high enough qualiy to collect data.
         
         In all these cases it is practical to store time-dependent data of the
         instrument state not in the respective instrument component groups
         of the top-level NXinstrument but in a sort of event data log.
         This is the idea behind this NX&quot;#&quot;em&quot;#&quot;_snapshot.
         
         The base class requires a start time and an optional end time. 
         The end time should be added to represent a time interval
         (remind the idea of the instrument state stream) during which the 
         scientist considered the microscope (beam and specimen) as 
         incrementally stable enough.
         
         For specific simulation purposes, mainly in an effort to digitally repeat
         or simulate the experiment, it is tempting to consider dynamics of the
         instrument, implemented as time-dependent functional descriptions of
         e.g. lens excitations, beam shape function, electron trajectories, or
         detector noise models.
         
         For now the preferred strategy to handle these cases is through
         customizations of the specific fields within NXem_snapshots. Another 
         alternative could be to sample finer, eventually dissimilarly along the
         time axis. This may cause situations though where an NXem_snapshot does
         not contain specific measurements (i.e. images, spectra of scientific
         relevance).
         
         In this case one should better go for a customized application definition
         with a functional property description inside NXem_snapshot members or
         resort to a specific application definition which allows to store metadata
         for tracking explicitly electrons (with ray-tracing based descriptors/
         computational geometry descriptors) or tracking of wave bundle approaches.
         
         This perspective on more subtle time-dependent considerations of electron
         microscopy can be advantageous also for storing details of time-dependent
         additional components that are coupled to and synced or not with the 
         instrument.
         
         Examples include cutting-edge experiments where the electron beam gets
         coupled/excited by e.g. lasers. In this case, the laser unit should be 
         registered under the top-level NXinstrument section. Its spatio-temporal
         details could be stored inside respective groups of the NXem_instrument
    </doc>
    <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included when the snapshot time interval started.
             If the user wishes to specify an interval of time that the snapshot should represent during which the
             instrument was stable and configured using specific settings and calibrations, the start_time is the 
             start (left bound of the time interval) while the end_time specifies the end (right bound) of the time interval.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC included when the snapshot time interval ended.
             If the user does not wish to specify a time interval, end_time should have the same value as start_time.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="event_identifier" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Reference to a specific state and setting of the microscope components.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="event_type" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Which specific event/measurement type. Pick one of the following:
             * in-lens detector, like bse detector usually build from quadrants,
             can be represented like in NXmx
             * secondary_electron, image, topography, fractography, overview
             * backscattered_electron, image, Z contrast, ECCI
             * bright_field, image, TEM
             * dark_field, image, crystal defects
             * adf, image (medium- or high-angle) annular dark field, TEM
             * diffraction, image, TEM diffraction, or a comparable technique in the SEM
             * kikuchi, image, SEM EBSD and TEM diffraction
             * xray, spectrum (point, line, surface, volume), composition,
             energy-dispersive X-ray spectroscopy (EDS/EDX) in SEM, 
             EDXS as equivalent techniques in TEM,
             also for low Z elements with grating technique detectors
             * eels, spectrum (p, l, s, v), binding, ZLP, plasmons, TEM
             * auger, spectrum, (low Z contrast)
             * cathodoluminescence (optical spectra)
             * ronchigram, image, a utility image to check the alignment specifically in TEM
             * chamber, image taken with the control monitor from inside
             the SEM or TEM to check e.g. placing of components or educational
             purposes
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="detector_identifier" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             The detector or set of detectors that was used to collect this signal.
             The name of the detector has to match the names used for available
             detectors, i.e. if the instrument has an ebsd_camera
             the detector for an NXimage_em_kikuchi should be the ebsd_camera
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_se"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_bse"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_ecci"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_bf"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_df"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_adf"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_kikuchi"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_diffrac"/>
    <group type="NXspectrum_set_em_xray"/>
    <group type="NXspectrum_set_em_eels"/>
    <group type="NXspectrum_set_em_auger"/>
    <group type="NXspectrum_set_em_cathodolum"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_ronchigram"/>
    <group type="NXimage_set_em_chamber"/>
    <group type="NXebeam_column"/>
    <group type="NXibeam_column"/>
    <group name="ebeam_deflector" type="NXscanbox_em"/>
    <group name="ibeam_deflector" type="NXscanbox_em"/>
    <group type="NXoptical_system"/>
    <group type="NXuser"/>
</definition>
