<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXevent_data_em" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Metadata and settings of an electron microscope for scans and images.
         
         The need for such a structuring of data is evident from the fact that
         electron microscopes are dynamic. Oftentimes it suffices to calibrate the
         instrument at the start of the session. Subsequently, data (images, spectra, etc.)
         can be collected. Users may wish to take only a single scan or image and
         complete their microscope session; however
         
         frequently users are working much longer at the microscope, recalibrate and take
         multiple data items (scans, images, spectra). Each item comes with own detector
         and eventually on-the-fly processing settings and calibrations.
         
         For the single data item use case one may argue that the need for an additional
         grouping is redundant. Instead, the metadata could equally be stored inside
         the respective groups of the top-level mandatory NXinstrument group.
         On the flip side, even for a session with a single image, it would also not
         harm to nest the data.
         
         In fact, oftentimes scientists feel that there is a need to store details
         about eventual drift of the specimen in its holder (if such data is available)
         or record changes to the lens excitations or apertures used and/or changed.
         Although current microscopes are usually equipped with stabilization
         systems for many of the individual components, it can still be useful
         to store time-dependent data in detail.
         
         Another reason if not a need for having more finely granularizable options for
         storing time-dependent data, is that over the course of a session one may
         reconfigure the microscope. What is a reconfiguration? This could be the
         change of an aperture mode because a scientist may first collect an image
         with some aperture and then pick a different value and continue.
         As the aperture affects the electron beam, it will affect the system.
         
         Let aside for a moment the technology and business models, an EM could be
         monitored (and will likely become so more in the future) for streaming out
         spatio-temporal details about its components, locations of (hardware components) and objects within the region-of-interest. Eventually external stimuli are applied
         and the specimen repositioned.
         
         Some snapshot or integrated data from this stream are relevant for understanding
         signal genesis and electron/ion-beam-sample interaction (paths). In such a generic
         case it might be necessary to sync these streaming data with those intervals
         in time when specific measurements are taken (spectra collected,
         images taken, diffraction images indexed on-the-fly).
         
         Therefore, both the instrument and specimen should always be considered as dynamic.
         Scientists often report or feel (difficult to quantify) observations that
         microscopes *perform differently* across sessions, without sometimes being
         able to identify clear root causes. Users of the instrument may consider
         such conditions impractical, or *too poor* and thus either abort their session
         or try to bring the microscope first into a state where conditions are considered
         more stable, better, or of some whatever high enough quality to reuse
         data collection.
         
         In all these cases it is practical to have a mechanism how time-dependent data
         of the instrument state can be stored and documented in a interoperable way.
         Where should these data be stored? With NeXus these data should not only be
         stored in the respective instrument component groups of the top-level NXinstrument.
         The reason is that this group should be reserved for as stable as possible
         quantities which do not change over the session. Thereby we can avoid to store
         repetitively that there is a certain gun or detector available but just store
         the changes. This is exactly what the em_lab group is for inside NXevent_data_em.
         
         Ideally, NXevent_data_em are equipped with a start_time and end_time
         to represent a time interval (remind the idea of the instrument state stream)
         during which the scientist considered (or practically has to consider)
         the microscope (especially ebeam and specimen) as stable enough.
         
         Arguably it is oftentimes tricky to specify a clear time interval when the
         microscope is stable enough. Take for instance the acquisition of an image
         or spectra stack. It is not fully possible (technically) to avoid that even
         within a single image instabilities of the beam are faced and drift occurs.
         Maybe in many cases this these instabilities are irrelevant but does this
         warrant to create a data schema where either the microscope state can only
         be stored very coarsely or one is forced to store it very finely?
         
         This is a question of how one wishes to granularize pieces of information.
         A possible solution is to consider each probed position, i.e. point in time
         when the beam was not blanked and thus when the beam illuminates a portion of
         the material, i.e. the interaction volume, whose signal contributions are then
         counted by the one or multiple detector(s) as per pixel- or per voxel signal
         in the region-of-interest.
         NXevent_data_em in combination with the NXem application definition
         allows researchers to document this. Noteworty to mention is that we understand
         that in many cases realizing such a fine temporal and logical granularization
         and data collection is hard to achieve in practice.
         
         A frequently made choice, mainly for convenience, is that drift and scan distortions
         are considered a feature or inaccuracy of the image and/or spectrum and thus
         one de facto accepts that the microscope was not as stable as expected during
         the acquisition of the image. We learn that the idea of a time interval
         during the microscope session may be interpreted differently by different
         users. Here we consider the choice to focus on images and spectra, and eventually
         single position measurements as the smallest granularization level.
         Which eventually may require to add optional NXprocess instances for respectively
         collected data to describe the relevant distortions. Nevertheless, the distortions
         are typically corrected for by numerical protocols. This fact warrants to
         consider the distortion correction a computational workflow which can be
         modelled as a chain of NXprocess instances each with own parameters.  an own 
         A more detailed overview of such computational steps to cope with scan distortions
         is available in the literature:
         
         * `C. Ophus et al. &lt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2015.12.002&gt;`_  
         * `B. Berkels et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2018.12.016&gt;`_  
         * `L. Jones et al. &lt;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s40679-015-0008-4&gt;`_  
         
         For specific simulation purposes, mainly in an effort to digitally repeat
         or simulate the experiment, it is tempting to consider dynamics of the
         instrument, implemented as time-dependent functional descriptions of
         e.g. lens excitations, beam shape functions, trajectories of groups of
         electrons, or detector noise models.
         
         For now the preferred strategy to handle these cases is through
         customizations of the specific fields within NXevent_data_em instances.
         
         Another alternative could be to sample finer, eventually dissimilarly along
         the time axi; however this may cause situations where an NXevent_data_em
         instance does not contain specific measurements (i.e. images, spectra of
         scientific relevance).
         
         In this case one should better go for a customized application definition
         with a functional property description inside members (fields or groups)
         in NXevent_data_em instances; or resort to a specific offspring application
         definition of NXem which documents metadata for tracking explicitly electrons
         (with ray-tracing based descriptors/computational geometry descriptors)
         or tracking of wave bundles.
         
         This perspective on much more subtle time-dependent considerations of electron
         microscopy can be advantageous also for storing details of time-dependent
         additional components that are coupled to and/or synced with a microscope.
         
         Examples include cutting-edge experiments where the electron beam gets
         coupled/excited by e.g. lasers. In this case, the laser unit should be
         registered under the top-level NXinstrument section. Its spatio-temporal
         details could be stored inside respective additional groups of the NXinstrument
         though inside instances of here detailed NXevent_data_em.
    </doc>
    <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included
             when the snapshot time interval started. If the user wishes to specify an
             interval of time that the snapshot should represent during which the instrument
             was stable and configured using specific settings and calibrations,
             the start_time is the start (left bound of the time interval) while
             the end_time specifies the end (right bound) of the time interval.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included
             when the snapshot time interval ended.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="event_identifier">
        <doc>
             Reference to a specific state and setting of the microscope.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="event_type">
        <doc>
             Which specific event/measurement type. Examples are:
             
             * In-lens/backscattered electron, usually has quadrants  
             * Secondary_electron, image, topography, fractography, overview images  
             * Backscattered_electron, image, Z or channeling contrast (ECCI)  
             * Bright_field, image, TEM  
             * Dark_field, image, crystal defects  
             * Annular dark field, image (medium- or high-angle), TEM  
             * Diffraction, image, TEM, or a comparable technique in the SEM  
             * Kikuchi, image, SEM EBSD and TEM diffraction  
             * X-ray spectra (point, line, surface, volume), composition EDS/EDX(S)  
             * Electron energy loss spectra for points, lines, surfaces, TEM  
             * Auger, spectrum, (low Z contrast element composition)  
             * Cathodoluminescence (optical spectra)  
             * Ronchigram, image, alignment utility specifically in TEM  
             * Chamber, e.g. TV camera inside the chamber, education purposes.  
             
             This field may also be used for storing additional information about the event.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXimage_set"/>
    <group type="NXspectrum_set"/>
    <group type="NXinstrument"/>
    <group type="NXuser"/>
    <group type="NXinteraction_vol_em"/>
    <!--a collection of images take and group under this event
NEW ISSUE: should this only be one instance for a given event?
(NXimage_set_em_se):
(NXimage_set_em_bse):
(NXimage_set_em_ecci):
(NXimage_set_em_bf):
(NXimage_set_em_df):
(NXimage_set_em_adf):
(NXimage_set_em_kikuchi):
(NXimage_set_em_diffrac):
(NXspectrum_set_em_xray):
(NXspectrum_set_em_eels):
(NXspectrum_set_em_auger):
(NXspectrum_set_em_cathodolum):
(NXimage_set_em_ronchigram):
(NXimage_set_em_chamber):
a collection of specific details about state of the microscope-->
</definition>
