<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXevent_data_apm" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="p">
            <doc>
                 Number of pulses collected in between start_time and end_time.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Base class to store state and (meta)data of events over the course of an atom probe experiment.
         
         This base class applies the concept of the :ref:`NXevent_data_em` base class to the specific needs
         of atom probe research. Against static and dynamic quantities are splitted to avoid a duplication
         of information. Specifically, the time interval considered is the entire time
         starting at start_time until end_time during which we assume the pulser triggered named pulses.
         These pulses are identified via the pulse_identifier field. The point in time when each was issued
         is specified via the combination of start_time and delta_time.
         
         Conceptually and technically NeXus currently stores tensorial information as arrays of values
         (with each value of the same datatype). For instance, a field temperature(NX_FLOAT) stores
         a set of temperature values but that field when used somewhere is a concept. However, that
         concept has no information at which point in time these temperatures were taken.
         An existent functional relationship between the two concepts is not defined.
         
         However, a correct interpretation of the temperature values demands knowledge about what is
         the independent quantity on which temperature depends on or according to which frequency
         temperature values were sampled.
         In NeXus there are two approaches which cope with such correlations:
         One is :ref:`NXdata` where the attribute signal specifies the correlation.
         The other one is :ref:`NXlog` which, like NXdata, demands to granularize logged_against
         (dependent signal) and independent quantities into an own group.
         In many cases this additional grouping is not desired though.
         
         One naive solution typically employed is then to store the independent variable values via a second
         vector e.g. time_stamp with the same number of entries (with dimensionality defined through symbols).
         However, there is no independent logical connection between these two concepts, i.e. temperature 
         and time_stamp.
         
         In the case of atom probe though the time that one would use in NXlog is defined implicitly via pulse_identifier,
         which is the independent variable vector against which eventually dozens of channels of data are logged.
         Not only are these channels logged they should ideally also be self-descriptive in that these channels have
         pulse_identifier as the independent variable but we do not wish to duplicate this information all the time but
         reference it.
         
         Therefore, we here explore the use of an attribute with symbol logged_against. Maybe it is better to use the
         symbol depends_on but this is easily to be confused with depends_on that is used for instances of
         :ref:`NXtransformations`. Consequently, if depends_on were to be used extra logic is needed by consuming
         applications to understand that the here build correlations are conceptually different ones.
         
         This issue should be discussed further by the NeXus community.
    </doc>
    <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included
             when the snapshot time interval started. If the user wishes to specify an
             interval of time that the snapshot should represent during which the instrument
             was stable and configured using specific settings and calibrations,
             the start_time is the start (left bound of the time interval) while
             the end_time specifies the end (right bound) of the time interval.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included
             when the snapshot time interval ended.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="delta_time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Delta time array which resolves for each pulse_identifier the time difference
             between when that pulse was issued and start_time.
             
             In summary, using start_time, end_time, delta_time, pulse_identifier_offset,
             and pulse_identifier exactly specifies the connection between when a pulse was
             issued relative to start and absolute in UTC.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="p"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
    <field name="pulse_identifier_offset" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Integer used to name the first pulse to know if there is an
             offset of the identifiers to zero.
             
             Identifiers can be defined either implicitly or explicitly.
             For implicit indexing identifiers are defined on the interval
             :math:`[identifier\_offset, identifier\_offset + c - 1]`.
             
             Therefore, implicit identifier are completely defined by the value of
             identifier_offset and cardinality. For example if identifier run from
             -2 to 3 the value for identifier_offset is -2.
             
             For explicit indexing the field identifier has to be used.
             Fortran-/Matlab- and C-/Python-style indexing have specific implicit
             identifier conventions where identifier_offset is 1 and 0 respectively.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="pulse_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Identifier that contextualizes how the detector and pulser of an atom probe
             instrument follows a sequence of pulses to trigger field evaporation.
             
             The pulse_identifier is used to associate thus an information about time
             when the quantities documented in this NXpulser_apm base class have been
             collected via sampling.
             
             In virtually all cases the pulser is a blackbox. Depending on how the
             instrument is configured during a measurement the target
             values and thus also the actual values may change.
             
             Maybe the first part of the experiment is run at a certain pulse fraction but thereafter
             the pulse_fraction is changed. In this case the field pulse_fraction is a vector which
             collects all measured values of the pulse_fraction, pulse_identifier is then an equally
             long vector which stores the set of events (e.g. pulsing events) when that value was
             measured.
             
             This may cause several situations: In the case that e.g. the pulse_fraction is never changed
             and also exact details not interesting, one stores the set value for the pulse_fraction
             and a single value for the pulse_identifier e.g. 0 to indicate that the pulse_fraction was set
             at the beginning and it was maintained constant during the measurement.
             If the pulse_fraction was maybe changed after the 100000th pulse, pulse_fraction is a
             vector with two values one for the first and another one for the value from the 100000-th
             pulse onwards. The values of pulse_identifier are then [0, 99999] respectively.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="p"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
    <group name="instrument" type="NXinstrument">
        <doc>
             (Meta)data of the dynamics and changes of the microscope over the course of
             pulsing.
        </doc>
        <group name="control" type="NXcollection">
            <doc>
                 Relevant quantities during a measurement with a LEAP system as suggested by
                 `T. Blum et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1002/9781119227250.ch18&gt;`_.
            </doc>
            <field name="evaporation_control" type="NX_CHAR">
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="detection_rate"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <field name="target_detection_rate" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY"/>
        </group>
        <group type="NXreflectron"/>
        <group name="local_electrode" type="NXlens_em"/>
        <group name="ion_detector" type="NXdetector">
            <field name="signal_amplitude" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_CURRENT">
                <doc>
                     Amplitude of the signal detected on the multi-channel plate (MCP).
                     
                     This field should be used for storing the signal amplitude quantity
                     within ATO files. The ATO file format is used primarily by the
                     atom probe groups of the GPM in Rouen, France.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="p"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
        </group>
        <!--does p only specific the length or does it also convey a logical correlation
conceptually to another vector which happens to have the same dimensions
I clear say NO !-->
        <group name="pulser" type="NXpulser_apm"/>
        <group name="stage_lab" type="NXstage_lab">
            <field name="setpoint_temperature" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_TEMPERATURE">
                <doc>
                     Set point temperature to achieve during the measurement.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="base_temperature" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_TEMPERATURE">
                <doc>
                     Average temperature (at the specimen base) during the measurement.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <!--normally one would use NXsensor/NXlog but point is that the temperature
is logged against the pulse_identifier as even in the proprietary file format from
AMETEK/Cameca nowhere there is the actual time when the pulse was triggered
just the sampling frequency and I guess but am not 100percent sure which quantity
from Cameca this is also the time when the first pulse was triggered
using NXlog does make sense when individual NXsensors have different timing
but for atom probe if at all the pulse-based implicit time is available-->
            <field name="temperature" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_TEMPERATURE">
                <doc>
                     The best estimate, at experiment time, for the temperature at the
                     sample base (furthest point along sample apex and holding assembly
                     that is removable from the sample stage).
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="p"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="logged_against" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Path to pulse_identifier in an instance of :ref:`NXevent_data_apm`.
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="analysis_chamber" type="NXchamber">
            <field name="chamber_pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                <doc>
                     Average pressure in the analysis chamber during the measurement.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                <doc>
                     Pressure in the analysis chamber.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="p"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="logged_against" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Path to pulse_identifier in an instance of :ref:`NXevent_data_apm`.
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="buffer_chamber" type="NXchamber">
            <field name="pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                <doc>
                     Pressure in the analysis chamber.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="p"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="logged_against" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Path to pulse_identifier in an instance of :ref:`NXevent_data_apm`.
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group name="load_lock_chamber" type="NXchamber">
            <field name="pressure" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_PRESSURE">
                <doc>
                     Pressure in the analysis chamber.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="p"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="logged_against" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                         Path to pulse_identifier in an instance of :ref:`NXevent_data_apm`.
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
        </group>
    </group>
    <!--getter_pump(NXpump):
roughening_pump(NXpump):
turbomolecular_pump(NXpump):-->
</definition>
