<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXevent_data_em" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Base class to store state and (meta)data of events with an electron microscopy.
         
         Electron microscopes are dynamic. Scientists often report that microscopes
         *perform differently* across sessions, that they perform differently from
         one day or another. In some cases, root causes for performance differences
         are unclear. Users of the instrument may consider such conditions impractical,
         or *too poor*, and thus abort their session. Alternatively, users may try to
         bring the microscope into a state where conditions are considered better
         or of whatever high enough quality for continuing the measurement.
         
         In all these use cases in practice it would be useful to have a mechanism
         whereby time-dependent data of the instrument state can be stored and
         documented with an interoperable representation. Indeed, how a session on an
         electron microscope is spent depends strongly on the research question,
         the user, and the imaging modalities used.
         
         :ref:`NXevent_data_em` represents an instance to describe and serialize flexibly
         whatever is considered a time interval during which the instrument is
         considered as stable enough for performing a task with the microscope.
         Examples of such tasks are the collecting of data (images and spectra) or
         the calibrating of some component of the instrument. Users may wish to take
         only a single scan or image and complete their microscope session thereafter.
         Alternatively, users are working for much longer time at the microscope,
         perform recalibrations in between and take several scans (of different
         regions-of-interest of the specimen), or they explore the state of the
         microscope for service or maintenance tasks.
         
         :ref:`NXevent_data_em` serves the harmonization and documentation of this situation
         with providing three key sections: Firstly, there is a header section whose
         purpose is to contextualize and identify the event instance in time.
         Secondly, there is a data and metadata section where individual data collections
         can be stored using a standardized representation.
         
         The idea of the first, the event-based em_lab section, is to document the
         state of the microscope as it was during the event. The idea of the other,
         the NXem application based em_lab(NXinstrument) section is to keep all those
         pieces of information which are static in the sense that they are the same
         across multiple :ref:`NXevent_data_em` instance. This reduces the amount of pieces of
         information that have to be stored repetitively.
         
         We are aware of the fact that given the variety how an electron microscope 
         is used, there is a need for a flexible and adaptive documentation system.
         At the same time we are also convinced though that just because one has
         different requirements for some specific aspect under the umbrella of settings
         to an electron microscope, this does not necessarily warrant that one has to
         cook up an own schema.
         
         Instead, the electron microscopy community should work towards reusing schema
         components as frequently as possible. This will enable that there is at all
         not only a value of harmonizing electron microscopy research content but also
         the technical possibility to build services around such harmonized
         pieces of information.
         
         Arguably it is oftentimes tricky to specify a clear time interval when the
         microscope is *stable enough*. Take for instance the acquisition of an image
         or a stack of spectra. Having to deal with instabilities is a common theme in
         electron microscopy practice. Numerical protocols can be used during data
         post-processing to correct for some of the instabilities.
         A few exemplar references to provide an overview on the subject is 
         available in the literature:
         
         * `C. Ophus et al. &lt;https://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2015.12.002&gt;`_
         * `B. Berkels et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultramic.2018.12.016&gt;`_
         * `L. Jones et al. &lt;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s40679-015-0008-4&gt;`_
         
         For specific simulation purposes, mainly in an effort to digitally repeat
         or simulate the experiment, it is tempting to consider dynamics of the instrument,
         implemented as time-dependent functional descriptions of e.g. lens excitations,
         beam shape functions, trajectories of groups of electrons and ions,
         or detector noise models. This warrants to document the time-dependent
         details of individual components of the microscope
         as is implemented in :ref:`NXevent_data_em`.
    </doc>
    <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included
             when the snapshot time interval started. If the user wishes to specify an
             interval of time that the snapshot should represent during which the instrument
             was stable and configured using specific settings and calibrations,
             the start_time is the start (left bound of the time interval) while
             the end_time specifies the end (right bound) of the time interval.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO 8601 time code with local time zone offset to UTC information included
             when the snapshot time interval ended.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="event_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Identifier of a specific state and setting of the microscope.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="event_type" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Which specific event/measurement type. Examples are:
             
             * In-lens/backscattered electron, usually has quadrants
             * Secondary_electron, image, topography, fractography, overview images
             * Backscattered_electron, image, Z or channeling contrast (ECCI)
             * Bright_field, image, TEM
             * Dark_field, image, crystal defects
             * Annular dark field, image (medium- or high-angle), TEM
             * Diffraction, image, TEM, or a comparable technique in the SEM
             * Kikuchi, image, SEM EBSD and TEM diffraction
             * X-ray spectra (point, line, surface, volume), composition EDS/EDX(S)
             * Electron energy loss spectra for points, lines, surfaces, TEM
             * Auger, spectrum, (low Z contrast element composition)
             * Cathodoluminescence (optical spectra)
             * Ronchigram, image, alignment utility specifically in TEM
             * Chamber, e.g. TV camera inside the chamber, education purposes.
             
             This field may also be used for storing additional information
             about the event. For which there is at the moment no other place.
             
             In the long run such free-text field description should be avoided as
             they are difficult to machine-interpret. Instead, reference should be given
             to refactoring these descriptions into structured metadata.
             The reason why in this base class the field event_type is nonetheless kept
             is to offer a place whereby practically users may enter data for
             follow-up modifications to support arriving at an improved :ref:`NXevent_data_em` base class.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXimage_r_set_diff"/>
    <group type="NXimage_r_set"/>
    <group type="NXimage_c_set"/>
    <group type="NXspectrum_set"/>
    <group name="em_lab" type="NXinstrument">
        <doc>
             (Meta)data of the dynamics and changes of the microscope during the event.
        </doc>
        <!--no need to duplicate the fabrication because that should remain the-->
        <group type="NXchamber"/>
        <group type="NXebeam_column"/>
        <group type="NXibeam_column"/>
        <group type="NXoptical_system_em"/>
        <group type="NXdetector"/>
        <group type="NXpump"/>
        <group type="NXstage_lab"/>
    </group>
    <!--(NXactuator):-->
    <group type="NXuser"/>
    <group type="NXinteraction_vol_em"/>
</definition>
