<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXimage_set_em_kikuchi" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <symbol name="n_sc">
            <doc>
                 Number of scanned points. Scan point may have none, one, or more pattern.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_p">
            <doc>
                 Number of diffraction pattern.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_y">
            <doc>
                 Number of pixel per Kikuchi pattern in the slow direction.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_x">
            <doc>
                 Number of pixel per Kikuchi pattern in the fast direction.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Measured set of electron backscatter diffraction data, aka Kikuchi pattern.
         Kikuchi pattern are the raw data for computational workflows in the field
         of orientation (imaging) microscopy. The technique is especially used in
         materials science and materials engineering.
         
         Based on a fuse of the `M. A. Jackson et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1186/2193-9772-3-4&gt;`_
         of the DREAM.3D community and the open H5OINA format of Oxford Instruments
         `P. Pinard et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S1431927621006103&gt;`_
         
         EBSD can be used, usually with FIB/SEM microscopes, for three-dimensional
         orientation microscopy. So-called serial section analyses. For a detailed
         overview of these techniques see e.g.
         
         * `M. A. Groeber et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1186/2193-9772-3-5&gt;`_  
         * `A. J. Schwartz et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4757-3205-4&gt;`_  
         * `P. A. Rottman et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.mattod.2021.05.003&gt;`_  
         
         With serial-sectioning this involves however always a sequence of measuring,
         milling. In this regard, each serial section (measuring) and milling
         is an own NXevent_data_em instance and thus there such a three-dimensional
         characterization should be stored as a set of two-dimensional data,
         with as many NXevent_data_em instances as sections were measured.
         
         These measured serial sectioning images need virtually always post-processing
         to arrive at the aligned and cleaned image stack before a respective digital
         model of the inspected microstructure can be analyzed. The resulting volume
         is often termed a so-called (representative) volume element (RVE).
         Several software packages are available for performing this post-processing.
         For now we do not consider metadata of these post-processing steps
         as a part of this base class because the connection between the large variety
         of such post-processing steps and the measured electron microscopy data
         is usually very small.
         
         If we envision a (knowledge) graph for EBSD it consists of individual
         sub-graphs which convey information about the specimen preparation,
         the measurement of the specimen in the electron microscope,
         the indexing of the collected Kikuchi pattern stack,
         eventual post-processing of the indexed orientation image
         via similarity grouping algorithms to yield (grains, texture).
         Conceptually these post-processing steps are most frequently
         serving the idea to reconstruct quantitatively so-called
         microstructural features (grains, phases, interfaces). Materials scientists
         use these features according to the multi-scale materials modeling paradigm
         to infer material properties. They do so by quantifying correlations between
         the spatial arrangement of the features, their individual properties,
         and (macroscopic) properties of materials.
    </doc>
    <!--a collection of pattern-related metadata-->
    <group type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
             Details how Kikuchi pattern were processed from the detector readings.
             Scientists interested in EBSD should inspect the respective NXem_ebsd
             application definition which can be used as a partner application definition
             to detail substantially more details to this processing.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group name="stack" type="NXdata">
        <doc>
             Collected Kikuchi pattern as an image stack. As raw and closest to the
             first retrievable measured data as possible, i.e. do not use this
             container to store already averaged, filtered or whatever post-processed
             pattern unless these are generated unmodifiably by the instrument
             given the way how the instrument and control software was configured
             for your microscope session.
        </doc>
        <field name="scan_point_identifier" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Array which resolves the scan point to which each pattern belongs.
                 Scan points are evaluated in sequence starting from scan point zero
                 until scan point n_sc - 1. Evaluating the cumulated of this array
                 decodes which pattern in intensity belong to which scan point.
                 In an example we may assume we collected three scan points. For the first
                 we measure one pattern, for the second we measure three pattern,
                 for the last we measure no pattern.
                 The values of scan_point_identifier will be 0, 1, 1, 1, as we have
                 measured four pattern in total.
                 
                 In most cases usually one pattern is averaged by the detector for
                 some amount of time and then reported as one pattern. Use compressed
                 arrays allows to store the scan_point_identifier efficiently.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_p"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="data_counts" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Signal intensity. For so-called three-dimensional or serial sectioning
                 EBSD it is necessary to follow a sequence of specimen surface preparation
                 and data collection. In this case users should collect the data for each
                 serial sectioning step in an own instance of NXimage_set_em_kikuchi.
                 All eventual post-processing of these measured data should be documented
                 via NXebsd, resulting microstructure representations should be stored
                 as NXms.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="3">
                <dim index="1" value="n_p"/>
                <dim index="2" value="n_y"/>
                <dim index="3" value="n_x"/>
            </dimensions>
            <!--n_p fast 2, n_y faster 1, n_x fastest 0
in axes fast to fastest
while for _indices fastest to fast-->
            <attribute name="long_name">
                <doc>
                     Kikuchi pattern intensity
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--\@signal: intensity
\@axes: [pattern_identifier, ypos, xpos]
\@xpos_indices: 0
\@ypos_indices: 1
\@pattern_identifier_indices: 2-->
        <field name="pattern_identifier" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Pattern are enumerated starting from 0 to n_p - 1.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_p"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="long_name">
                <doc>
                     Kikuchi pattern identifier
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="axis_y" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                 Pixel coordinate along the y direction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_y"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="long_name">
                <doc>
                     Label for the y axis
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="axis_x" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                 Pixel coordinate along the x direction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_x"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="long_name">
                <doc>
                     Label for the x axis
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
    </group>
    <!--maybe time code data when the pattern were taken?
key is it all happened in between the time defined in NXevent_data_em
optionally link to NXebsd instance?-->
</definition>
