<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<definition category="application" extends="NXobject" name="NXIVtemp" type="group" xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<doc>Draft application definition for temperature dependent IV curve measurements. In this application definition, times should be specified always together with a UTC offset.</doc>
	<symbols>
		<doc>Variables used throughout the document, e.g. dimensions and important parameters</doc>
		<symbol name="N_data_points">
			<doc>Number of elements in the scanned voltage array</doc>
		</symbol>
		<symbol name="N_variables">
			<doc>Number of additional variables that are changed with the temperature (can be understood as columns next to the temperature)</doc>
		</symbol>
		<symbol name="N_different_temperatures">
			<doc>Number of different temperatures that are set</doc>
		</symbol>
	</symbols>
	<group type="NXentry">
		<doc>This is the application definition describing temperature dependent IV curve measurements. For this a temperature is set. After reaching the temperature a voltage sweep is performed and for each voltage a current is measured. Then the next desired temperature is set and an IV measurement is performed.

The application definition defines: - elements of the experimental instrument - calibration information if available - parameters used to tune the state of the sample - sample description</doc>
		<field name="definition" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>An application definition for temperature dependent IV curve measurements.</doc>
			<attribute name="version" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Version number to identify which definition of this application definition was used for this entry/data.</doc>
			</attribute>
			<attribute name="url" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>URL where to find further material (documentation, examples) relevant to the application definition</doc>
			</attribute>
		</field>
		<field name="experiment_identifier" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>Unique identifier of the experiment, such as a (globally persistent) unique identifier. - The identifier is usually defined by the facility or principle investigator. - The identifier enables to link experiments to e.g. proposals.</doc>
		</field>
		<field name="experiment_description" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>Description of the exact experiment performed.</doc>
		</field>
		<field name="start_time" recommended="true" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
			<doc>UTC offset should be specifiec.</doc>
		</field>
		<group optional="true" type="NXprocess">
			<doc>Define the program that was used to generate the results file(s) with measured data and metadata.</doc>
			<field name="program" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Commercial or otherwise defined given name of the program (or a link to the instrument software).</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="version" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Either version with build number, commit hash, or description of a (online) repository where the source code of the program and build instructions can be found so that the program can be configured in such a way that result files can be created ideally in a deterministic manner.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="program_url" recommended="true" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Website of the software.</doc>
			</field>
		</group>
		<group minOccurs="1" name="operator" type="NXuser">
			<doc>Contact information of at least the user of the instrument or the investigator who performed this experiment. Adding multiple users if relevant is recommended.</doc>
			<field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Name of the user.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="affiliation" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Name of the affiliation of the user at the point in time when the experiment was performed.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="address" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Full address (street, street number, ZIP, city, country) of the user's affiliation.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="email" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Email address of the user.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="orcid" recommended="true" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Author ID defined by https://orcid.org/.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="telephone_number" recommended="true" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Official telephone number of the user.</doc>
			</field>
		</group>
		<group type="NXinstrument">
			<doc>General properties of the temperature dependent IV curve measurements equipment</doc>
			<group name="IVvoltage_source" type="NXsensor">
				<doc>Specify the used voltage source used in the voltage sweep for the IV measurement.</doc>
				<field name="model" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Free-text desribing the model and make of the voltage source which is used for the IV sweep measurement</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="name" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Custom name of the voltage source for the IV sweep given by the user/institution</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="measurement" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Free-text describing the measurement performed in a few words</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="type" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Free-text describing the type of voltage setting: an internal sweep using the functionality of the voltage supply, or a set/wait/read/repeat mechanism.</doc>
				</field>
			</group>
			<group name="IVcurrent_source" type="NXsensor">
				<doc>Specify the used current source used in the voltage sweep for the IV measurement.</doc>
				<field name="model" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Free-text desribing the model and make of the current source which is used for the IV sweep measurement</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="name" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Custom name of the current source for the IV sweep given by the user/institution</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="measurement" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Free-text describing the measurement performed in a few words</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="type" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Free-text describing the type of current measuring: an internal sweep using the functionality of the voltage supply, or a set/wait/read/repeat mechanism.</doc>
				</field>
			</group>
			<group name="calibration" optional="true" type="NXsubentry">
				<doc>Calibration of the temperature sensor is possible</doc>
				<field name="calibration_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
					<doc>ISO8601 datum when calibration was last performed before this measurement. UTC offset should be specifiec.</doc>
				</field>
			</group>
			<group name="temperature_control" optional="true" type="NXsubentry">
				<doc>Describes the system for controlling the temperature if temperature control was used.</doc>
				<field name="type" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>What kind of temperature control was used? PID, custom temp control?</doc>
				</field>
				<group name="PID_settings" optional="true" type="NXenvironment">
					<doc>Specify the settings of the PID temperature controller: K_p, K_i, and K_d values used for the temperature control</doc>
					<field name="K_p_value" type="NX_NUMBER">
						<doc>Proportional term. The proportional term produces an output value that is proportional to the current error value. The proportional response can be adjusted by multiplying the error by a constant Kp, called the proportional gain constant.</doc>
					</field>
					<field name="K_i_value" type="NX_NUMBER">
						<doc>The contribution from the integral term is proportional to both the magnitude of the error and the duration of the error. The integral in a PID controller is the sum of the instantaneous error over time and gives the accumulated offset that should have been corrected previously. The accumulated error is then multiplied by the integral gain (Ki) and added to the controller output</doc>
					</field>
					<field name="K_d_value" type="NX_NUMBER">
						<doc>The derivative of the process error is calculated by determining the slope of the error over time and multiplying this rate of change by the derivative gain K_d. The magnitude of the contribution of the derivative term to the overall control action is termed the derivative gain, K_d</doc>
					</field>
				</group>
				<field name="temp_sensor_type" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Specify the temperature sensor that was used</doc>
					<enumeration>
						<item value="thermocouple"/>
						<item value="thermistor"/>
						<item value="RTD"/>
						<item value="other"/>
					</enumeration>
				</field>
				<field name="other_temp_sensor" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>If you specified 'other' as temperature sensor, please write down what it is.</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="raw_temp_data" optional="true" type="NX_NUMBER">
					<dimensions rank="1">
						<dim index="1" value="N_raw_temp_data"/>
					</dimensions>
					<doc>Data of the most principal measurement of the temperature. For example resistance of a Pt1000.</doc>
				</field>
				<field name="conversion_function" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
					<doc>Algebraic function that is used to determine temperature from the raw_temp_data. All values should be given in SI units.</doc>
				</field>
			</group>
		</group>
		<group type="NXsample">
			<doc>Properties of the sample, its history, the sample environment and experimental conditions (e.g. surrounding medium, temperature, pressure etc.), along with the data (data type, wavelength array, measured data).</doc>
			<field name="sample_name" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Descriptive name of the sample</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="sample_history" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Ideally, a reference to the location or a unique (globally persistent) identifier (e.g.) of e.g. another file which gives as many as possible details of the material, its microstructure. In the case that such a detailed history of the sample is not available, use this field as a free-text description to specify details of the sample and its preparation.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="preparation_date" recommended="true" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
				<doc>ISO 8601 date with time zone specified. UTC offset should be specifiec.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="data_identifier" type="NX_NUMBER">
				<doc>An identifier to correlate data to the experimental conditions, if several were used in this measurement; typically an index of 0 - N</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="measured_data" type="NX_NUMBER">
				<doc>Resulting data from the measurement, described by data type.</doc>
				<dimensions rank="3">
					<dim index="3" value="N_different_temperatures"/>
					<dim index="2" value="N_variables"/>
					<dim index="1" value="N_data_points"/>
				</dimensions>
			</field>
			<field name="environment_conditions" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Information about external parameters that have influenced the sample.</doc>
			</field>
			<field name="varied_parameters" optional="true" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Indicates which parameter was changed. Its definition must exist below. The specified variable has to be number_of_runs long, providing the parameters for each data set.</doc>
				<enumeration>
					<item value="temperature"/>
				</enumeration>
			</field>
		</group>
		<group name="plot" optional="true" type="NXdata">
			<doc>A default view of the data. The current (y-axis) should be plotted against the voltage (x-axis) with color coding for the temperature of each IV-curve</doc>
			<attribute name="axes">
				<doc>We recommend to use voltage as a default attribute</doc>
			</attribute>
		</group>
	</group>
</definition>
