<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2022 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXiv_bias" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Application definition for bias devices.
    </doc>
    <field name="bias" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
        <doc>
             Applied a voltage between tip and sample.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="tunneling_resistor" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
             The ratio between the tunneling current at the sample surface and the bias voltage 
             applied between the sample and the tip.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="calibration" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Calibration of the Bias output (V/V).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="offset" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
        <doc>
             Allows compensating for an offset in Bias. Hardware parameter offset.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="modulated_signal_bias" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
        <doc>
             Sets the amplitude (in physical units of the modulated signal) of the sine
             modulation.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXbias_spectroscopy">
        <doc>
             Bias sweeps while measuring arbitrary channels with I(V) curves.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <field name="channels" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Select the channels to record.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="reset_bias" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
             When selected, the Bias voltage returns to the initial value (before starting the sweep) at 
             the end of the spectroscopy measurement (default). When not selected, Bias remains at the 
             last value of the sweep. This is useful e.g. when combining several sweep segments. Example
             for an automated measurement (using Programming Interface): switch off Z-Controller, start 
             spectroscopy sweep segments (only fwd sweep, no reset bias), set bias back to initial value,
             switch on Z-Controller.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="record_final_z" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
             Select whether to record the Z position during Z averaging time at the end of
             the sweep (after Z control time) and store the average value in the header of
             the file when saving. Using this option increases the sweep time by Z averaging
             time.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="lock_in_run" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
             Select whether to set the Lock-In to run during the measurement. When using this
             feature, make sure the Lock-In is configured correctly and settling times are
             set to twice the Lock-In period at least. This option is ignored when Lock-In is
             already running. This option is disabled if the Sweep Mode is MLS and the flag
             to configure the Lock-In per segment in the Multiline segment editor is set.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="integration_time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Time during which the spectroscopy data are acquired and averaged.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="number_of_sweeps" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Number of sweeps to measure and average.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="sweep_start" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
        <doc>
             The first bias values of the sweep.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="sweep_end" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
        <doc>
             The last bias values of the sweep.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="num_pixel" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Define the sweep number of points, that is, the maximum spectrum resolution eq.
             Bias window divide by Num Pixel.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="z_avg_time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Duration over which the Z position is recorded and averaged before and after the
             sweep (the latter only if Record final Z position is selected in the Advanced
             section). After the initial Z averaging time, if Z-Controller to Hold is
             selected in the Advanced section, the Z-Controller is set to hold and the tip is
             placed at the previously averaged Z position (plus Z offset).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="sw_filter_type" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Select a filter to smooth the displayed data. When saving, if any filter
             selected, filtered data are saved to file along with the unfiltered data.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="sw_ilter_order" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Filter order of a dynamic filter or width (in number of points) for the gaussian
             filter.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="sw_filter_cutoff_frq" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Cutoff frequency for dynamic filters.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="z_offset" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
        <doc>
             Offset added to the initial averaged position Zaver before starting to sweep.
             This parameter is disabled when Z-Controller to Hold is deselected in the
             Advanced section. The LED “Alt” next to the Z offset indicates if an alternate
             Z-controller setpoint is enabled.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="settling_time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             time to wait after changing the bias to the next level and before starting to
             acquire data.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="end_settling_time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Time to wait after the sweep has finished and the bias is ramped to the initial
             value.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="z_control_time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Time during which the Z-Controller is enabled once a sweep has finished. When
             averaging multiple sweeps (i.e. Sweeps&gt;1), the Z-Controller is enabled for this
             duration between each sweep. After the last sweep, it will wait the specified
             time before continuing a running scan. This ensures each sweep reliably starts
             from the same position. This parameter is disabled when Z-Controller to Hold is
             deselected in the Advanced section.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="max_sew_rate" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Maximum rate at which the bias changes (before, during and after sweeping).
             (V/s)
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="backward_sweep" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
             Select whether to measure the backward (return) sweep or the forward only.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="z_controller_hold" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
             Select whether to set the Z-Controller on hold (i.e. disabled) during the sweep.
             It is selected by default. When deselected, Z-offset and Z-control time
             parameters are disabled.
        </doc>
    </field>
</definition>
