<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXmicrostructure" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <!--, and Volterra line defects (dislocation, disconnection, disclination).-->
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <!--one-dimensional sections of either projections (see below) or true one-dimensional cuts across a volume of material-->
        <symbol name="n_c_one">
            <doc>
                 The number of one-dimensional crystal projections
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_i_one">
            <doc>
                 The number of one-dimensional interface projections
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <!--n_<line defect>_one, n_<point defect>_one are hypothetical scenarios such as line defect hitting right into a point
two-dimensional projections of three-dimensional objects using E. E. Underwood notation
crystals/grains are projections that are delineated by projections of interface, i.e. interface lines which meet at projections of triple lines aka triple points-->
        <symbol name="n_c_two">
            <doc>
                 The number of two-dimensional crystal projections
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_i_two">
            <doc>
                 The number of two-dimensional interface projections
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_tj_two">
            <doc>
                 The number of two-dimensional triple line projections
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_ld_two">
            <doc>
                 The number of two-dimensional line defect projections
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <!--n_<point defect>_two is the hypothetical scenario when a point defect lies right in the projection plane
three-dimensional real objects, volumetrically characterized
crystals are delineated by interfaces that are delineated by triple lines that meet at quad junctions-->
        <symbol name="n_c_three">
            <doc>
                 The number of crystals (grain and sub-grain are exact synonyms for crystal).
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_i_three">
            <doc>
                 The number of interfaces (grain boundary and phase boundary are subclasses of
                 interfaces).
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_tj_three">
            <doc>
                 The number of triple junctions (triple line is a exact synonym for triple
                 junction, triple point is projection of a triple junction).
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_qj_three">
            <doc>
                 The number of quadruple junctions.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <!--  n_ld_three:
    The number of line defects.-->
        <symbol name="d">
            <doc>
                 The dimensionality of the representation that needs to match the value for
                 configuration/dimensionality
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Base class to describe a microstructure, its structural aspects, associated descriptors, properties.
         
         Whether one uses a continuum or atomic scale description of materials, these are always a model
         the true internal structure of a material. Such models are useful as they enable a coarse graining and
         categorizing of properties and representational aspects from which measured or simulated descriptions
         can be correlated with properties i.e. descriptor values.
         
         Keep in mind that most specimens are thermo-chemo-mechanically processed prior their characterization.
         Therefore, the characterized microstructure may not have probe the same structure as of the untreated
         sample from which the region-of-interests on the specimen were probed.
         
         Fields such as time and increment enable a quantification of the spatiotemporal evolution of a materials
         structure by using multiple instances of NXmicrostructure. Both measurements and simulation virtually
         always sample this evolution. Most microscopy techniques support to generate only a two-dimensional
         representation (projection) of the characterized material, often materials are characterized only for
         specific states with much history or via sampling coarsely in time relative to the timescale at which the
         physical phenomena take place because of technical and practical limitations.
         
         The term microstructural feature covers here crystals and all sorts of crystal defects within the material. 
         A key challenge with the description representations and properties of microstructural features is that
         features with different dimensionality exist and combinations of features of different dimensionality are
         frequently expected to be documented with intuitive naming conventions using flat property lists.
         For these key-value dictionaries often folksonomies are used often relying on ad hoc documentation
         of such dictionaries in the literature and the metadata section of public data repositories.
         
         NXmicrostructure is an attempt to standardize these descriptions stronger.
         
         The descriptive variety is large especially for junctions. Like crystals and interfaces junctions are features in
         three-dimensional Euclidean space even if they are formed maybe only through a monolayer or pearl chain of atoms.
         Either way the local atomic and electronic environment is different compared to the situation of an ideal crystal
         which gives rise to a plethora of useful configurations of which some cause that materials have useful properties.
         
         Junctions are assumed, like crystals and interfaces to represent groups of atoms that have specific descriptor values
         which are different to other features. As an example a triple junction is practically a three-dimensional defect as its atoms
         are arrange in three-dimensional space but the characteristics of that defect can often be reduced to a lower-dimensional
         description such as a triple point or a triple line. Therefore, different representations can be used to describe the location,
         shape, and structure of the defect. As different types of crystal defects can interact there is a substantial number of
         in principle characterizable and representable objects. Take a triple line as an example. It is a tubular feature built from three
         adjoining interfaces. However, dislocations as line defects can interact with triple lines. Therefore, one can also argue that
         along a triple line there can be dislocation-line-triple-line junctions, likewise dislocations form own junctions.
         
         It is not the aim of this base class to cover all these cases, rather this base class currently provides examples how the
         typically most relevant types of features can be represented using a combination of base classes in NeXus. Currently,
         these are crystals, interfaces, triple lines, quadruple junctions.
         
         The description attempt here took inspiration from `E. E. Underwood &lt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2818.1972.tb03709.x&gt;`_
         and E. E. Underwood's book on Quantitative Stereology published 1970 to categorize features based on their dimensionality.
         
         Identifiers can be defined either implicitly or explicitly. Identifiers for implicit indexing are defined
         on the interval :math:`[identifier\_offset, identifier\_offset + cardinality - 1]`.
    </doc>
    <!--as e.g. a result of one grain reconstruction with an algorithm with MTex or the grain/phase i.e. interface network reconstruction software in commercial tools
the idea is we may wish to run as many grain reconstructions as we want and add details about the processing used for each of them if needed-->
    <field name="comment" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Discouraged free-text field for leaving comments.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="date" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
        <doc>
             ISO8601 with offset to local time zone included when a timestamp is required.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Measured or simulated physical time stamp for this microstructure snapshot.
             Not to be confused with wall-clock timing or profiling data.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="iteration" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Iteration or increment counter.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group name="configuration" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
             Group where to store details about the configuration and parameterization of algorithms
             used whereby microstructural features were identified.
        </doc>
        <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Dimensionality of Euclidean space in which the analysis is performed.
                 
                 This field can be used e.g. by a research data management system to identify
                 if the description specifies one-, two-, or three-dimensional microstructural representations.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="1"/>
                <item value="2"/>
                <item value="3"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="algorithm" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Algorithm whereby interfaces between crystals were reconstructed.
                 
                 * Disorientation clustering groups nearby material points based on their crystallographic disorientation
                 * Fast multiscale clustering based on `D. Kushnir et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.patcog.2006.04.007&gt;`_
                 * Markov chain clustering `F. Niessen et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1107/S1600576721011560&gt;`_
            </doc>
            <!--could also be used to specify algorithms for precipitate detection-->
            <enumeration>
                <item value="unknown"/>
                <item value="disorientation_clustering"/>
                <item value="fast_multiscale_clustering"/>
                <item value="markov_chain_clustering"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="disorientation_threshold" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANGLE">
            <doc>
                 Threshold to define at which disorientation angle to assume two crystalline regions have a significant
                 orientation difference that warrants to assume that there exists an interface between the two regions.
            </doc>
        </field>
    </group>
    <!--use controlled vocabulary terms grid, point, line, surface, volume, use singular term when instantiating-->
    <group type="NXcg_grid"/>
    <group type="NXcg_point_set"/>
    <group type="NXcg_polyline_set"/>
    <group type="NXcg_triangle_set"/>
    <group type="NXcg_polyhedron_set"/>
    <!--constructive solid geometry to describe curved features
(NXcsg):
(NXcontinuous_function):
examples for specific frequently discussed microstructural features-->
    <group name="crystal" type="NXobject">
        <doc>
             One- or two-dimensional projections, or three-dimensional representations of crystals.
             
             An example for a volume bounded by other crystal defects. Crystals can be grains of
             different phases, precipitates, dispersoids; there are many terms used specifically in
             the materials engineering community.
             
             Typically, crystals are measured on the surface of a sample using with optical or electron microscopy
             represented or simulated as a set of pixel, voxel, or polygons and their polyline boundaries.
             Using X-ray diffraction methods crystals can be observed in bulk specimens.
        </doc>
        <!--maybe some enum what this is-->
        <field name="representation" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Reference to an instance of:
                 
                 * :ref:`NXcg_polyline_set` for a one-dimensional representation as only a projection is available (like in linear intercept analysis)
                 * :ref`NXcg_polygon_set` for a two-dimensional representation as only a projection is available (like in most experiments)
                 * :ref:`NXcg_polyhedron_set` or :ref:`NXcg_grid` for regularly pixelated or voxelated representation in one, two, or three dimensions
                   (like in computer simulations or 3D experiments)
                 
                 which represent the geometrical entities of the discretization.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="number_of_crystals" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 How many crystals are distinguished.
                 
                 Crystals are listed irrespective of the phase to which these are assigned.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="number_of_phases" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 How many phases are distinguished.
                 
                 Phases are typically distinguished based on statistical thermodynamics argument and crystal structure.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="crystal_identifier_offset" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 First identifier whereby to identify crystals implicitly.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="crystal_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Identifier whereby to identify each crystal explicitly.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="phase_identifier_offset" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 First identifier whereby to identify phases implicitly.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="phase_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Identifier whereby to identify phase for each crystal explicitly.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <!--EXAMPLES FOR DESCRIPTOR VALUES, SUMMARY STATISTICS-->
        <field name="boundary_contact" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
            <doc>
                 True or false value, one for each crystal, to communicate whether that feature
                 makes contact with the edge of the ROI.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="orientation_spread" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANGLE">
            <doc>
                 Average disorientation angle for each crystal between individual orientations
                 of that crystal evaluated as a summary statistic for all probed positions vs the
                 average disorientation of that crystal.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="length" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                 Length of each crystal
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="area" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_AREA">
            <doc>
                 Area of each crystal.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="volume" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLUME">
            <doc>
                 Volume of each crystal
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="interface" type="NXobject">
        <doc>
             One- or two-dimensional projections or three-dimensional representation of interfaces
             between crystals as topological entities equivalent to dual_junctions.
             
             An example for a surface defect. Most important are interfaces such as grain and phase boundaries
             but factually interfaces also exist between the environment and crystals exposed at the
             surface of the specimen or internal surfaces like between crystals, cracks and pores.
        </doc>
        <field name="representation" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Reference to an instance of:
                 
                 * :ref:`NXcg_point_set` for a one-dimensional representation as only a projection is available (as in linear intercept analyses)
                 * :ref:`NXcg_polyline_set` or :ref:`NXcg_polygon_set` for a two-dimensional representation as only a projection is available (like in most experiments)
                 * :ref:`NXcg_grid` for regularly pixelated or voxelated representation in one, two, or three dimensions using (boolean) masks
                   (like in computer simulations or 3D experiments)
                 
                 which represent the geometrical entities of the discretization.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="number_of_interfaces" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 How many interfaces are distinguished.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 First identifier whereby to identify interfaces implicitly.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Identifier whereby to identify each interface explicitly.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <!--topological view, interface specification through the the pair of crystals sharing an interface-->
        <field name="crystal_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of pairs of crystal_identifier for each interface.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="2"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifiers whereby to resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="phase_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of pairs of phase_identifier for each interface.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="2"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifiers whereby to resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--topological view, interface specification through the pair of triple line projections (i.e. triple points) adjoining the interface-->
        <field name="triple_junction_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of pairs of triple_junction_identifier for each interface.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="2"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifiers whereby to resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--EXAMPLES FOR DESCRIPTOR VALUES-->
        <field name="boundary_contact" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
            <doc>
                 True or false value, one for each crystal, to communicate whether that feature
                 makes contact with the edge of the ROI.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="surface_energy" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
            <doc>
                 Gibbs free surface energy for each interface.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="mobility" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
            <doc>
                 Non-intrinsic mobility of each interface.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="length" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                 The length of each interface if only projections are available.
                 
                 This is not necessarily the same as the length of the individual
                 polyline segments whereby the interface is discretized.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="area" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_AREA">
            <doc>
                 The surface area of all interfaces.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="triple_junction" type="NXobject">
        <doc>
             Projections of or representations of junctions at which three interfaces meet.
             
             An example for a line defect. Triple junctions are characterized as triple lines or triple points as their projections,
             or junctions observed between crystals (at the specimen surface exposed to an environment)
             (including wetting phenomena) or inside the specimen (crack, pores).
        </doc>
        <field name="representation" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Reference to an instance of:
                 
                 * :ref:`NXcg_point_set` for a one-dimensional representation as only a projection is available (like in most experiments)
                 * :ref:`NXcg_polyline_set` for a two-dimensional representation as only a projection is available
                 * :ref:`NXcg_polygon_set` for a two-dimensional representation in the (seldom) case of sufficient spatial resolution
                   and the line in the projection plane or cases where triple junction locations are approximated e.g. using a set of triangles
                 * :ref:`NXcg_polyhedron_set` for a three-dimensional representation via e.g. a representation of Voronoi cells about atoms
                 * :ref:`NXcg_grid` for regularly pixelated or voxelated representation in one, two, or three dimensions using (boolean) masks
                 
                 which represent the geometrical entities of the discretization.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="number_of_junctions" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Number of triple junctions.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 First identifier to identify triple junctions implicitly.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Identifier to identify each triple junction explicitly.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <!--various strategies are used to talk about aspects of triple junctions, some examples follow
example i) triple points as projections of triple lines have locations-->
        <field name="location" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of identifier for positions whereby to identify the location of each
                 junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifiers whereby to resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="position" type="NX_INT" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                 Explicit positions.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="d"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="crystal_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of tuples of identifier of crystals connected to the junction for each
                 triple junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="3"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <!--example ii) three interfaces (maybe projections of them) meet at a triple junction-->
        <field name="interface_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of tuples of identifier of interfaces connected to the junction for each
                 triple junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="3"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific interface identifiers whereby to resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--example iii) three polyline segments meet at a triple junction, polyline segments of discretized interface segments-->
        <field name="polyline_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of tuples of identifier for polyline segments connected to the junction for
                 each triple junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="3"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific polyline identifiers whereby to resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--example iv) e.g. crystals of three different phases meet at a triple junction
EXAMPLES FOR DESCRIPTOR VALUES-->
        <field name="boundary_contact" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
            <doc>
                 True or false value, one for each crystal, to communicate whether that feature
                 makes contact with the edge of the ROI.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="line_energy" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
            <doc>
                 Specific line energy of each triple junction
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="mobility" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
            <doc>
                 Non-intrinsic mobility of each triple junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="length" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                 The length of each triple junction.
                 
                 This is not necessarily the same as the length of the individual
                 polyline segments whereby the junction is discretized.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="volume" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLUME">
            <doc>
                 The volume of the each triple junction
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="quadruple_junction" type="NXobject">
        <doc>
             Quadruple junctions as a region where four crystals meet.
             
             An example for a point defect.
        </doc>
        <field name="representation" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Reference to an instance of:
                 
                 * :ref:`NXcg_point_set`
                 * :ref:`NXcg_grid` for regularly pixelated or voxelated representation in one, two, or three dimensions using (boolean) masks
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="number_of_junctions" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Number of quadruple junctions.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 First identifier to identify quadruple junctions implicitly.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Identifier to identify each quadruple junction explicitly.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <!--different scenarios can be envised how quadruple_junctions are discussed
example i) quadruple point locations explicitly-->
        <field name="location" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of identifier for positions whereby to identify the location of each
                 junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific point identifier whereby to resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="position" type="NX_INT" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                 Explicit positions.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="3"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <!--example ii) four crystals meet at a quadruple junction-->
        <field name="crystal_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of tuples of identifier of crystals connected to the junction for each
                 junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="4"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifier to instances of crystal identifiers whereby to resolve
                     ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="interface_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of tuples of identifier of interfaces connected to the junction for each
                 junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="4"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifier to instances of interface identifiers whereby to resolve
                     ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--example iii) e.g. three triple lines meet at a quadruple junction-->
        <field name="triple_junction_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of tuples of identifier for triple junctions connected to the junction for
                 each quadruple junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="3"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifier to instances of triple junction identifiers whereby to
                     resolve ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--example iv) crystals of eventually four different phases meet at a quadruple junction-->
        <field name="phase_identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 Set of tuples of identifier for phases of crystals connected to the junction for
                 each quadruple junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
                <dim index="2" value="4"/>
            </dimensions>
            <attribute name="use_these" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     The specific identifier to instances of phase identifier whereby to resolve
                     ambiguities.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <!--EXAMPLES FOR DESCRIPTOR VALUES-->
        <field name="boundary_contact" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
            <doc>
                 True or false value, one for each crystal, to communicate whether that feature
                 makes contact with the edge of the ROI.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="energy" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
            <doc>
                 Energy of the quadruple_junction as a defect.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="mobility" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
            <doc>
                 Non-intrinsic mobility of each quadruple_junction.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="i"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
    </group>
</definition>
