<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2022 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXms_crystal_set" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="d">
            <doc>
                 The dimensionality of the description.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_objects">
            <doc>
                 The number of objects, which can be crystals, grains, phases or phase field
                 regions.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Base class to describe data about observed crystals in microstructures.
         
         Both experiments and computer simulations support that atoms organize into regions
         which are often separated and interconnected by different types of crystal defects.
         Crystalline regions show a long-range periodic arrangement (compared to the 
         length scale of nearest neighbor distances).
         Although the group of atoms forming a crystal is virtually never static, due
         to diffusive in- and outflux of atoms and thermal fluctuations of the atoms
         about their equilibrium positions, crystals are relevant persistent features
         in microstructures. The size of crystals can span orders of magnitude from
         meters to nanometers.
         
         There are two different and (somewhat extremal) views on crystals and how to
         describe their eventually very rich variety of internal defects. Either 
         crystals can be coarse-grained into continuum objects or not. In the second case
         they need a more advanced internal description of defects inside the grains
         which convinces many that eventually a grain has to be viewed from its
         individual atoms, its material points, and the hierarchy of structural motifs
         local arrangements in the crystal.
         
         Despite these details, identifying crystals is foremost a labeling task.
         Atoms are clustered into structural motifs and (noise) and these motifs
         are again clustered into crystals.
         
         There are two main approaches how crystals are described in mesoscale
         microstructure evolution simulations. Assuming for now transformations in the
         solid state, precipitates, phase regions, sub-grains or grains are examples
         of crystals:
         
         * Objects are either tracked explicitly in the sense that their shape will
           be resolved through the crystal interfaces using e.g. a phase-field, 
           level-set, grid, or finite element mesh based models and implementations.
           These simulations may keep track of explicit crystal/grain/object-related
           quantities. Such models can treat the interface network implicitly while
           still focusing their description on the explicit crystals.
           During such simulations the interface is often analyzed on-the-fly,
           because of technical demands (like in level-set implementations) or to
           trigger specific situations where it is relevant to resolve the
           position of the interfaces explicitly (like for placing seeds for phases,
           recrystallizing grains etc, or for visualization purposes), demand a
           description of interfaces between crystals.
           For explicitly tracking simulations this base class can be applied as is.
         * Objects are tracked implicitly in the sense that the computational domain
           is discretized into an ensemble of what one can call material points.
           Such models can be described at different length scale: On the one hand
           where atom dynamics are (whether the assumption is substantiated or not)
           homogenized/-able already or not. Each material point is assumed to have
           at least one associated constitutive phase.
           Such simulations usually do not/cannot resolve crystal-related quantities
           without executing an on-the-fly post-processing of snapshot data from
           which the spatial representation of the crystal is recovered.
           An important case are large-strain formalism crystal plasticity methods.
           Here the initial configuration represents most frequently material points
           on a regular grid. Within the course of the simulation this grid gets
           deformed implicitly. The code internally keeps no track of how the cells/
           material points of what is essentially a Voronoi tessellation, are deformed.
           Only in the case when one would like to visualize the deformed configuration,
           a post-processing of the simulation snapshot data is executed which
           recovers the positions of the material points in the deformed configuration
           in the laboratory coordinate system  from which one can then extract a
           representation of grains/precipitates, i.e. crystals.
           It is a signature of such simulations that quantities like orientation
           are defined as material point quantities. This means what constitutes the grain
           needs to be extracted by cluster analyses.
           In this regard, such simulation are essentially matching the representation and
           case of molecular dynamics simulations, with the important difference
           that these track atoms, from whose configuration
           in a snapshot a description has to be computed what are most likely the
           atoms that belong to the volume of the crystal or the interface/defect 
           network.
    </doc>
    <field name="dimensionality" type="NX_POSINT" units="NX_UNITLESS"/>
    <field name="number_of_objects" type="NX_POSINT" units="NX_UNITLESS"/>
    <field name="identifier_offset" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Integer which specifies the first index to be used for distinguishing
             objects. Identifiers are defined either implicitly
             or explicitly. For implicit indexing the identifiers are defined on the
             interval [identifier_offset, identifier_offset+c-1].
             For explicit indexing the identifier array has to be defined.
             
             The identifier_offset field can for example be used to communicate if the
             identifiers are expected to start from 1 (referred to as Fortran-/Matlab-)
             or from 0 (referred to as C-, Python-style index notation) respectively.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="identifier" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
        <doc>
             Integer used to distinguish objects for explicit indexing.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="n_objects"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
    <field name="object_size" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Depending on the value of dimensionality, the area or volume of each object.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="n_objects"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
</definition>
