<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2022 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXms_dislocation_set" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Base class to describe details about dislocations observed in microstructures.
         
         Dislocations are one-dimensional crystal defects whose primary interest is
         that they are the carrier of plastic deformation. Conceptually dislocations
         are a continuum-scale description of how atoms arrange spatio-temporally on
         the one hand as a persistent defect which on the other hand though, when 
         inspected in detail for the atom dynamics and their interaction with other 
         crystal defects manifest as an involved microstructural feature for which 
         very different descriptions are used depending which length-, time-scale, 
         and research question people address.
         
         This is manifested in the large amount of literature on the topic:
         
         * https://www.sciencedirect.com/bookseries/dislocations-in-solids  
         
         Dislocations are one prominent group of representatives for one-dimensional
         features, other defects include disconnections and/or disclinations, and even
         more complicated configurations, especially when one considers not-necessarily
         crystalline materials, quasi crystals. It would be rude to claim that a single
         base class can encompass the entire complexity that this effectively 
         coarse-graining of atomic spatio-temporal configurations has, in an effort 
         to simplicify the description in the hope to arrive at physical models which
         do not need to take into account the location and movement of every atom.
         
         However, it is also a fact that not every description, research question, and 
         thus use cases that one could think of what one should store as data and metadata
         for one-dimensional, primarily line-type crystal defects, is equally relevant
         for an ensemble of research studies.
         
         Thus, for the design of concrete schemata for the purpose of structured storage
         of research data on dislocations or studies where dislocations are measured
         or characterized, one has to prioritize which descriptors and aspects about
         dislocations are likely relevant for a large number of users of a research 
         infrastructure. Consequently, it is possible to narrow down the scope of 
         the base class and application definition.
         
         It is noteworthy to mention that this applies not only to description
         using NeXus, but points to the problem of creating a golden-bullet schema
         capable of handling all possible subtleties.
         
         For now we have to accept that is not yet an ontology of e.g. the above
         understanding of what dislocations are. Pragmatically we thus make the
         following assumptions:
         
         * This base class is essentially a template how specific often referred  
           quantities for one-dimensional crystal defects can be stored.  
         * In practice dislocations have a finite length as they are embedded in a  
           finite specimen and wired into an ensemble of adjoining dislocations  
           or other adjoining crystal defects.  
         * There are the following general approaches of studying/characterizing  
         * 1. Indirect measurements where dislocations characterized statistically.  
           In this case different types of dislocations are distinguished  
           (geometrically-necessary, mobile, immobile), mainly motivated by  
           different constitutive, continuum-models how they are threated in  
           computer simulations with respect to what their effect is on ms evolution.  
         * 2. Electron microscopy measurements of single or several dislocation (bundles)  
           In this case post-processing strategies are necessary which can  
           extract statistical descriptors or d-dimensional reconstructions  
         * 3. Atomic-scale-resolved simulations. In this case the most frequently  
           performed tasks are again post-processing into polyline networks,  
           detailed local investigations of the atomic configurations, or both  
           with or without some correlation.  
         * 4. Analytical approaches whereby dislocations are resolved at the continuum  
           scale, as line defects containing other elementary defects (for instance)  
           in models of disconnection motion), or again atomically resolved treatments.  
         
         From this we can conclude that an NXms_dislocation_set can primarily be
         useful as a wrapper class in which specific details about dislocations
         can be stored in an arbitrarily nested manner.
    </doc>
</definition>
