<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2022 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXms_interface_set" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Base class to describe details about interfaces observed in microstructures.
         
         Classically, interfaces are two-dimensional crystal defects whose relevance is
         that they are agents which trigger crystal growth and discontinuities of the
         crystal at which defects can accumulate and solutes segregate with fundamental
         effect on the properties of materials. Conceptually, interfaces are a
         continuum-scale description of how atoms arrange spatio-temporally. Interfaces
         manifests as persistent defects. When inspected in more detail though they show
         atom dynamics, coarse-grainable into again interactions between line-type
         crystal defects (disconnections) through which interfaces are dynamic and can
         interact with other defects. Owing to this complexity very different
         descriptions are used depending on which length-, time-scale,
         and research question people address.
         
         This is manifested in the large amount of literature on the topic:
         
         * A. P. Sutton et al. ISBN-13 978-0198500612  
         * G. Gottstein et al. ISBN-13 978-1-4200-5436-1  
         * K. Chen et al. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1920504117  
         
         Interfaces, specifically grain and phase boundaries, are representatives of
         two-dimensional microstructural features. It would be rude to claim that a single
         base class can encompass the entire complexity that this effective
         coarse-graining of atomic spatio-temporal configurations has. In the end,
         interfaces are a model, an effort to simplicify the description in the hope
         to arrive at physical models which do not need to take into account the static
         and dynamic details of every atom.
         
         However, it is also a fact that not every description, research question, and 
         thus use cases that one could think of storing as data and metadata for
         interfaces, is equally relevant and useful for an ensemble of research studies.
         
         Thus, for the design of concrete schemes for a structured storage of data on
         interfaces are measured or characterized, one has to prioritize which
         descriptors and aspects about interfaces are likely relevant for a large
         number of users of the research infrastructure. Consequently, it is possible
         to narrow down the scope of this base class.
         
         It is noteworthy to mention that this applies not only to schemes build
         with NeXus, but points to the problem of creating a golden-bullet schema
         that could handle all possible subtleties of interfaces.
         
         For now we have to accept that there is not yet an ontology of e.g. the
         above-mentioned understanding of what interfaces are.
         
         Pragmatically we thus make the following assumptions:
         
         * This base class is essentially a template how specific, often referred to  
           quantities, for two-dimensional crystal defects can be stored.  
         * Coarse-graining point-like features into a curve or surfaces is an  
           ill-posed problem. In practice, it has to be accounted for that interfaces  
           have a finite extent, they are delineated by triple lines and quadruple  
           junctions. Interfaces are thus connected into a three-dimensional network  
           of defects. Interfaces can interact or intersect with other defects  
           (partially or completely, as it is the case for disconnections).  
         
         There are the following general approaches of studying/characterizing:
         
         * Non-atomically resolved measurements of 2D or 3D sections.  
           Examples are optical, electron, X-ray, or atom probe microscopy.  
         * Under specific conditions using electron microscopy, electron tomography  
           (provided numerical post-processing is applied) as well as with atom probe  
           microscopy these measurement can resolve structural motifs of or in the  
           interface plane.  
         * Atomic-scale-resolved simulations. In this case the most frequently  
           performed tasks are again post-processing snapshots with grain identification  
           or graph-based techniques to identify which atoms belong to the regions  
           with local changes or breakdown of the long-range crystal symmetry.  
         * Analytical approaches whereby grain boundaries are resolved at the continuum  
           scale, as surface defects containing other elementary defects (for instance)  
           in models of disconnection motion), using eventual statistical approaches,  
           or again atomically resolved treatments.  
         
         From this we can conclude that an NXms_interface_set can primarily be
         useful as a wrapper class in which specific details about interfaces
         can be stored in an arbitrarily nested manner.
    </doc>
</definition>
