<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="application" type="group" name="NXsensor_scan" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             Variables used to set a common size for collected sensor data.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="N_scanpoints">
            <doc>
                 The number of scan points measured in this scan.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Application definition for a generic scan using sensors.
         
         In this application definition, times should be specified always together
         with an UTC offset.
    </doc>
    <group type="NXentry">
        <field name="definition" type="NX_CHAR">
            <attribute name="version"/>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="NXsensor_scan"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="experiment_identifier" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true"/>
        <field name="experiment_description" type="NX_CHAR"/>
        <field name="start_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME" recommended="true"/>
        <field name="end_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME" recommended="true"/>
        <group type="NXprocess">
            <doc>
                 Define the program that was used to generate the results file(s)
                 with measured data and metadata.
            </doc>
            <field name="program" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Commercial or otherwise defined given name of the program
                     (or a link to the instrument software).
                </doc>
                <attribute name="version">
                    <doc>
                         Either version with build number, commit hash, or description of an
                         (online) repository where the source code of the program and build
                         instructions can be found so that the program can be configured in
                         such a way that result files can be created ideally in a
                         deterministic manner.
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
                <attribute name="program_url">
                    <doc>
                         Website of the software.
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group type="NXuser">
            <doc>
                 Contact information of at least the user of the instrument or the
                 investigator who performed this experiment. Adding multiple users if
                 relevant is recommended.
            </doc>
            <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Name of the user.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="affiliation" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Name of the affiliation of the user at the point in time when
                     the experiment was performed.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="address" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Full address (street, street number, ZIP, city, country)
                     of the user's affiliation.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="email" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Email address of the user.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="orcid" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Author ID defined by https://orcid.org/.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="telephone_number" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true">
                <doc>
                     Official telephone number of the user.
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
        <group type="NXinstrument">
            <group type="NXenvironment">
                <doc>
                     Describes an environment setup for the experiment.
                     
                     All the setting values of the independently scanned controllers are listed under corresponding
                     NXsensor groups. Similarly, seperate NXsensor groups are used to store the readings from each
                     measurement sensor.
                     
                     For example, in a temperature-dependent IV measurement, the temperature and voltage must be
                     present as independently scanned controllers and the current sensor must also be present with
                     its readings.
                </doc>
                <group type="NXsensor">
                    <group type="NXdata" recommended="true">
                        <doc>
                             Plot of measured signal as a function of the timestamp of when they have been
                             acquired is also possible.
                        </doc>
                    </group>
                    <field name="value" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
                        <doc>
                             For each point in the scan space, either the nominal setpoint of an independently scanned controller
                             or a representative average value of a measurement sensor is registered.
                             
                             The length of each sensor's data value array stored in this group should be equal to the number of scan points
                             probed in this scan. For every scan point [N], the corresponding sensor value can be picked from index [N].
                             This allows the scan to be made in any order as the user describes above in the experiment. We get matching
                             values simply using the index of the scan point.
                        </doc>
                        <dimensions rank="1">
                            <dim index="1" value="N_scanpoints"/>
                        </dimensions>
                    </field>
                    <field name="value_timestamp" type="NX_DATE_TIME" recommended="true">
                        <doc>
                             Timestamp for when the values provided in the value field were registered.
                             
                             Individual readings can be stored with their timestamps under value_log. This is to timestamp
                             the nominal setpoint or average reading values listed above in the value field.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="run_control" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true">
                        <attribute name="description">
                            <doc>
                                 Free-text describing the data acquisition control: an internal
                                 sweep using the built-in functionality of the controller device,
                                 or a set/wait/read/repeat mechanism.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                    <field name="calibration_time" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
                        <doc>
                             ISO8601 datum when calibration was last performed
                             before this measurement. UTC offset should be specified.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                </group>
                <group type="NXpid"/>
                <field name="independent_controllers">
                    <doc>
                         A list of names of NXsensor groups used as independently scanned controllers.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="measurement_sensors">
                    <doc>
                         A list of names of NXsensor groups used as measurement sensors.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
        </group>
        <group type="NXsample">
            <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR"/>
        </group>
        <group type="NXdata">
            <doc>
                 A scan specific representation of the measured signals as a function of the independently controlled environment settings.
                 Plot of every measured signal as a function of the timestamp of when they have been acquired is also possible.
            </doc>
        </group>
    </group>
</definition>
