<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2025-2025 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXspm_scan_pattern" extends="NXobject" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
        Basic base class to define the pattern of a scan in a given scan region.
        
        The base class is intended to handle the following scan types or patterns:
        
        Trajectory: A list of N-dimensional sequential vectors, representing a point in phase space, describes
                    the trajectory line for a full scan.
        Mesh: For each dimension, a range and a direction are chosen.
              When a scan along a dimension is done, a single step in the next dimension is taken, and
              then the scan in the previous dimension is repeated. As such we can speak about the fastest and
              the slowest scan axes.
        Snake: Similar to a mesh scan but the current scanning direction reversed after each line completed.
        Spiral: A scan taken along a spiral trajectory.
        Tilt: At each step, a proportional movement is done in all dimensions (Not addressed in this version).
        Linear: A scan where the scanning will be performed along a single independent axis.
    </doc>
    <field name="scan_speedN" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
            Define the scan speed in the forward direction along the axis (except the spiral and trajectory scans),
            if forward and backward speeds below are not specified.
            
            If the scan goes in the negative direction, the speed should be negative.
            
            Rename the field, according to the name of the dimension (e.g. scan_speed_x, scan_speed_voltage).
            
            Trajectory scan: N refers to the nth trajectory line (line between two trajectory points).
            Spiral scan: N refers to the nth circle from center.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="forward_speedN" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
            Define the scan speed in the forward directions (except the spiral and trajectory scans).
            Rename the field, according to the name of the dimension.
            
            Trajectory scan: N refers to the nth trajectory line (line between two trajectory points).
            Spiral scan: N refers to the nth circle from center.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="backward_speedN" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
            Define the scan speed in the backward directions (except the spiral and trajectory scans).
            Rename the field, according to the name of the dimension.
            
            Trajectory scan: N refers to the nth trajectory line (line between two trajectory points).
            Spiral scan: N refers to the nth circle from center.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="channelNAME" nameType="partial">
        <doc>
            Name of the channel that leads the scan data. The ending annotation 'NAME' is to represent the name of the channel and/or dimension.
            
            Rename the field, according to the name of the channel and dimension (e.g. channel_piezo_scanner_x).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="scan_pointsN" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial">
        <doc>
            Define the total number of points in the given axis the scan to be performed (except the spiral and trajectory scans).
            Rename the field, according to the name of the dimension (e.g. scan_points_x, scan_points_voltage).
            
            Trajectory scan: N refers to the nth trajectory line (line between two trajectory points).
            Spiral scan: N refers to the nth circle from center.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="steppingN" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial">
        <doc>
            The number of steps the probe jumps over the scan steps or points in the scanning process. This comes into picture, when not
            every point from the scan_points is scanned along an axis (except the spiral and trajectory scans).
            
            Rename the field, according to the name of the dimension (e.g. stepping_x, stepping_voltage).
            
            Trajectory scan:  N refers to the nth trajectory line (line between two trajectory points).
            Spiral scan: N refers to the nth circle from center.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="step_sizeN" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
            The size of each step in the scan on each dimension (except the spiral and trajectory scans).
            
            Rename the field, according to the name of the dimension (e.g. step_size_x, step_size_voltage).
            
            Trajectory scan:  N refers to the nth trajectory line (line between two trajectory points).
            Spiral scan: N refers to the nth circle from center.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="continuousN" type="NX_BOOLEAN" nameType="partial">
        <doc>
            If the scan probe moves continuously over the scan points or steps, use True. The default value is True.
            Usually, continuous scanning is possible in one dimension. On other dimensions, the scan probe moves
            in steps.
            
            Rename the field, according to the name of the dimension (e.g. continuous_voltage).
            
            Trajectory scan: N refers to the nth trajectory line (line between two trajectory points).
            Spiral scan: N refers to the nth circle from center.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="oscillating" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
            If the scan probe oscillates over the scan point, use True.
            The default value is False.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="oscillation_frequency" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
            The number of oscillations on each scanning point per second.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="number_of_trajectory_points" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
            The number of trajectory points in the entire scan that defines the path or lines of the trajectory.
            Each trajectory line is defined by two subsequent trajectory points.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="trajectory_points" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
            The trajectory points (nTraj) are the N-dimensional vectors (nD), each vector refers to a point in
            N-dimensional phase space.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="2">
            <dim index="1" value="nTraj"/>
            <dim index="2" value="nD"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
    <field name="spiral_radiusN" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
            Define the radius of the spiral circle of scanning.
            
            Rename the field, according to the circle order, the nearest circle to the center is 0.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group name="SCAN_DATA" type="NXdata" nameType="any">
        <doc>
            The scan data is the data collected during the scan.
            If the scan has several channels or derivatives from the channel data, please
            duplicate this NXdata group for each.
        </doc>
        <field name="DATA" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="any" units="NX_ANY">
            <doc>
                The scan data is the data collected during the scan.
            </doc>
        </field>
    </group>
</definition>
