<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!-- # $Id$ -->
<section 
    xml:id="PhysicalFileFormatSection" 
    xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  >
    <title>Physical File format</title>
    <para>
      This section describes how NeXus structures are mapped to features of the underlying 
      physical file format.
      <indexterm>
        <primary>NeXus</primary>
        <secondary>low-level file formats</secondary>
      </indexterm> 
      This is a guide for people who wish to create NeXus files without 
      using the NeXus-API.
      <indexterm>
        <primary>NAPI</primary>
        <secondary>bypassing</secondary>
      </indexterm>
    </para>

  <section xml:id="sec.fileformat.mapping.hdf">
    <title>Mapping NeXus into HDF</title>
    <para>
      NeXus groups map directly into HDF groups, NeXus 
      data sets directly into HDF SDS (scientific data sets) and 
      attributes directly to HDF group or SDS attributes. 
      <indexterm>
        <primary>attributes</primary>
      </indexterm>
      The only special is the NeXus class name. HDF-4 supports a group class 
      which is set with the <code>Vsetclass()</code> call 
      and read with <code>VGetclass()</code>. 
       HDF-5 has no group class. Thus the NeXus class 
       is stored as a group attribute with the name <code>NX_class</code>. 
    </para>
    </section>

  <section xml:id="sec.fileformat.mapping.xml">
    <title>Mapping NeXus into XML</title>
    <para>
      This takes a bit more work than HDF. 
      At the root of NeXus XML file 
      is a XML element with the name <code>NXroot</code>. 
      Further XML attributes to 
      <indexterm>
        <primary>attributes</primary>
      </indexterm> 
      <code>NXroot</code> define the NeXus file level attributes.
    </para>
    <para>
      NeXus groups are encoded into XML as elements with the 
      name of the NeXus class and an XML attribute <code>name</code> which defines the 
      NeXus name of the group. Further group attributes become XML attributes. An example:
      <example>
        <title>NeXus group element in XML</title>
        <programlisting language="xml" linenumbering="numbered"
              ><xi:include href="examples/mapping1.xml.txt" parse="text"
              /></programlisting>
      </example>
    </para>
    <para>
      NeXus data sets are encoded as XML elements with 
      the name of the data. An attribute <code>NAPItype</code> defines the type and 
      dimensions of the data. The actual data is 
      stored as <code>PCDATA</code><footnote><para
        ><code>PCDATA</code> is the XML term for 
      		<emphasis>parsed character data</emphasis> (see: <link
              xlink:href="http://www.w3schools.com/xml/xml_cdata.asp"
              >
      		<code>http://www.w3schools.com/xml/xml_cdata.asp</code
      		></link>).</para></footnote> in the element. Another example:
      <example>
        <title>NeXus data elements</title>
        <programlisting language="xml" linenumbering="numbered"
              ><xi:include href="examples/mapping2.xml.txt" parse="text"
              /></programlisting>
      </example>
      Data are printed in appropriate formats and in C storage order. 
      The codes understood for <code>NAPItype</code> are 
      all the NeXus data type names. The dimensions are 
      given in square brackets as a comma 
      separated list. No dimensions need to be given if 
      the data is just a single value. 
      Data attributes are represented as XML attributes.  
      <indexterm>
        <primary>attributes</primary>
      </indexterm>
      If the attribute is not a text string, then the 
      attribute is given in the form: <emphasis>type:value</emphasis>, for example: 
      <code>signal="NX_INT32:1"</code>.  
    </para>
    <para>
      NeXus links are stored in XML as XML elements 
      with the name <code>NAPIlink</code> and a XML attribute 
      <code>target</code> which stores the path to the linked 
      entity in the file.  If the item is linked under 
      a different name, then this name is  specified as a XML attribute name to 
      the element <code>NAPIlink</code>. 
    </para>
    </section>

  <section xml:id="sec.fileformat.special_attributes">
    <title>Special Attributes</title>
    <para>
      NeXus makes use of some special attributes for its internal purposes. 
      <indexterm>
        <primary>attributes</primary>
      </indexterm>
      These attributes are stored as normal group or data set attributes 
      in the respective file format. These are:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><term>target</term>
          <listitem><para>
            This attribute is automatically created when items get linked. The target attribute contains a text string with 
            the path to the source of the item linked. 
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term><code>napimount</code></term>
          <listitem><para>
            The <code>napimount</code> attribute is used to implement external linking in NeXus. 
            The string is a URL to the file and group in the 
            external file to link too. The system is meant to be extended. 
            But as of now, the only format supported is: 
            <code>nxfile://path-to-file#path-infile</code>. 
            This is a NeXus file in the file system at path-to-file 
            and the group path-infile in that 
            NeXus file.  
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term><code>NAPIlink</code></term>
          <listitem><para>
            NeXus supports linking items in another group under another name. 
            This is only supported natively in HDF-5. 
            For HDF-4 and XML a crutch is needed. 
            This crutch is a special class name or attribute 
            <code>NAPIlink</code> combined with the 
            target attribute. For groups, <code>NAPILink</code> 
            is the group class, for data items a special attribute 
            with the name <code>NAPIlink</code>.  
          </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
