<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!-- # $Id$ -->
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="History" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Brief history of the NeXus format</title>
    <para> Two things to note about the development and history of NeXus: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para> All efforts on NeXus have been voluntary except for one year when we had one
                    full-time worker. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para> The NIAC has already discussed many matters related to the format. </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>June 1994</term>
            <listitem>
                <para> Mark Koennecke (then ISIS, now PSI) made a proposal using netCDF for the
                    European neutron scattering community while working at ISIS </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>August 1994</term>
            <listitem>
                <para> Jonathan Tischler and Mitch Nelson (ORNL) proposed an HDF-based format as a
                    standard for data storage at APS </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>1995 and 1996</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>At SoftNeSS 1995 (at NIST), the three individual data format proposals by
                    Przemek Klososki (NIST), Jonathan Tischler (APS) and Mark Koennnecke (then ISIS)
                    were joined to form the basis of the current NeXus format. After reviewing the
                    different scientific data formats available in 1996, it was decided to use HDF-4
                    as it provided the best grouping support. The basic structure of a NeXus file
                    was agreed upon. At SoftNeSS 1996 (ANL) the NeXus proposal was further refined.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>August 1996</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>The HDF-4 API is quite complex. Thus a NeXus Abstract Programmer Interface
                    (NAPI) <indexterm>
                        <primary>NAPI</primary>
                    </indexterm> was released which simplified reading and writing NeXus
                files</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>July 1997</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>SINQ at PSI started writing NeXus files to store raw data.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>Summer 2001</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>MLNSC at LANL started writing NeXus files to store raw data</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>September 2002</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>NeXus API version 2.0.0 is released. This version brought support for the new
                    version of HDF, HDF-5, released by the HDF group. HDF-4 imposed limits on file
                    sizes and the number of objects in a file. These issues were resolved with
                    HDF-5. The NeXus API abstracted the difference between the tow physical file
                    formats away form the user. </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>June 2003</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>Przemek Klosowski, Ray Osborn, and Richard Riedel recieved the only known 
                    grant explicitly for working on NeXus from  the Systems Integration for Manufacturing 
                    Applications (SIMA) program of the National Institute of Standards and Technology 
                    (NIST). The grant funded a person for one year to work on community wide infrastructure 
                    in NeXus.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>October 2003</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>In 2003, NeXus had arrived at a stage where informal gatherings of a group of
                    people were no longer good enough to oversee the development of NeXus. This lead
                    to the formation of the NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC) which
                    strives to include representatives of all major stake holders in NeXus. A first
                    meeting was held at CalTech. Since 2003, the NIAC meets every year to discuss
                    all matters NeXus. </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>July 2005</term>
            <listitem>
                <para> The community asked the NeXus team to provide an ASCII based physical file
                    format which allows them to edit their scientific results in emacs. This lead to
                    the development of a XML NeXus physical format. This was released with NeXus API
                    version 3.0.0. </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>May 2007</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>NeXus API version 4.0.0 is released with broader support for scripting
                    languages and the feauture to link with external files. </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>October 2007</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>NeXus API version 4.1.0 is released with many bug-fixes.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>October 2008</term>
            <listitem>
                <para><link xlink:href="#NXDL"> The NeXus Definition Language (NXDL) is defined.
                    </link> Before NXDL NeXus used another XML format, meta-DTD, for defining base
                    classes and application definitions. There were several problems with meta-DTD,
                    the biggest one being that it was not easy to validate against it. NXDL was
                    designed to circumvent these problems and all current base classes and
                    application definitions were ported into the NXDL. </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>April 2009</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>NeXus API version 4.2.0 is released with additional C++, IDL, and python/numpy interfaces.</para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>September 2009</term>
            <listitem>
                <para>NXDL and draft <code>NXsas</code> presented to canSAS at SAS2009 conference
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
            <term>January 2010</term>
            <listitem>
                <para> NXDL presented to ESRF HDF5 workshop on hyperspectral data </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
</chapter>
