<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!-- # $Id$ -->
<section 
    version="5.0"
    xml:id="sect.NAPI.java" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>NAPI: Java Application Programming Interface</title>
    <!-- http://www.nexusformat.org/Java_API -->
    
    <indexterm significance="preferred">
        <primary>NAPI</primary>
        <secondary>java</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
        The NeXus Java API provides NeXus data 
        file access to programs written in the Java programming language. 
        This API was implemented by Java code calling the original C 
        language NeXus API through the Java Native Methods Interface.
    </para>
    
    <section xml:id="sect.NAPI.java.intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <!-- http://www.nexusformat.org/Japinotes -->
        <para>
            Contents of http://www.nexusformat.org/Japinotes go here
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="sect.NAPI.java.online">
        <title>On-line Documentation</title>
        <para>
            The following documentation is browsable online:
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The NeXus for Java API general instructions including installation notes, instructions for running NeXus for Java programs and a brief introduction to the API.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The Doxygen API documentation<footnote><para><link 
                            xlink:href="http://download.nexusformat.org/doxygen/html-java/"
                            ><literal
                                >http://download.nexusformat.org/doxygen/html-java/</literal
                            ></link></para></footnote>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        A verbose tutorial for the NeXus for Java API.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The API Reference.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Finally, the source code for the test driver for the API which also serves as a documented usage example.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="sect.NAPI.java.ack">
        <title>Acknowledgement</title>
        <para>
            All the code for number type conversion has been taken from the Java HDF Interface library provided by NCSA. JHI also served as an inspiration for many aspects of this API. See NCSA's copyright statement for more details. Downloads
        </para>
        <para>
            All binary distributions carry the full documentation, the Java source files and the shared libraries necessary to run the NeXus for Java API on the platforms supported. By downloading anything from the NeXus WWW site, you agree to the following disclaimer:         
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="sect.NAPI.java.disclaimer">
        <title>Disclaimer</title>
        <para>
            THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHORS AND THE CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" WITH NO WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED. In no event shall the Author or the Contributors be liable for any damages suffered by the users arising out of the use of this software, even if advised of the possibility of such damage.         
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="sect.NAPI.java.ref">
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            Binary Packages for the Java NeXus API 1.3x These packages are based on version 1.3.x of the NeXus-API and support only HDF-4. System type Creation Date DigitalUnix4.0D October, 19, 2000 Redhat Linux 6.2 Intel October, 19, 2000 Windows NT, 95, 98 October, 19, 2000
        </para>
        <para>
            Binary Packages for the Java NeXus API 2.0
        </para>
        <para>
            These packages are based on the NeXus-API version 2.0. This version supports both HDF-4 and HDF-5. System type Creation Date True64Unix 5.1 December, 18, 2002 Redhat Linux 6.2 Intel December, 18, 2002 Windows NT, 95, 98 December, 18, 2002 Please send shared libraries compiled by you for platforms not in this list to the maintainer of this page for inclusion. Source Code
        </para>
        <para>
            The source code for the NeXus for Java API is included in the general NeXus API developer package downloadable from the NeXus API page. 
        </para>
    </section>
    
</section>
