<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!-- # $Id$ -->
<section xml:id="NIAC" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xreflabel="NIAC: The NeXus International Advisory Committee"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>NIAC: The NeXus International Advisory Committee</title>
    
    <indexterm significance="preferred">
        <primary>NIAC</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm significance="preferred">
        <primary>NeXus International Advisory Committee</primary>
        <see>NIAC</see>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The purpose of the NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)<footnote>
            <para>For more details about the NIAC constitution, procedures, and meetings, refer to
                the NIAC wiki page: <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.nexusformat.org/NIAC"
                        ><literal>http://www.nexusformat.org/NIAC</literal></link>
                The members of the NIAC may be reached by email:
                <link
                    xlink:href="mailto://nexus-committee@nexusformat.org"
                    ><literal>NIAC &lt;nexus-committee@nexusformat.org&gt;</literal></link>
                
            </para>
        </footnote> is to supervise the development and maintenance of the NeXus common data format
        for neutron, x-ray, and muon science. This purpose includes, but is not limited to, the
        following activities.</para>
    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>To establish policies concerning the definition, use, and promotion of the NeXus
                format.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To ensure that the specification of the NeXus format is sufficiently complete and
                clear for its use in the exchange and archival of neutron, x-ray, and muon
                data.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                To receive and examine all proposed amendments and extensions to the NeXus format.
                In particular, to ratify proposed instrument and group class definitions, to ensure
                that the data structures conform to the basic NeXus specification, and to ensure
                that the definitions of data items 
                <!-- 2010-02-06,PRJ: Can we change "data item" to "field" and be consistent with NXDL nomenclature? -->
                are clear and unambiguous and conform to accepted
                scientific usage.
            </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To ensure that documentation of the NeXus format is sufficient, current, and
                available to potential users both on the internet and in other forms.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To coordinate with the developers of the NeXus Application Programming Interface
                to ensure that it supports the use of the NeXus format in the neutron, x-ray, and
                muon communities, and to promote other software development that will benefit users
                of the NeXus format.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>To coordinate with other organizations that maintain and develop related data
                formats to ensure maximum compatibility.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para> The committee will meet at least once every other calendar year according to the following
        plan: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>In years coinciding with the NOBUGS series of conferences (once every
                    two years), members of the entire NIAC will meet as a satellite meeting to
                    NOBUGS, along with interested members of the community.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>In intervening years, the executive officers of the NIAC will attend,
                    along with interested members of the NIAC. This is intended to be a working
                    meeting with a small group.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

</section>
