<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!-- # $Id$ -->
<section xml:id="orphans" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Manual Content orphaned due to editing</title>
    <section>
        <title>from Motivations</title>
        <para>By the late 1980s, it had become common practice for a scientific instrument
            or facility to define its own data format, often at the convenience of the local
            computer system. Data from these facilities were not easily interchanged due to various
            differences in computer systems and the compression schemes of binary data. It was
            necessary to contact the facility to obtain a description so that one could write an
            import routine in software. Experience with facilities closing (and subsequent lack of
            access to information describing the facility data format) revealed a significant
            limitation with this common practice.  Further, there existed a 
            <emphasis>N * N</emphasis> number of conversion routines necessary to convert 
            data between various formats.
            In <xref linkend="fig.data-pre-nexus"/>, circles represent different
            data file formats while arrows represent conversion routines.  Note that
            the red circle only maps to one other format.
            <figure xml:id="fig.data-pre-nexus">
                <title><emphasis>N</emphasis> separate file formats</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="img/data-pre-nexus.jpg" width="200pt"
                            scalefit="1"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure> 
            One early idea has been for NeXus to become the common data exchange format,
            and thereby reduce the number of data conversion routines from 
            <emphasis>N * N</emphasis> down to <emphasis>2N</emphasis>, as show in
            <xref linkend="fig.data-post-nexus"/>.
            <figure xml:id="fig.data-post-nexus">
                <title><emphasis>N</emphasis> separate file formats joined 
                    by a common NeXus converter</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="img/data-post-nexus.jpg" width="200pt"
                            scalefit="1"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure> 
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>more from Motivations</title>
        <para> At its beginnings, the founders of NeXus identified the 
            Hierarchical Data Format (HDF), 
            <indexterm>
                <primary>HDF</primary>
            </indexterm> initially from the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA)
            at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign (UIUC) and later spun off into its own
            group called The HDF Group (THG),<footnote>
                <para> The HDF Group: <link xlink:href="http://www.hdfgroup.org/">http://www.hdfgroup.org/</link>
                </para>
            </footnote> as a multi-platform data storage format with capacity for conveying large
            data payloads and a substantial user community. HDF (now HDF5) was provided with
            software to read and write data (this is the application-programmer interface, or API) <indexterm>
                <primary>API</primary>
            </indexterm> using a large number of computing systems in common use for neutron and
            X-ray science. HDF is a binary data file format that supports compression and structured
            data.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title></title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title></title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
</section>
