<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<!-- # $Id$ -->
<chapter xml:id="VerificationChapter" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title>Verification and validation of files</title>
    <indexterm significance="preferred">
        <primary>validation</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para> The intent of verification and validation of files is to ensure, in an unbiased way, that
        a given file conforms to the relevant specifications. NeXus uses various tools to validate
        files. These tools include conversion of content from HDF to XML and transformation (via
        XSLT) from XML format to another such as NXDL, XSD, and Schematron. This chapter will first
        provide an overview of the process, then define the terms used in validation, then describe
        how multiple base classes or application definitions might apply to a given NeXus data file,
        and then describe the various validation techniques in more detail. </para>

    <section>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <para>This is a paragraph.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Definitions of these terms</title>
        <para>This is a paragraph.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>NeXus data files may use multiple base classes or application definitions</title>
        <para>This is a paragraph.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Validation techniques</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>validation</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para> NeXus files adhere to a set of rules and can be tested against these rules for
            compliance. The rules are implemented using standard tools and can themselves be tested
            to verify compliance with the standards for such definitions. Validation includes the
            testing of both NeXus data files and the NXDL specifications that describe the rules. </para>
        <!-- 
            Describe what is being validated and what is not being validated.
            
            Each NXDL file must be validated against the rules for NXDL files.
            
            Each NeXus data file can be validated against the NXDL rules.  
            That validation is done using Schematron.
        -->

        <section>
            <title>Overview</title>
            <para>This is a paragraph.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Validation of NeXus data files</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>validation</primary>
                <secondary>NeXus data files</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Each NeXus data file can be validated against the NXDL rules. That validation is
                done using Schematron.</para>
            <note>
                <para>It is very important to describe what is and is not being validated.</para>
            </note>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Validation of NeXus Definition Language (NXDL) specification files</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>validation</primary>
                <secondary>NXDL specifications</secondary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>Each NXDL file must be validated against the rules that define how NXDL files are
                to be arranged.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Schematron</title>
            <indexterm significance="preferred">
                <primary>Schematron</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>This is a paragraph.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Transformation of NXDL files to Schematron</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>NXDL</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>Schematron</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>This is a paragraph.</para>
        </section>

    </section>

</chapter>
