<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd" type="group" category="application" name="NXapm_paraprobe_config_intersector" extends="NXobject">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="n_elements">
            <doc>
                 How many elements to use for computing a composition.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Configuration of a paraprobe-intersector tool run in atom probe microscopy.
    </doc>
    <group type="NXentry">
        <attribute name="version">
            <doc>
                 Version specifier of this application definition.
            </doc>
        </attribute>
        <field name="definition" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Official NeXus NXDL schema with which this file was written.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="NXapm_paraprobe_config_intersector"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="program" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Given name of the program/software/tool with which this NeXus
                 (configuration) file was generated.
            </doc>
            <attribute name="version" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                     Ideally program version plus build number, or commit hash or description
                     of ever persistent resources where the source code of the program and
                     build instructions can be found so that the program can be configured
                     ideally in such a manner that the result of this computational process
                     is recreatable in the same deterministic manner.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="analysis_identifier" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
            <doc>
                 Ideally, a (globally persistent) unique identifier for referring
                 to this analysis.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="analysis_description" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
            <doc>
                 Possibility for leaving a free-text description about this analysis.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="time_stamp" type="NX_DATE_TIME">
            <doc>
                 ISO 8601 formatted time code with local time zone offset to
                 UTC information included when this configuration file was created.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="intersection_detection_method" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                 Specifies the method to use which decides if two objects intersect.
                 For reasons which are detailed in the supplementary material of
                 `M. Kühbach et al. &lt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.13510&gt;`_, the tool by
                 default assumes that two objects intersect if they share at least one
                 ion with the same evaporation ID
                 (shared_ion). Alternatively, with specifying tetrahedra_intersections,
                 the tool can perform an intersection analysis which attempts to 
                 tetrahedralize first each polyhedron. If successful, the tool then checks
                 for at least one pair of intersecting tetrahedra to identify if two objects
                 intersect or not.
                 
                 However, we found that these geometrical analyses can result in corner
                 cases which the currently used library (TetGen) was not unable to
                 tetrahedralize successfully. These cases were virtually always
                 associated with complicated non-convex polyhedra
                 which had portions of the mesh that were connected by almost point like
                 tubes of triangles.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="shared_ion"/>
                <item value="tetrahedra_intersections"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="has_object_volume" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
            <doc>
                 Specifies if the tool should load the volume of each object
                 (if existent in the input file) to characterize the evolution of the
                 objects' volume as a function of set identifier (e.g. time).
                 
                 This and the has_object_composition option enables to activate
                 computations in the code which correlate the spatio-temporal tracking
                 with an object's properties. This is useful to explore/understand how
                 the object descriptor values evolve as a function of the parameterization
                 of the object. To arrive at a detailed understanding and quantification
                 of the differences of a given object as a function of delocalization and
                 e.g. iso-surfacing settings.
                 
                 The point made in M. Kühbach et al. 2022, is that this functionality
                 can be used to track for instance how the accumulated volume and
                 composition of an object depends on its segmentation via iso-surfaces.
                 The benefit of such computations is that users can inspect the
                 parameter sensitivity of an objects representation rigorously.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="has_object_composition" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
            <doc>
                 Specifies if the tool should load the composition of each object
                 (if existent in the input file) to characterize the evolution of the
                 object's composition as a function of set identifier. See the description
                 of has_object_volume for further details. In M. Kühbach et al. 2022, both
                 has_object options were used to characterize e.g. the parameter
                 sensitivity of computed composition, volume, and shape specifically,
                 for a carbide that was segmented via different carbon iso-composition
                 values.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="element_whitelist" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 List of np.uint16 elements, via their proton number. The whitelist is
                 evaluated to compute the composition of an object during tracking
                 when has_object_composition is set to true.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_elements"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="number_of_processes" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                 For now a support field for the tool to identify how many individual
                 analyses the tool should execute as part of the analysis.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <group type="NXprocess">
            <field name="number_of_tracking_sets" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                     For now a support field for the tool to identify how many individual
                     analyses (i. e. individual current_to_next mappings) the tool should
                     perform as part of the high-throughput analysis.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <group type="NXprocess" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
                <doc>
                     Tracking is the process of building logical relations between objects
                     based on proximity and mesh intersections. For each time step pairs
                     of sets are compared: members of a current_set and a next_set.
                     Members have to be objects and eventually can in addition be so-called
                     proxies. Objects and proxies are non-degenerated closed polyhedra which
                     are not necessarily convex. Proxies are doppelganger/replacement
                     meshes of objects which would otherwise be impossible to describe
                     with a closed mesh.
                </doc>
                <group name="current_set" type="NXcollection">
                    <doc>
                         Current set stores a set of object geometries that should be checked
                         for proximity and/or intersection with member of the next_set.
                    </doc>
                    <field name="identifier" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_ANY">
                        <doc>
                             This identifier can be used to label the current set. The label
                             effectively represents the time/iteration step when the current
                             set was taken. As it is detailed in M. Kühbach et al. 2022,
                             this identifier takes the role of the time variable k.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="filename" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             Name of the HDF5 file which contain geometry (vertex coordinates,
                             facet indices) and properties (ions, composition) of polyhedra
                             (l objects) which should be included in the current set.
                             The user has to ensure that the datasets under list_of_dataset_names
                             (vertices, facet_indices, ions) exist and are formatted consistently.
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="version" type="NX_CHAR">
                            <doc>
                                 Version identifier of the file such as a secure hash which documents
                                 the binary state of the file to add an additional layer of
                                 reproducibility from which file specifically contains these data.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_object_geometry_data" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             Paraprobe-intersector loads triangulated surface mesh data of a
                             set of objects. For each object its mesh is expected to have
                             three-dimensional position data of the unique vertices and a
                             matrix of vertex indices which describe the faces.
                             As each object has to be a polyhedron/closed surface mesh, this
                             matrix has as many rows as faces, i.e. triangles and three columns.
                             Vertex indices have to start at zero.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_object_supplementary_data" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             The default intersection detection method uses shared ions.
                             Therefore, it is necessary to specify where the results from the
                             paraprobe-nanochem tool run are located which document which ions
                             (with their evaporation IDs) are inside or on the surface of each
                             object. This field points the tool to these evaporation IDs.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_object_property_data" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             In order to correlate object properties like volume and composition
                             with tracking data, it is necessary to specify where the results
                             (object properties) from the paraprobe-nanochem tool run are located.
                             This field instructs the tool where to load these object property data
                             from.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="dataset_object_identifier" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             Paraprobe-intersector does not just compare two objects but a set
                             of sets of objects. This field instructs the tool where to load
                             the identifiers (names) of each object in a current_set or next_set
                             respectively from.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_proxy_geometry_data" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
                        <doc>
                             Like groupname_object_geometry_data but for the proxies.
                             Triangulated surface meshes of proxies have to be formatted
                             in the same manner as objects.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_proxy_interior_supplementary_data" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
                        <doc>
                             Like groupname_proxy_supplementary_data but for the interior proxies.
                             Leave an empty string if proxies should not be used.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_proxy_exterior_supplementary_data" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
                        <doc>
                             Like groupname_proxy_supplementary_data but for the exterior proxies.
                             Leave an empty string if proxies should not be used.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                </group>
                <group name="next_set" type="NXcollection">
                    <doc>
                         Next set stores a set of object geometries that should be checked
                         for proximity and/or intersection with (each) member(s) of the
                         current_set.
                    </doc>
                    <field name="identifier" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_ANY">
                        <doc>
                             This identifier can be used to label the next set. Like for the current_set
                             the identifier is effectively the time/iteration step when the next set was taken.
                             As it is detailed in M. Kühbach et al. 2022, this identifier
                             takes the role of the time variable k+1.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="filename" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             Name of the HDF5 file which contain geometry (vertex coordinates,
                             facet indices) and properties (ions, composition) of
                             polyhedra(l objects) which should be included in the current set.
                             The user has to ensure that the datasets that are referred to
                             under list_of_dataset_names (vertices, facet_indices, ions).
                        </doc>
                        <attribute name="version" type="NX_CHAR">
                            <doc>
                                 Version identifier of the file such as a secure hash which documents
                                 the binary state of the file to add an additional layer of
                                 reproducibility from which file specifically contains these data.
                            </doc>
                        </attribute>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_object_geometry_data" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             Paraprobe-intersector loads triangulated surface mesh data of a
                             set of objects. For each object its mesh is expected to have
                             three-dimensional position data of the unique vertices and a
                             matrix of vertex indices which describe the faces.
                             As each object has to be a polyhedron/closed surface mesh
                             this matrix has as many rows as faces, i.e. triangles and
                             three columns. Vertex indices have to start at zero.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_object_supplementary_data" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             The default intersection detection method uses shared ions.
                             Therefore, it is necessary to specify where the results from the
                             paraprobe-nanochem tool run are located which document which ions
                             (with their identifiers) are inside or on the surface of each object.
                             This field instructs the tool where to load these
                             ion evaporation ids from.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_object_property_data" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             In order to correlate object properties like volume and composition
                             with tracking data, it is necessary to specify where the results
                             (object properties) from the paraprobe-nanochem tool run are located.
                             This field instructs the tool where to load these object property
                             data from.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="dataset_object_identifier" type="NX_CHAR">
                        <doc>
                             Paraprobe-intersector does not just compare two objects but a set
                             of sets of objects. This field instructs the tool where to load
                             the identifiers (names) of each object in a current or next set
                             respectively from.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_proxy_geometry_data" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
                        <doc>
                             Like groupname_object_geometry_data but for the proxies.
                             Triangulated surface meshes of proxies have to be formatted
                             in the same manner. Leave an empty string if proxies should not
                             be used.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_proxy_interior_supplementary_data" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
                        <doc>
                             Like groupname_proxy_supplementary_data but for the interior proxies.
                             Leave an empty string if proxies should not be used.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                    <field name="groupname_proxy_exterior_supplementary_data" type="NX_CHAR" optional="true">
                        <doc>
                             Like groupname_proxy_supplementary_data but for the exterior proxies.
                             Leave an empty string if proxies should not be used.
                        </doc>
                    </field>
                </group>
                <field name="add_proxies_to_objects" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if, in the case of small finite datasets, objects which are
                         located at the edge of the dataset should be accounted for or not.
                         If these so-called proxy/doppelganger objects are accounted for, the
                         respective groupname_proxy and dataset_proxy fields have to be
                         filled to tell the tool where to load which proxy meshes from.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="analyze_intersection" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool evaluates if for each pair the two objects
                         (and proxies if used) intersect volumetrically.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="analyze_proximity" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool evaluates if for each pair the two objects
                         (and proxies if used) lie closer to one another than the
                         threshold_proximity.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="analyze_coprecipitation" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool evaluates, ones all tracking tasks were
                         successfully completed, how intersecting or proximity related
                         objects build sub-graphs. This is the feature which enabled
                         M. Kühbach et al. 2022 the high-throughput analyses of how many
                         objects are coprecipitates in the sense that they are single,
                         duplet, triplet, or high-order. For these analyses to work
                         has_object_volume needs to be activated.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="threshold_proximity" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_LENGTH">
                    <doc>
                         The maximum Euclidean distance between two objects below which
                         both objects are still considered within proximity.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_current_to_next_links" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool stores the so-called forward relations between
                         nodes representing members of the current_set to nodes representing
                         members of the next_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
                <field name="has_next_to_current_links" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
                    <doc>
                         Specifies if the tool stores the so-called backward relations between
                         nodes representing members of the next_set to nodes representing
                         members of the current_set.
                    </doc>
                </field>
            </group>
        </group>
    </group>
</definition>
