<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd" type="group" category="base" name="NXlens_em" extends="NXobject">
    <doc>
         Description of an electro-magnetic lens or a compound lens.
         
         Details of an `electro-magnetic lens`_.
         
         For NXtransformations the origin of the coordinate system is placed
         in the center of the lens (its polepiece, pinhole, or another point of
         reference. The origin should be specified in the NXtransformations.
         
           .. _electro-magnetic lens: https://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-540-38967-5
    </doc>
    <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Qualitative type of lens with respect to the number of pole pieces
        </doc>
        <enumeration>
            <item value="single"/>
            <item value="double"/>
            <item value="quadrupole"/>
            <item value="hexapole"/>
            <item value="octupole"/>
        </enumeration>
    </field>
    <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Colloquial or short name for the lens. For manufacturer names and identifiers
             use respective manufacturer fields.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="manufacturer_name" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Name of the manufacturer who built/constructed the lens.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXmanufacturer"/>
    <field name="model" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Hardware name, hash identifier, or serial number that was given by the
             manufacturer to identify the lens.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="description" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Ideally an identifier, persistent link, or free text which gives further details
             about the lens.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="voltage" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
        <doc>
             Excitation voltage of the lens. For dipoles it is a single number. For higher
             orders, it is an array.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="current" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_CURRENT">
        <doc>
             Excitation current of the lens. For dipoles it is a single number. For higher
             orders, it is an array.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="depends_on" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             Specifies the position of the lens by pointing to the last transformation in the
             transformation chain in the NXtransformations group.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group type="NXtransformations">
        <doc>
             Collection of axis-based translations and rotations to describe the location and
             geometry of the lens as a component in the instrument. Typically, the components
             of a system should all be related relative to each other and only one component
             should relate to the reference coordinate system.
        </doc>
    </group>
</definition>
