<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXcg_parallelogram_set" extends="NXcg_primitive_set" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <doc>
             The symbols used in the schema to specify e.g. dimensions of arrays.
        </doc>
        <symbol name="c">
            <doc>
                 The cardinality of the set, i.e. the number of parallelograms.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
         Computational geometry description of a set of parallelograms.
         
         This class can also be used to describe rectangles or squares, irrespective
         whether these are axis-aligned or not. The class represents different
         access and description levels to embrace applied scientists and computational
         geometry experts with their different views:
         
         * The simplest case is the communication of dimensions aka the size of a
           region of interest in the 2D plane. In this case, communicating the
           alignment with axes is maybe not as relevant as it is to report the area
           of the ROI.
         * In other cases the extent of the parallelogram is relevant though.
         * Finally, in CAD models it should be possible to specify the polygons
           which the parallelograms represent with exact numerical details.
         
         Parallelograms are important geometrical primitives as their usage for
         describing many scanning experiments shows where typically parallelogram-shaped
         ROIs are scanned across the surface of a sample.
         
         The term parallelogram will be used throughout this base class thus including
         the important special cases rectangle, square, 2D box, axis-aligned bounding box
         (AABB), or optimal bounding box (OBB) as analogous 2D variants to their 3D
         counterparts. See :ref:`NXcg_hexahedron_set` for the generalization in 3D.
         
         An axis-aligned bounding box is a common data object in computational science
         and simulation codes to represent a rectangle whose edges are aligned with the
         axes of a coordinate system. As a part of binary trees AABBs are important data
         objects for executing time- as well as space-efficient queries
         of geometric primitives in techniques like kd-trees.
         
         An optimal bounding box is a common data object which provides the best, i.e.
         most tightly fitting box about an arbitrary object. In general such boxes are
         rotated. Other than in 3D dimensions, the rotation calipher method offers
         a rigorous approach to compute an optimal bounding box to a point set in 2D.
    </doc>
    <!--qualifiers and properties of parallelograms-->
    <field name="is_rectangle" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
             To specify which parallelogram is a rectangle.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="c"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
    <field name="is_axis_aligned" type="NX_BOOLEAN">
        <doc>
             Only to be used if is_rectangle is present. In this case, this field
             describes whether parallelograms are rectangles whose primary edges
             are parallel to the axes of the coordinate system.
        </doc>
        <dimensions rank="1">
            <dim index="1" value="c"/>
        </dimensions>
    </field>
    <!--detailed mesh-based representation-->
    <group name="parallelograms" type="NXcg_face_list_data_structure">
        <!--
exists: [min, 0, max, 1]
-->
        <doc>
             Combined storage of all primitives of all parallelograms.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group name="parallelogramID" type="NXcg_face_list_data_structure">
        <doc>
             Individual storage of each parallelogram.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <!--#MK::parallelogram_half_edgeID(NXcg_half_edge_data_structure)
a half-edge structure would be overkill as this is a simple primitive-->
</definition>
