<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2022 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXcircuit" extends="NXobject" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
         Application definition for circuit devices.
    </doc>
    <group name="hardware" type="NXfabrication">
        <doc>
             Hardware type used in circuit, includes hardware manufacturers and type
        </doc>
    </group>
    <field name="tunneling_current" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_CURRENT">
        <doc>
             The tunneling current between tip and sample after application of bias voltage.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="calibration" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Calibration of the current measurement (A/V).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="offset" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_CURRENT">
        <doc>
             Offset of the current measurement.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="gain" type="NX_NUMBER">
        <doc>
             Proportional relationship between the probe output voltage and the actual
             tunneling current when measuring the tunneling current.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="channels" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             The scan channels are selected by users (in scan contronaller).
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="rt_frequency" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_FREQUENCY">
        <doc>
             The bandwitdh of the Hardware and/or Software
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="signals_oversampling" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
             (Signals Periods) The Signals Period is the rate at which the signals are
             transferred to the host computer running the control software. This is usually
             lower by a factor of 10 than the sampling rate, because an internal oversampling
             of the signal is done on the real time engine. You can reduce the oversampling
             down to 1 in order to resolve higher frequencies in the Spectrum Analyzer.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="acquisition_period" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Update rate for several processes like History Graph, Auto-Approach, and for
             many Programming Interface functions. This is usually set to 20 ms. All
             additional timings (7-9) can only be integer multiples of this value. They can
             be set to different values, but the actual timing value will be coerced to a
             multiple of the Acquisition Period.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="animations_period" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Update rate of animated graphical indicators. These are e.g. some graphs &amp;
             sliders. A reasonable value is 40 ms (25 updates per second). Increase this
             period to reduce the processor load for the graphical user interface, especially
             on slow computers. This value is purely a user interface update rate and does
             not affect measurements in any way.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="indicators_period" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             Update rate of digital indicators, e.g. the numbers displayed besides each
             slider. Here, 3 updates per second, or 300 ms is enough. This value is purely a
             user interface update rate and does not affect measurements in any way.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="measurements_period" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
        <doc>
             The Measurements period is the integration time for precise measurements
             (averaging over specified period), mostly used in sweep modules. Examples are
             recording of a force-distance curve or a resonance of a cantilever. For fast
             measurements with small steps, a value of 40 ms may be reasonable. For normal
             use, 300-500 ms is a good value, but for recording a resonance of a high-Q
             cantilever, values of several seconds might be necessary. Usually this parameter
             doesn’t need to be set from this module; the sweep modules will set this value
             according to the sweep timings.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="number_of_outputs" type="NX_INT">
        <doc>
             Number of output channels
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="output_mode" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             The user output in each monitor mode.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="output_value" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
             The values for each output channel.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="output_name" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             User outputs whose name can be modified in the corresponding module.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="output_slew_rate" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
             The rate at which the one of the signal changes when ramping to the starting
             point. (V/s)
        </doc>
    </field>
</definition>
