<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<definition category="base" extends="NXobject" name="NXdeflector" type="group" xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<doc>Draft class definition for electro-static deflectors as they are used e.g. in an electron analyser.</doc>
	<field name="type" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Qualitative type of lens with respect to the number of pole pieces</doc>
		<enumeration>
			<item value="dipole"/>
			<item value="quadrupole"/>
			<item value="hexapole"/>
			<item value="octupole"/>
		</enumeration>
	</field>
	<field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Colloquial or short name for the lens. For manufacturer names and identifiers use respective manufacturer fields.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="manufacturer_name" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Name of the manufacturer who built/constructed the lens.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="manufacturer_model" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Hardware name, hash identifier, or serial number that was given by the manufacturer to identify the lens.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="description" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Ideally an identifier, persistent link, or free text which gives further details about the lens.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="voltage" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
		<doc>Excitation voltage of the lens. For dipoles it is a single number. For higher orders, it is an array.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="current" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_CURRENT">
		<doc>Excitation current of the lens. For dipoles it is a single number. For higher orders, it is an array.</doc>
	</field>
	<group type="NXtransformations">
		<doc>Collection of axis-based translations and rotations to describe the location and geometry of the corrector as a component in the instrument. Conventions from the NXtransformations base class are used. In principle, the McStas coordinate system is used. The origin of the coordinate system is placed in the center of the gun pinhole as the virtual point-like assumed source of the electron beam. A right-handed coordinate system is assumed whose positive z-axis points in the direction of the propagating electron beam.</doc>
		<field name="position" type="NX_CHAR">
			<attribute name="transformation_type" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Following transformation_type argument of NXtranslations but allowed value is only translation.</doc>
			</attribute>
			<attribute name="vector" type="NX_NUMBER">
				<doc>Following vector argument of NXtranslations. The translation actively brings the coordinate system under depends_on into registration with a coordinate system in the center of the lens.</doc>
			</attribute>
			<attribute name="depends_on" type="NX_CHAR">
				<doc>Enter the path where the reference coordinate system for the instrument is defined.</doc>
			</attribute>
		</field>
	</group>
</definition>
