<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2023-2025 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXem_ebsd" extends="NXprocess" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <symbols>
        <symbol name="n_op">
            <doc>
                Number of arguments per orientation for given parameterization.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_sc">
            <doc>
                Number of scan points.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_z">
            <doc>
                Number of pixel along the slowest changing dimension for a rediscretized,
                i.e. standardized default plot orientation mapping.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_y">
            <doc>
                Number of pixel along slow changing dimension for a rediscretized i.e.
                standardized default plot orientation mapping.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_x">
            <doc>
                Number of pixel along fast changing dimension for a rediscretized i.e.
                standardized default plot orientation mapping.
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_solutions">
            <doc>
                Number of phase solutions
            </doc>
        </symbol>
        <symbol name="n_hkl">
            <doc>
                Number of reflectors (Miller crystallographic plane triplets).
            </doc>
        </symbol>
    </symbols>
    <doc>
        Base class method-specific for Electron Backscatter Diffraction (EBSD).
        
        The general procedure of an EBSD experiment is as follows:
        Users load the specimen, collect first a coarse image of the surface.
        Next, they set an approximate value for the calibrated working distance
        and tilt the stage into diffraction conditions.
        
        Users then typically configure the microscope for collecting quality data.
        The EBSD detector is pushed in (if retractable). Subsequently, they fine tune
        the illumination and aberration corrector settings and select one or multiple ROIs
        for the microscope to machine off automatically. They configure on-the-fly
        indexing parameter and then typically start the measurement queue.
        From this point onwards typically the microscope runs automatically.
        
        Diffraction pattern get collected until the queue finishes or gets interrupted by
        either errors or arrival at the end of the users' allocated timeslot at the instrument.
        
        Kikuchi pattern (EBSP) are usually indexed on-the-fly. These patterns are the raw data.
        Once indexed, these patterns are often not stored.
        
        Results are stored in files, which afterwards are typically copied
        automatically or manually for archival purposes to certain storage
        locations for further consumption. The result of such an EBSD
        measurement/experiment is a set of usually proprietary or open files
        from technology partners.
        
        This :ref:`NXem_ebsd` base class is a proposal how to represent method-specific
        data, metadata, and connections between these for the research field of
        electron microscopy exemplified here for electron backscatter diffraction (EBSD).
        The base class solves two key documentation issues within the EBSD community:
        
        Firstly, an instance of NXem_ebsd (such as a NeXus/HDF5 file that is formatted
        according to NXem_ebsd) stores the connection between the microscope session and
        the key datasets which are considered typically results of the afore-mentioned
        steps involved in an EBSD experiment.
        
        Different groups in NXem_ebsd make connections to data artifacts which were collected
        when working with electron microscopes via the NXem application definition.
        Using a file which stores information according to the NXem application definition
        has the benefit that it connects the sample, references to the sample processing,
        the user operating the microscope, details about the microscope session,
        and details about the acquisition and eventual indexing of Kikuchi patterns,
        associated overview images, like secondary electron or backscattered electron
        images of the region-of-interest probed, and many more (meta)data.
        
        Secondly, NXem_ebsd connects and stores the conventions and reference frames
        which were used and which are the key to a correct mathematical interpretation
        of every experiment or simulation using EBSD.
        
        Otherwise, results would be ripped out of their context like it is the current situation
        with many traditional studies where EBSD data were indexed on-the-fly and shared
        with the community only via sharing the strongly processed files with results in some
        formatting but without communicating all conventions used or just relying on the assumptions
        that colleagues likely know these conventions even though
        multiple definitions are possible.
        
        NXem_ebsd covers experiments with one-, two-dimensional, and so-called three-
        dimensional EBSD datasets. The third dimension is either time (in the case of
        quasi in-situ experiments) or space (in the case of serial-sectioning) experiments
        where a combination of repetitive removal of material from the surface layer to measure
        otherwise the same region-of-interest at different depth increments. Material removal
        can be achieved with mechanical, electron, or ion polishing, using manual steps or
        automated equipment like a robot system `S. Tsai et al. &lt;https://doi.org/10.1063/5.0087945&gt;`_.
        
        Three-dimensional experiments require to follow a sequence of specimen, surface
        preparation, and data collection steps. By virtue of design, these methods are destructive
        either because of the necessary material removal or surface degradation due to e.g.
        contamination or other electron-matter interaction.
        
        For three-dimensional EBSD, multiple two-dimensional EBSD orientation mappings
        are combined into one reconstructed stack via a computational workflow. Users collect
        data for each serial sectioning step via an experiment. This assures that data for associated
        microscope sessions and steps of data processing stay contextualized and connected.
        
        Eventual tomography methods also use such a workflow because first diffraction
        images are collected (e.g. with X-ray) and then these images are indexed to process
        a 3D orientation mapping. Therefore, the here proposed base class can be a blueprint
        also for future classes to embrace our colleagues from X-ray-based techniques be it 3DXRD or HEDM.
        
        This concept is related to term `Electron Backscatter Diffraction`_ of the EMglossary standard.
        
        .. _Electron Backscatter Diffraction: https://purls.helmholtz-metadaten.de/emg/EMG_00000019
    </doc>
    <group name="gnomonic_reference_frame" type="NXcoordinate_system">
        <doc>
            Details about the gnomonic (projection) reference frame.
            
            It is assumed that the configuration is inspected by looking towards the sample surface.
            If a detector is involved, it is assumed that the configuration is inspected from a position
            that is located behind this detector.
            
            If any of these assumptions are not met, the user is required to explicitly state this.
            
            Reference `&lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matchar.2016.04.008&gt;`_ suggests to label the
            base vectors of this coordinate system as :math:`X_g, Y_g, Z_g`.
        </doc>
        <field name="origin" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Origin of the gnomonic_reference_frame.
                
                Reference `&lt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.matchar.2016.04.008&gt;`_ suggests to
                assume that this is coordinate :math:`Xg = 0, Yg = 0, Zg = 0`.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="in_the_pattern_center"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="x_direction" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Direction of the positively pointing x-axis base vector of the
                gnomonic_reference_frame.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="north"/>
                <item value="east"/>
                <item value="south"/>
                <item value="west"/>
                <item value="in"/>
                <item value="out"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="y_direction" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Direction of the positively pointing y-axis base vector of the
                gnomonic_reference_frame.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="north"/>
                <item value="east"/>
                <item value="south"/>
                <item value="west"/>
                <item value="in"/>
                <item value="out"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="z_direction" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Direction of the positively pointing z-axis base vector of the
                gnomonic_reference_frame.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="north"/>
                <item value="east"/>
                <item value="south"/>
                <item value="west"/>
                <item value="in"/>
                <item value="out"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="pattern_center" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
            Details about the definition of the pattern center as a special point in the
            gnomonic_reference_frame.
            
            Typically the gnomonic space is embedded in the detector space.
            Specifically, the XgYg plane is defined such that it is laying inside the
            XdYd plane (of the detector reference frame).
            
            When the normalization direction is the same as e.g. the detector x-axis direction
            one effectively normalizes in fractions of the width of the detector.
            
            The issue with terms like width and height, though, is that these become degenerated
            if the detector region-of-interest is square-shaped. This is why instead of referring to
            width and height it is better to state explicitly which direction is considered positive
            when measuring distances.
            
            For the concepts used to specify the boundary_convention it is assumed that the
            region-of-interest is defined by a rectangle, referring to the direction of outer-unit
            normals to the respective edges of this rectangle.
        </doc>
        <field name="x_boundary_convention" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                From which border of the EBSP (in the detector reference frame) is the pattern
                center's x-position (PCx) measured.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="top"/>
                <item value="right"/>
                <item value="bottom"/>
                <item value="left"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="x_normalization_direction" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                In which direction are positive values for the x-axis coordinate value measured
                from the specified boundary.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="north"/>
                <item value="east"/>
                <item value="south"/>
                <item value="west"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="y_boundary_convention" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                From which border of the EBSP (in the detector reference frame) is the pattern
                center's y-position (PCy) measured.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="top"/>
                <item value="right"/>
                <item value="bottom"/>
                <item value="left"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <field name="y_normalization_direction" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                In which direction are positive values for the y-axis coordinate value measured
                from the specified boundary.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="north"/>
                <item value="east"/>
                <item value="south"/>
                <item value="west"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="measurement" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
            This group documents relevant details about the conditions and the
            tools for measuring diffraction patterns with an electron microscope.
            
            The most frequently collected EBSD data are captured for rectangular
            regions-of-interest using a discretization into square or hexagon tiles.
        </doc>
        <field name="time" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_TIME">
            <doc>
                Physical time since the beginning of a timestamp that is required to be
                the same for all experiments in the set. The purpose of this marker is
                to identify how all experiments in the set need to be arranged
                sequentially based on the time elapsed.
                The time is relevant to sort e.g. experiments of consecutive quasi
                in-situ experiments where a measurement was e.g. taken after 0 minutes,
                30 minutes, 6 hours, or 24 hours of annealing.
            </doc>
            <attribute name="epoch_start" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                    Timestamp relative to which time was counted to aid
                    converting between time and timestamp.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="depends_on" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Path to an instance of :ref:`NXdata` where the measured patterns are stored.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <group name="source" type="NXnote">
            <doc>
                Reference (e.g. path and filename) to an existent data artifact which
                stores either the measured patterns or input (already processed EBSD data).
            </doc>
        </group>
    </group>
    <group name="simulation" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
            This group documents relevant details about the conditions and the tools
            used for simulating diffraction patterns with some physical model.
            
            This group should be used if (e.g. instead of a measurement) the patterns
            were simulated (possibly awaiting indexing).
             
            In many practical cases where patterns are analyzed on-the-fly and dictionary
            indexing strategies used, so-called master pattern(s) are used to compare
            measured or simulated patterns with the master patterns.
        </doc>
        <field name="depends_on" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Path to an instance of :ref:`NXimage` where the simulated patterns are stored.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <group name="source" type="NXnote">
            <doc>
                Reference (e.g. path and filename) to an existent digital resource which
                stores either the patterns or input (already processed EBSD data) that are
                about to become processed further as described by this NXem_ebsd instance.
            </doc>
        </group>
    </group>
    <group name="calibration" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
            The EBSD system, including components like the electron gun, pole-piece,
            stage tilt, EBSD detector, and the gnomonic projection have to be
            calibrated to achieve reliable, precise, and accurate scientific results.
            
            Specifically, the gnomonic projection has to be calibrated.
            Typically, standard specimens made from silicon or quartz crystals
            in specific orientations are used for this purpose.
            
            Considering that a system used is already calibrated well-enough is much
            more frequently the case in practice than that users perform the calibration
            themselves (with above-mentioned standard specimens).
            
            In the first case, the user assumes that the principle geometry of the
            hardware components and the settings in the control and EBSD pattern
            acquisition software has been calibrated already. Consequently, users pick from
            an existent library of phase candidates, i.e. :ref:`NXunit_cell` instances.
            Examples are reflector models as stored in CRY files (HKL/Channel 5/Flamenco).
            
            In the second case, users calibrate the system during the session
            using standards (silicon, quartz, or other common specimens).
            There is usually one person in each lab responsible for doing such
            calibrations. Often this person or technician is also in charge of
            configuring the graphical user interface and software with which most
            users control and perform their analyses.
            
            For EBSD this has key implications: Taking TSL OIM/EDAX as an example,
            the conventions how orientations are stored is affected by how the
            reference frames are configured and how this setup in the GUI.
            
            Unfortunately, these pieces of information are not necessarily stored
            in the results files. In effect, key conventions become disconnected
            from the data so it remains the users' obligation to remember these
            settings or write these down in a lab notebook. Otherwise, these metadata
            get lost. All these issues are a motivation and problem which :ref:`NXem_ebsd`
            solves in that all conventions can be specified explicitly.
        </doc>
        <field name="depends_on" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Path to an instance of :ref:`NXem` where calibration data are stored.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <group name="source" type="NXnote">
            <doc>
                Reference to a digital resource where the calibration is stored.
            </doc>
        </group>
    </group>
    <group name="indexing" type="NXprocess">
        <doc>
            Indexing is a data processing step performed either after or while (aka on-the-fly)
            the beam scans the specimen. The resulting method is also
            known as orientation imaging microscopy (OIM).
            
            Different algorithms can be used to index EBSP. Common to them is the
            computational step where simulated or theoretically assumed patterns
            are compared with the measured ones. These latter patterns are referred
            to via the measurement or simulation groups of this base class respectively.
            
            Quality descriptors are defined based on which an indexing algorithm
            yields a quantitative measure of how similar measured and reference
            patterns are, and thus if no, one, or multiple so-called solutions were found.
            
            Assumed or simulated patterns are simulated using kinematical or dynamical
            theory of electron diffraction delivering master patterns.
            
            The Hough transform, one of the most frequently used traditional method for indexing
            EBSP is essentially a discretized Radon transform (for details see `M. van Ginkel et al. &lt;https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/A-short-introduction-to-the-Radon-and-Hough-and-how-Ginkel/fb6226f606cad489a15e38ed961c419037ccc858&gt;`_). Recently, dictionary-based and artificial intelligence-based methods
            find more widespread usage for indexing.
        </doc>
        <group name="source" type="NXnote">
            <doc>
                This group enables to establish a logical connection between previous
                processing steps or on-the-fly-performed indexing of the EBSD map.
                Typically these processing steps are performed with commercial software.
                Therefore, in many cases a results file from this indexing is often
                all that is communicated and saved. These are typically files in a format
                specific to the instrument and its configuration.
                
                Typical file formats are CPR/CRC, ANG, OSC, HDF5, H5EBSD, EDAXH5.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <field name="method" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Principal algorithm used for indexing.
            </doc>
            <enumeration open="true">
                <item value="hough_transform"/>
                <item value="dictionary"/>
                <item value="radon_transform"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <group name="background_correction" type="NXprocess">
            <doc>
                Details about the background correction applied to each Kikuchi pattern.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <group name="binning" type="NXprocess">
            <doc>
                Binning i.e. downsampling to each pattern.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <group name="parameter" type="NXcollection">
            <doc>
                Specific parameter relevant only for certain algorithms used.
            </doc>
        </group>
        <group name="phaseID" type="NXphase" nameType="partial">
            <doc>
                Details for each phase used as a model with which the patterns were
                indexed. Instances of :ref:`NXunit_cell` in this group must
                have the group name prefixed with phase. The identifier in the name is an
                integer. Start counting from 1 because the value 0 is reserved for
                the special phase that is the null-model, the null phase also known
                as notIndexed.
            </doc>
            <field name="dspacing" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                    Spacing between the crystallographic planes that are defined via ``miller``.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_hkl"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
            <field name="relative_intensity" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_DIMENSIONLESS">
                <doc>
                    Relative intensity for the computed diffraction intensity (signal) for the
                    plane.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_hkl"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
            <field name="number_of_scan_points" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                    In case the :ref:`NXunit_cell` base class is used with analyzed orientation maps
                    this field stores how many scan points of the map were identified as matching best
                    with this phase.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="number_of_planes" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                    How many reflectors for crystallographic planes are distinguished.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="miller" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                    Miller indices :math:`(hkl)[uvw]` of the planes.
                    
                    The first triplet specifies :math:`(hkl)`. The second triplet specifies :math:`[uvw]`.
                    Miller indices refer to the Cartesian right-handed coordinate system of the unit cell.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="2">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_hkl"/>
                    <dim index="2" value="6"/>
                </dimensions>
            </field>
        </group>
        <field name="status" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                Which return value did the indexing algorithm yield for each scan point.
                
                * 0 - Not analyzed
                * 1 - Too high angular deviation
                * 2 - No solution
                * 100 - Success
                * 255 - Unexpected errors
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_sc"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="phases_per_scan_point" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                How many phases i.e. crystal structure models were used to index each
                scan point if any? Let's assume an example to explain how this field
                should be used: In the simplest case users collected one pattern for
                each scan point and have indexed using one phase, i.e. one instance
                of an :ref:`NXunit_cell`.
                
                In another example users may have skipped some scan points (not indexed
                them at all) or used differing numbers of phases for indexing different scan points.
                
                The cumulated of this array decodes how phase_id and matching_phase
                arrays have to be interpreted. In the simplest case (one pattern per scan
                point, and all scan points indexed using that same single phase model),
                phase_id has as many entries as scan points
                and matching_phase has also as many entries as scan points.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_sc"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="phase_id" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                The array phases_per_scan_point details how the phase_id
                and the matching_phase arrays have to be interpreted.
                
                For the example of a single-phase material phase_id has trivial
                values either 0 (no solution) or 1 (solution matching
                sufficiently significant with the model for phase1, an instance of :ref:`NXphase`).
                
                For the example of multi-phase material, it is possible (although not frequently
                required) that a pattern agrees significantly with multiple patterns. Examples are
                cases of pseudosymmetry, insufficiently precise and accurate calibrated systems,
                or usage of inaccurate phase models. Having such field is especially relevant
                for recent dictionary- or artificial intelligence-based indexing methods to communicate
                the results in a model-agnostic way in combination with matching_phase.
                
                Depending on the phases_per_scan_point value, phase_id and
                matching_phase arrays represent a collection of concatenated tuples.
                These are organized in sequence: The solutions for the 0-th scan point,
                the 1-th scan point, the n_sc - 1 th scan point and omitting tuples
                for those scan points with no phases according to phases_per_scan_point.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_solutions"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="matching_phase" type="NX_INT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                One-dimensional array, pattern-by-pattern labelling the solutions found.
                The array phases_per_scan_point has to be specified because it details
                how the phase_id and the matching_phase arrays are interpreted.
                See documentation of phase_id for further details.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="n_solutions"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="matching_phase_descriptor" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Phase_matching is a descriptor for how well the solution matches or not.
                Examples can be confidence_index, mean_angular_deviation, or other.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="confidence_index"/>
                <item value="mean_angular_deviation"/>
                <item value="other"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <group name="rotation" type="NXrotations"/>
        <field name="scan_point_positions" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                Calibrated center positions of each scan point
                in the sample surface reference system.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="2">
                <dim index="1" value="n_sc"/>
                <dim index="2" value="2"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
        <field name="indexing_rate" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_DIMENSIONLESS">
            <doc>
                Fraction of successfully indexed patterns with a phase
                not the null-phase vs the number_of_scan_points.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="number_of_scan_points" type="NX_UINT" units="NX_UNITLESS">
            <doc>
                Number of scan points in the original mapping.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="pixel_shape" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                The shape of the polygon or polyhedron that was used for the tiling
                respectively tessellation of the region-of-interest into scan points.
            </doc>
            <enumeration>
                <item value="square"/>
                <item value="hexagon"/>
                <item value="cube"/>
                <item value="other"/>
            </enumeration>
        </field>
        <group name="roi" type="NXdata">
            <doc>
                An overview of the entire ROI.
            </doc>
            <field name="descriptor" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                    Descriptor representing the image contrast.
                </doc>
                <enumeration>
                    <item value="band_contrast"/>
                    <item value="confidence_index"/>
                    <item value="mean_angular_deviation"/>
                </enumeration>
            </field>
            <field name="title" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                    Title of the default plot.
                </doc>
            </field>
            <field name="data" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_UNITLESS">
                <doc>
                    Descriptor values displaying the ROI.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="2">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_y"/>
                    <dim index="2" value="n_x"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="long_name" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                        Descriptor values
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
            <field name="axis_y" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                    Calibrated coordinate along the y-axis.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_y"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="long_name" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                        Label for the y axis
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
            <field name="axis_x" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
                <doc>
                    Calibrated coordinate along the x-axis.
                </doc>
                <dimensions rank="1">
                    <dim index="1" value="n_x"/>
                </dimensions>
                <attribute name="long_name" type="NX_CHAR">
                    <doc>
                        Label for the x axis
                    </doc>
                </attribute>
            </field>
        </group>
    </group>
</definition>
