<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<definition category="base" extends="NXobject" name="NXfib" type="group" xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
	<doc>Draft of a base class for describing focused-ion beam capabilities of an instrument. The class is designed to be used as an additional component of e.g. an electron microscope to describe sample/specimen preparation and the collecting of data and metadata for (scanning) electron microscope/focused-ion beam, (S)EM/FIB instruments.</doc>
	<field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Given name.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="model" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Given brand or model name by the manufacturer.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="serial_number" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Given hardware name/serial number or hash identifier issued by the manufacturer.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="manufacturer_name" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Given name of the manufacturer.</doc>
	</field>
	<field name="description" type="NX_CHAR">
		<doc>Ideally a reference to persistent documentation which specifies further details for the device. If this is not available, add a free-text description to deliver further details about the focused-ion unit.</doc>
	</field>
	<group name="ion_gun" type="NXsource">
		<field name="ion_source" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>The type of source which creates the ion beam.</doc>
			<enumeration>
				<item value="liquid-metal"/>
				<item value="plasma"/>
				<item value="gas-field"/>
			</enumeration>
		</field>
		<field name="ionized_species" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>Which ionized elements or molecule are ionized to form the beam that sputters material. Examples a gallium, helium, neon, argon, krypton, or xenon, O2+.</doc>
		</field>
		<field name="brightness" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
			<doc>Average/nominal (discuss further with colleagues) brightness of the ion beam (at which location?).</doc>
		</field>
		<field name="flux" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_FLUX">
			<doc>Ion flux</doc>
		</field>
		<field name="current" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_CURRENT">
			<doc>Charge current</doc>
		</field>
		<field name="voltage" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_VOLTAGE">
			<doc>Ion acceleration voltage upon source exit and entering the vacuum flight path.</doc>
		</field>
		<field name="ion_energy_profile" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ENERGY">
			<doc>Needs further discussion with colleagues how this should be defined.</doc>
		</field>
	</group>
	<group type="NXtransformation">
		<doc>A right-handed Cartesian coordinate system is used whose positive z-axis points in the direction of the ion beam, i.e. towards the sample. For modelling ion milling it is relevant to document the illumination vector. NXtransformations offers a place to store how the ion gun coordinate system has to be rotated to align its positive z-axis with the positive z-axis of e.g. the electron beam and ion beam respectively.</doc>
	</group>
	<group type="NXlens_em"/>
	<group type="NXaperture"/>
</definition>
