<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
#
# Copyright (C) 2023-2025 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
#
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" type="group" name="NXinstrument_em" extends="NXinstrument" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
        Base class for instrument-related details of a real or simulated electron microscope.
        
        For collecting data and experiments which are simulations of an electron
        microscope (or such session) use the :ref:`NXem` application definition and
        the :ref:`NXevent_data_em` groups it provides.
        
        This base class implements the concept of :ref:`NXem` whereby (meta)data are distinguished
        whether these typically change during a session (dynamic) or not (static metadata).
        This design allows to store e.g. hardware related concepts only once instead of demanding
        that each image or spectrum from the session needs to be stored also with the static metadata.
    </doc>
    <field name="name" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
            Given name of the microscope at the hosting institution.
            This is an alias. Examples could be NionHermes, Titan, JEOL,
            Gemini, etc.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="location" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
            Location of the lab or place where the instrument is installed.
            Using GEOREF is preferred.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="type" type="NX_CHAR" recommended="true">
        <doc>
            Different types of electron microscopes exist:
            
            * sem, a scanning electron microscope without focused-ion beam capabilities
            * fib, a scanning electron microscope with focused-ion beam capabilities
              irrespective whether these were used or not
            * tem, a transmission electron microscope
            
            NXem is one joint data model that can be used to document research that is performed
            with several of these types of microscopes (SEM, TEM, or FIB). The NXem data model
            stresses that these types of instruments despite having several differences are still all
            electron beamlines with which to probe electron and/or ion matter interaction and in fact
            in practice have many similarities in how they are used, the components, they contain, etc.
            
            This field can be used in research data management systems for enabling a categorization
            or tagging of experiments without having to analyze if groups like NXibeam_column are present
            (which would indicate type is fib) or if certain lens configurations or instrument models are used
            which suggests the microscope is a scanning (sem) or transmission electron microscope (tem):
        </doc>
        <enumeration>
            <item value="sem"/>
            <item value="fib"/>
            <item value="tem"/>
        </enumeration>
    </field>
    <group type="NXfabrication"/>
    <group type="NXebeam_column"/>
    <group type="NXibeam_column"/>
    <!--(NXpbeam_column) for adding laser pulsing capabilities (NXsource + x)-->
    <group type="NXoptical_system_em"/>
    <group type="NXdetector">
        <doc>
            Description of the type of the detector.
            
            Electron microscopes have typically multiple detectors.
            Different technologies are in use like CCD, scintillator,
            direct electron, CMOS, or image plate to name but a few.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group name="stageID" type="NXmanipulator">
        <doc>
            Stages in an electron microscope are multi-functional devices.
            
            Stages enable experimentalists the application of controlled external stimuli
            on the specimen. Modern stages realize a hierarchy of components.
            A multi-axial tilt rotation holder is a good example where the control of
            each degree of freedom is technically implemented via providing instances
            of e.g. :ref:`NXpositioner` or :ref:`NXactuator` that achieve the rotating
            and positioning of the specimen.
            
            The physical process of mounting a specimen on a stage in practice often
            comes with an own hierarchy of fixtures to bridge e.g. length scales technically.
            An example from atom probe microscopy is that researchers may work
            with wire samples which are clipped into a larger fixing unit to enable
            careful specimen handling. Alternatively, a microtip is a silicon post
            upon which e.g. an atom probe specimen is mounted. Multiple of such microtips
            are then grouped into a microtip array to conveniently enable loading of multiple
            specimens into the instrument with fewer operations. There are further scenarios
            typically encountered related to mounting and locating specimens inside an
            electron microscope, a few examples follow:
            
            * A nanoparticle on a copper grid. The copper grid is the holder.
              This grid itself is fixed to a stage.
            * An atom probe specimen fixed in a stub. In this case the stub can be
              considered the holder, while the cryostat temperature control unit is
              a component of the stage.
            * For in-situ experiments with e.g. chips with read-out electronics
              as actuators, the chips are again placed in a larger unit. A typical
              example are in-situ experiments using e.g. the tools of `Protochips &lt;https://www.protochips.com&gt;`_.
            * Other examples are (quasi) in-situ experiments where experimentalists
              anneal or deform the specimen via e.g. in-situ tensile testing machines
              which are mounted on the specimen holder.
            
            For specific details and inspiration about stages in electron microscopes:
            
            * `Holders with multiple axes &lt;https://www.nanotechnik.com/e5as.html&gt;`_
            * `Chip-based designs &lt;https://www.protochips.com/products/fusion/fusion-select-components/&gt;`_
            * `Further chip-based designs &lt;https://www.nanoprobetech.com/about&gt;`_
            * `Stages in transmission electron microscopy &lt;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-662-14824-2&gt;`_ (page 103, table 4.2)
            * `Further stages in transmission electron microscopy &lt;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4757-2519-3&gt;`_ (page 124ff)
            * `Specimens in atom probe &lt;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4614-8721-0&gt;`_ (page 47ff)
            * `Exemplar micro-manipulators &lt;https://nano.oxinst.com/products/omniprobe/omniprobe-200&gt;`_
        </doc>
        <!--see for complicated positioning tools like an eucentric five-axis table stage in an SEM
https://www.nanotechnik.com/e5as.html-->
        <field name="design" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Principal design of the stage.
                
                Exemplar terms could be side_entry, top_entry,
                single_tilt, quick_change, multiple_specimen,
                bulk_specimen, double_tilt, tilt_rotate,
                heating_chip, atmosphere_chip,
                electrical_biasing_chip, liquid_cell_chip
            </doc>
        </field>
        <field name="alias" type="NX_CHAR">
            <doc>
                Free-text field to give a term how that a stage_lab at this level of the
                stage_lab hierarchy is commonly referred to. Examples could be stub,
                puck, carousel, microtip, clip, holder, etc.
            </doc>
        </field>
        <!--the pragmatic view for the majority of published datasets and EM images
only tilt and position values are reported but the coordinate systems and conventions
used in which these were defined are often not reported in the associated scientific publications
this can be interpreted as that position values and tilts are only meaningful for those users
in a particular narrow community which work with that particular microscope-->
        <field name="tilt1" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANGLE">
            <doc>
                The interpretation of this tilt1 value can be contextualized via the comment
                attribute. However, it is better to describe the reference frame in which the
                tilt is defined explicitly using instances of :ref:`NXtransformations` and
                respective instances of :ref:`NXcoordinate_system`. Especially when this
                NXinstrument_em base class is used in an application definition like NXem.
            </doc>
            <attribute name="comment" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                    Discouraged free-text field to provide details about how to interpret tilt1.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="tilt2" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANGLE">
            <doc>
                The interpretation of this tilt2 value can be contextualized via the comment
                attribute. However, it is better to describe the reference frame in which the
                tilt is defined explicitly using instances of :ref:`NXtransformations` and
                respective instances of :ref:`NXcoordinate_system`. Especially when this
                NXinstrument_em base class is used in an application definition like NXem.
            </doc>
            <attribute name="comment" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                    Discouraged free-text field to provide details about how to interpret tilt2.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="rotation" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_ANGLE">
            <doc>
                The interpretation of this rotation value can be contextualized via the comment
                attribute. However, it is better to describe the reference frame in which the
                rotation is defined explicitly using instances of :ref:`NXtransformations` and
                respective instances of :ref:`NXcoordinate_system`. Especially when this
                NXinstrument_em base class is used in an application definition like NXem.
            </doc>
            <attribute name="comment" type="NX_CHAR">
                <doc>
                    Discouraged free-text field to provide details about how to interpret rotation.
                </doc>
            </attribute>
        </field>
        <field name="position" type="NX_NUMBER" units="NX_LENGTH">
            <doc>
                The interpretation of these position values can be contextualized via the comment
                attribute. However, it is better to describe the reference frame in which the
                position values are defined explicitly using instances of :ref:`NXtransformations`
                and respective instances of :ref:`NXcoordinate_system`. Especially when this
                NXinstrument_em base class is used in an application definition like NXem.
            </doc>
            <dimensions rank="1">
                <dim index="1" value="3"/>
            </dimensions>
        </field>
    </group>
    <group name="nanoprobeID" type="NXmanipulator">
        <doc>
            In contrast to the stage, the nanoprobe is an additional manipulator that is a specifically
            frequently found component of FIB/SEM instruments. A nanoprobe is used to pick up and
            relocated portions of the specimen that have been cut off during site-specific lift-outs
            and specimen preparation.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group name="gas_injector" type="NXcomponent">
        <doc>
            Gas injection systems (GIS) are components of microscopes that are equipped with focused-ion beam
            capabilities. The component is used to introduce reactive neutral gases to the sample surface for
            enhanced etching, preferential etching, or material deposition.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <group type="NXpump"/>
    <group type="NXsensor"/>
    <group type="NXactuator"/>
</definition>
