<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl" ?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2008-2025 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" category="base"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd"
	name="NXobject" 
	type="group">
	<doc>
        This is the base object of NeXus. The groups and fields contained 
        within this file are allowed to be present in any derived base class.

        If nameType="partial", the placeholders (e.g., FIELDNAME or GROUPNAME)
        can be replaced by the name of any object (field or group, 
        respectively) that exists within the same group.
	</doc>
    <group type="NXcollection" minOccurs="0" />
    <group type="NXdata" minOccurs="0" />
    <group type="NXlog" minOccurs="0" />
    <group type="NXnote" minOccurs="0" />
    <group type="NXparameters" minOccurs="0" />
    <group name="GROUPNAME_log" type="NXlog" nameType="partial" minOccurs="0">
        <doc>
            NXlog group containing logged values of GROUPNAME.
        </doc>
    </group>
    <field name="FIELDNAME_set" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" minOccurs="0">
        <doc>
            Target values of FIELDNAME. 
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="FIELDNAME_errors" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" minOccurs="0">
        <doc>
            Uncertainties of FIELDNAME values.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="FIELDNAME_weights" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="partial" minOccurs="0">
        <doc>
            Weights of FIELDNAME values.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="FIELDNAME_mask" type="NX_BOOLEAN" nameType="partial" minOccurs="0">
        <doc>
            Boolean mask of FIELDNAME values. The value is masked if set to 1.
        </doc>
    </field>
	<field name="identifierNAME" type="NX_CHAR" nameType="partial">
		<doc>
			An identifier for a (persistent) resource.

			An identifier, provided by some authority, that has been assigned to an
			object described by this ``NXobject``. To be useful, the identifier
			must not be reassigned to a different real-world object. It is typical for
			there to be some mechanism to resolve an identifier, obtaining metadata
			about the object. Identifiers for which some guarantees exist regarding
			this resolution process are called persistent identifiers.
			Persistent identifiers are also known as PIDs.
		</doc>
		<attribute name="type" type="NX_CHAR">
			<doc>
				The type of identifier used.

				It is recommended to use the most specific type when describing the identifier.
				
				For example, all IGSNs (see below) are DOIs and all DOIs are Handles; however, an IGSN should have type IGSN (and not DOI or Hdl).
				Similarly, an ARK, Purl, ORCID and ROR identifiers should have their corresponding types and should not use the more generic URL identifier.
			</doc>
			<enumeration open="true">
				<item value="ARK">
					<doc>
						Archival Resource Key.
						
						An ARK is a Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) designed to support long-term access to a variety of information objects.
						
						Syntax: https://NMA/ark:/NAAN/Name[Qualifier]. Brackets indicate optional elements.
						Example: https://example.org/ark:/12345/abcde
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="DOI">
					<doc>
						Digital Object Identifier.
						
						A DOI is a unique alphanumeric string used to identify digital content. It consists of a prefix and a suffix, separated by a slash.
						
						Syntax: 10.XXXX/XXXXXX
						Example: 10.1107/S1600576714027575
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="Hdl">
					<doc>
						A handle is a unique identifier that consists of a prefix indicating the naming authority and a suffix representing the local name 
						of a resource.
						
						A handle is a unique identifier used to facilitate the identification and management of digital objects. It is composed of a prefix that 
						indicates the naming authority and a suffix that specifies the resource's local name. 
						
						This refers specifically to an ID in the Handle system operated by the Corporation for National Research Initiatives (CNRI).
						
						Syntax: prefix/identifier
						Example: 123456789/abc123
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="IGSN">
					<doc>
						International Generic Sample Number.
						
						The IGSN is a unique identifier assigned to a specific sample or specimen in the context of scientific research.

						Since 2021, IGSNs are issued by DataCite, meaning that there are now DataCite-issued DOIs for all IGSNs, 
						including those historical IGSNs issued beforehand. Therefore, the syntax is the same as for DOIs.
						
						Syntax: 10.XXXX/XXXXXX
						Example: 10.1107/S1600576714027575
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="ISNI">
					<doc>
						ISNI is an ISO standard to uniquely identify individuals and organizations involved in creative work, including pseudonyms
						and other public personas.
						
						An ISNI-ID is made up of 16 digits, the last character being a check character. The check character may be either a decimal digit
						or the character “X”.
						
						A URL can be generated from the ISNI ID by combining it with the prefix https://isni.org/isni/, resulting in
						https://isni.org/isni/{ISNI-ID}.
						
						Syntax: 16 base-10 digits stored without any spaces.
						Example: 0000000121032683
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="ISSN">
					<doc>
						International Standard Serial Number
						
						An ISSN is an 8-digit unique identifier used to distinguish a serial publication, whether in print or electronic form.
						The last character (a digit or 'X') serves as a check character, making the ISSN uniquely defined by its first seven digits.
						
						Syntax: NNNN-NNNC, where N a decimal digit character (i.e., in the set {0,1,2,...,9}), and C is in {0,1,2,...,9,X}
						Example: 1234-5678 or 1234-567X
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="ISSN-L">
					<doc>
						Linking ISSN
						
						The linking ISSN, or ISSN-L, is a specific ISSN that groups the different media of the same serial publication.
						
						Syntax: NNNN-NNNC, where N a decimal digit character (i.e., in the set {0,1,2,...,9}), and C is in {0,1,2,...,9,X}
						Example: 1234-5678 or 1234-567X
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="ORCID">
					<doc>
						Open Researcher and Contributor identifier.
						
						ORCID provides a free and persistent identifier that uniquely distinguishes authors and contributors in scientific research.
						
						Syntax: https://orcid.org/XXXX-XXXX-XXXX-XXXX
						Example: https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1825-0097
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="PURL">
					<doc>
						Persistent Uniform Resource Locator.
						
						A Persistent Uniform Resource Locator (PURL) is a type of URL designed to provide a stable, long-term reference to a web 
						resource by using a resolver to redirect users to the resource's current location, even if it moves over time.
						
						A PURL has three parts: (1) a protocol, (2) a resolver address, and (3) a name.
						
						Syntax: https://purl.org/foo/bar
						Example: https://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/title
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="ROR">
					<doc>
						Research Organization Registry
						
						A ROR ID is a globally unique identifier for research organizations, enabling unambiguous linking of institutions across systems.
						
						Syntax: https://ror.org/{ROR-ID}
						Example: https://ror.org/052gg0110
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="URL">
					<doc>
						Uniform Resource Locator
						
						Also known as web address, a URL is the address used to access a resource on the internet, 
						specifying its location and the protocol to retrieve it.
						
						Syntax: scheme://domain:port/path?query_string#fragment_id
						Example: https://www.example.com/about
					</doc>
				</item>
				<item value="URN">
					<doc>
						Uniform Resource Name
						
						A URN is a unique, persistent identifier for a resource regardless of where it is stored.

						It is recommended that identifiers with more specific type attribute (such as DOI or ISSN) values should not be stored as a URN,
						even when this is valid. As an example, the URN doi:10.1107/S1600576714027575 is a valid URN-based representation for the DOI
						10.1107/S1600576714027575, but it is recommended to use type="DOI" in this case.
						
						Syntax: urn:&lt;namespace&gt;:&lt;namespace-specific-string&gt;. The leading urn: sequence is case-insensitive.
						Example: urn:isbn:0000000000000
					</doc>
				</item>
			</enumeration>
		</attribute>
	</field>
	<attribute name="default">
        <doc>
			.. index:: plotting

			Declares which child group contains a path leading
			to a :ref:`NXdata` group or a group using a base class
			extending :ref:`NXdata`.

			It is recommended (as of NIAC2014) to use this attribute
			to help define the path to the default dataset to be plotted.
			See https://www.nexusformat.org/2014_How_to_find_default_data.html
			for a summary of the discussion.
        </doc>
    </attribute>
</definition>
