<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="nxdlformat.xsl"?>
<!--
# NeXus - Neutron and X-ray Common Data Format
# 
# Copyright (C) 2014-2024 NeXus International Advisory Committee (NIAC)
# 
# This library is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
# modify it under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either
# version 3 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.
#
# This library is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
# but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
# MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
# Lesser General Public License for more details.
#
# You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
# License along with this library; if not, write to the Free Software
# Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307  USA
#
# For further information, see http://www.nexusformat.org
-->
<definition xmlns="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" category="base" name="NXpid_controller" extends="NXcomponent" type="group" xsi:schemaLocation="http://definition.nexusformat.org/nxdl/3.1 ../nxdl.xsd">
    <doc>
        A description of a feedback system in terms of the settings of a proportional-integral-derivative (PID) controller.
         
        Automated control of a physical quantity is often achieved by connecting the output of a sensor to an actuator
        (e.g. using a thermocouple to monitor the effect of a heater and influence the power provided to it). The physical
        quantity being operated on is typically referred to as the "Process Variable", with the desired value being the 
        "Setpoint" (which may vary as a function of time) and the "Error Value" is the time-varying function of the difference 
        between the Setpoint value and the concurrent measurement of the Process Variable  (Error Value = Setpoint - Process Variable).
         
        A PID controller calculates an output value for use as an input signal to an actuator via the weighted sum of four terms:
        * Proportional: the current Error Value
        * Integral: the integral of the Error Value function
        * Derivative: the first derivative of the Error Value function
        * Feed Forward: A model of the physical system (optional)
        
        The weightings of these terms are given by the corresponding constants:
        * K_p
        * K_i
        * K_d
        * K_ff
         
        A classic PID controller only implements the P, I and D terms and the values of the K_p, K_i and K_d constants are sufficient to fully
        describe the behaviour of the feedback system implemented by such a PID controller. The inclusion of a Feed Forward term in a feedback system
        is a modern adaptation that aids optimisation of the automated control. It is not present in all PID controllers, but it is also not uncommon.
         
        Note that the ``NXpid_controller`` is designed to be a child object of the actuator that its output is connected to. The parent object
        representing the actuator is likely to be represented by an ``NXactuator`` or ``NXpositioner`` base class, but there is a wide variety
        of possible applications for PID controllers.
    </doc>
    <field name="description">
        <doc>
            Description of how the Process Value for the PID controller is produced by sensor(s) in the setup.
             
            For example, a set of sensors could be averaged over before feeding it back into the loop.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <group name="pv_sensor" type="NXsensor">
        <doc>
            The sensor representing the Process Value used in the feedback loop for the PID.
             
            In case multiple sensors were used, this NXsensor should contain the proper calculated/aggregated value.
        </doc>
        <group name="value_log" type="NXlog">
            <field name="value" type="NX_NUMBER">
                <doc>
                     The actual timeseries data fed back into the PID controller.
                </doc>
            </field>
        </group>
    </group>
    <field name="setpoint" type="NX_FLOAT" units="NX_ANY">
        <doc>
            The Setpoint(s) used as an input for the PID controller.
             
            It can also be a link to an ``NXsensor.value`` field.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="K_p" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="specified">
        <doc>
            Proportional gain constant. This constant determines how strongly the output value
            directly follows the current Error Value. When this constant dominates, the output
            value is linearly proportional to the Error Value.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="K_i" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="specified">
        <doc>
            Integral gain constant. This constant determines how strongly the output value
            should react to an accumulated offset in the Error Value that should have
            been corrected previously. since the integral term is proportional to both
            the magnitude and persistence of the Error Value over time.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="K_d" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="specified">
        <doc>
            Derivative gain constant. This constant determines how much the feedback system
            should anticipate the future value of the Error Value function through adjustment of the 
            output value that is proportional to the rate of change (i.e. derivative) of the Error Value.
            This term is important for damping oscillations in the feedback system.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="K_ff" type="NX_NUMBER" nameType="specified">
        <doc>
            Feed Forward gain constant. This constant determines how much the feedback system
            should rely on a calculated output value to achieve the desired Process Variable value.
            A Feed Forward system uses a model of the physical system to calculate an appropriate 
            output value to achieve a desired Setpoint value. A description of this model should be provided
            in the ``feed_forward_model`` field.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="feed_forward_model" type="NX_CHAR">
        <doc>
            A description of the model used for the Feed Forward part of the feedback system. Note that such models typically
            involve the Setpoint value, but not the Error Value. The simplest model is simply proportional to the Setpoint value.
            For example, the position (Process Variable) of a sample is measured by a a linear optical encoder (sensor) and 
            manipulated by a piezoelectric scanning stage (actuator). The corresponding Feed Forward model could be that the 
            output value (voltage applied to the piezo) is proportional to the Setpoint value (measured position of the sample).
             
            A complex model could involve any number of input variables, mathematical functions, and coefficients in order to
            describe the physical system relevant to the PID controller.
        </doc>
    </field>
    <field name="control_action">
        <doc>
            The Error Value of PID feedback system is normally constructed in terms of the correction needed to bring
            the Process Variable towards a match with the Setpoint. This "direct" control action means that a measurement of
            the Process Variable that is lower than the Setpoint results in a positive Error Value and a generally positive 
            control output that tells the actuator to push the value of the Process Variable upwards. In some implementations,
            the actuator will respond to a more positive control output by pushing the Process Variable towards lower values (e.g. 
            a Peltier cooler) and so the output of the feedback system must be reversed to match the behaviour of the physical system.
            A feedback system may also be implemented with reverse action in order to ensure that failures (e.g. disconnected sensor
            output or actuator input) result in a safe state (e.g. a valve should be left open to release pressure).
        </doc>
        <enumeration>
            <item value="direct" />
            <item value="reverse" />
        </enumeration>
    </field>
</definition>
